Targets of Opportunity

Quest Completed: Fleshsmith - Pendleham will have to find a new moniker, because it is the City of Flesh no more. What will replace it is unclear, but with time, some sense of normalcy will set in, and a new member polity might find entrance to the Empire of Common Cause.

Quest Progress: Slayer of Horrors (1/12)

Grak and I returned from the fleshsmith exclusion zone four days after we’d touched down there. I’d been a little disappointed with the whole thing: it was clearly a side quest, something that didn’t have all that much impact on the greater story. I’d been hoping that it would tie back in with the main quest somehow, or give me some kind of power up, but the actual benefits of being there were rather marginal, with just a few upgrades to my physical body thanks to a sympathetic group of resistance fighters, which was a whole thing. I didn’t even have a level to show for it, though that made sense, because with gold magic active, it had been a bit of a cakewalk.

I was glad that I hadn’t taken anyone but Grak, mostly because things got serious enough for me to unleash the full power of gold magic. Back when we’d been wee little adventurers in Barren Jewel, I had been pretty worried about Aumann, because he could fire off little bits of metal as fast as bullets, so many of them so fast that his only issue would be aiming a hose of metal and running out of ammo (and to be fair, the latter was a serious consideration).

I could fire off metal balls fast enough that they would tear themselves apart inches from my skin as they hit a solid wall of air. I’d sat down for a day and done some engineering work to try to make a long barrel that would allow rifling and spin bullet-shaped projectiles that had some aerodynamics to them, but even once I’d built a contraption that I could mount on my hand, I still couldn’t shoot as fast as I was physically capable of, given some insurmountable problems. In theory, with the right setup, I might even have been able to punch through dragonhide with the bullets, but it would take a lot of precision engineering and materials science, some of which was beyond what was feasible for me, which was a shame.

In a combat encounter, especially one that was taking place at relatively close range, I could cut loose and not give a shit about the fact that my projectiles couldn’t handle the stress of being fired, nor that velocity fell off sharply with distance. In a few of the fights, I would just grab whatever was nearby and blast it at the people around us, putting my full power on display. Once, I did a blood attack, spraying my blood around a room and then using the blood as a conduit for gold magic, tearing apart a building in the process and killing everyone but Grak and myself.

The fleshsmiths were, for the most part, not actually that bad. If all of the Thirteen Horrors were meant to be some kind of reflection of me, then the fleshsmiths probably had something to say about my relationship with my body. I was a transhumanist, and one of the things that had always attracted me about transhumanism was the idea that I was my own self, a person that happened to run on meat rather than silicon, though that was something that might some day change. The lesson of the fleshsmiths, if there was one, was that bodies weren’t just some inert, neutral hardware that the mind ran on, they were part and parcel of thinking and being itself. As lessons went, it wasn’t something that I thought that I needed, which made it hard to decide whether or not it actually was a lesson.

Maybe I had always felt a little uncomfortable in my own skin, in ways that were kind of normal, and maybe the transhumanist stuff was a way of saying ‘fuck that noise’ when it came to bodies. I hated getting acne, or scabs on my knees, or little scars that didn’t look cool or have a good story to them. There was a lot of upkeep that I didn’t particularly enjoy, things like cutting hair, cutting nails, shaving, brushing teeth, body stuff that you couldn’t just stop doing, but which I didn’t imagine anyone really enjoyed, except that there were weirdos out there. My stance on bodies was basically my stance on a lot of things, which was that it was a shame that we didn’t have a better way of doing things, and as soon as we did, I would be on board.

There were pustule mages there, which I’d have expected even if I’d been going in blind, rather than with a full dossier from Uniquities. On a purely mechanical level, pustule magic worked well with bodily manipulation, and on a thematic level, they were both variations on body horror and ugly biological reality. Pustule mages had come to me during a bad case of acne, I was pretty sure, and as such, represented one aspect of the general idea that Pendleham seemed to be pointing at.

The whole thing would have probably landed a bit better if my PHY hadn’t been so high. I was in better shape than I had ever been in my life, probably better shape than I would ever have been able to get in on Earth unless I fully devoted myself to strength training, bodybuilding, cardio, and a whole bunch of other stuff. There were, I was assuming, some fringe benefits of high END that changed a few things about how my body fundamentally regulated itself, because there were a lot of things that I just didn’t really need to think about anymore, like the aforementioned acne, the common cold, ingrown hairs, dry skin, and all kinds of other things. Given a few days (or a swing of Grak’s axe) I could have had a full beard, rather than something wispy and disappointing. My body had given me almost no trouble, and because of that, there was a bit of a disconnect when I looked at the fleshsmiths, and what I thought they were trying to ‘say’.

“There’s not really anything worth recounting,” I said. I looked at Grak for confirmation. “Right? I mean, no major clues that I missed?”

“They suggested that we go to a place called Sulid Isle to speak with an elf named Fallatehr,” said Grak.

“I’m starting to think that’s less in the way of bread crumbs leading back to something important and more a running joke,” I said.

“There were other bread crumbs,” said Grak. “There were hints that the secrets of their craft originated at a library that contained the knowledge of alternate futures. We also met a man who claimed to be dream skewered.”

“Which he wasn’t,” I said quickly. “He was, however, quite off his rocker. He had a very detailed fanfic version of Earth which bore pretty much no resemblance to the real thing. I made a few notes about his rambling, if anyone wants to look, and I’m sure that he would talk to you, but I don’t think that there was really a point to him.”

“He had his own troubled life,” said Grak.

“And was a powerful pustule mage,” I said. “But other than that, nothing much to report.”

“That’s good,” said Amaryllis, though there was a note of caution in her voice. She believed me, I was sure, but she wasn’t so sloppy that she would take it all at face value.

“Second generation of tuung should be done now, right?” I asked.

“It is,” said Amaryllis. “So far as I’ve been able to tell, it was a complete success. I need some time in the chamber myself in order to get a handle on the reports that were generated, but that’s all afterbirth, and at the moment, almost all my effort is going into coordination. In theory, we’re a week away from a kind of new normal.”

“The Captain’s been behaving?” I asked.

“So far,” replied Amaryllis. “If we didn’t have Valencia … well, we do have her, and she’s been a godsend.” I was fairly sure that she meant that literally. “She’s ferreted out the other backups, and we discovered the mechanism for their creation, which is thankfully intensive and visible. Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle is in the dark for the time being, which should make it easier to handle him. There was a bit of a heated discussion between the two of us, but I’m sure she’ll talk to you more about it, and I don’t want to prejudice you.”

“Heated discussion about him?” I asked, raising an eyebrow.

“No, lower stakes than that,” said Amaryllis. “About his non-anima. But again, I just want you to be aware, because she’ll bring it up, and I don’t want to treat it as a non-issue.”

“Okay,” I said. “I guess I’ll hear more about that later. And all the other balls you’re juggling?”

“You’d have heard about it if it were urgent, or even particularly important,” said Amaryllis. “Poran is secure, Anglecynn is secure, and the dragons are laying low. Very little rumblings from the hells, both from the imperial reports and our usual sources. As I believe I predicted, we’ve seen two separate incidents where major soul mages were uncovered, but both were fairly minor in the scheme of things, neither the kind of far-reaching conspiracy that would have caused some real international ripples.”

“So what you’re saying is that I can be gone for a handful of days and the world will be fine?” I asked. “Sounds good to me. That might mean that there’s time to bang out a few of these other quests, right? We’re netting a ton of money off closing the exclusion in Pendleham.” Flesh magic had been removed from everyone there, though a good number of them had been left alive, and many people who lived in the zone hadn’t been practitioners.

“We’re netting money, which is going to be translated to gold,” said Amaryllis. “So in essence, we’re netting almost nothing but the good that’s done by closing the exclusions, which is arguable depending on the case. How has the call of the gold been?”

“Fine,” I said. “No direct input for pretty much the whole period, actually, which was a little weird, but I still have the power and I was in the middle of accomplishing a goal that it had set for me.” Based on past records of how things went for gold mages, it would probably get less reasonable over time, asking more of me. In theory, we were still in the honeymoon phase. I hadn’t been pushed too hard, aside from the demand to fly to the moon to stash gold.

“Juniper is of the opinion that we should make a run at Fel Seed as soon as possible,” said Grak.

“And depend on the gold magic?” asked Amaryllis. “That’s dangerous.”

“We wouldn’t actually be making a run at Fel Seed,” I said. “We’d be trying our best to sidle past him without a confrontation. You were working on mapping the zone, right?”

“It’s been done,” said Amaryllis. “But I don’t see a way we could possibly accomplish anything aside from our deaths in Fel Seed’s zone unless we have Bethel.”

“Ah,” I said. “How has she, uh, been? You’ve talked?”

“She’s making the right noises,” said Amaryllis. “It’s apparent that Valencia has been putting in some work.” She frowned. “I have my concerns, but they’re rooted in the past, not in the present. The risk of future interpersonal problems seems low, but I can’t be confident that she’s as stable as I would like her to be, especially not in a combat situation. And then there’s the matter of how you feel.”

“If we were on Earth, and this was all mundane, I would give it more time, and I certainly wouldn’t put myself in a situation where we had to interact, let alone trust each other,” I said. “Given the circumstances, I think that I need to race through my misgivings and get this done.”

“I want Valencia there when you meet, and probably as much as possible after that,” said Amaryllis.

“It’s foolish,” said Grak. “We should wait. There is more to do across Aerb before we finally embark. Another level would be preferable.”

“Grak doesn’t want to die,” I said. “And seems to think that we won’t all make it through Fel Seed’s zone alive.” Grak and I had a lot of time to talk in Pendleham, which was good, in a way, but also a little maddening, because when we disagreed, he could really commit himself to not giving an inch. “It’s unlikely that only one of us would die,” I said. “Much more likely that if something in our defenses fails, it fails for everyone.”

“This is true,” said Grak. “It is also not comforting.”

“We’ll have to game it out ahead of time,” said Amaryllis. “Given Fel Seed’s known capabilities, compared with his suspected capabilities, we can do a risk assessment.”

“And you haven’t already done that?” I asked.

“I have,” Amaryllis replied. “But I’m not so full of myself that I’m willing to state the risks without having first had a consultation with everyone involved. Consider my risk assessment preliminary, if you want to.”

“But it doesn’t matter, because Fel Seed can do anything,” I said. “There would just be some bullshit to justify it.”

“You’ve said that before,” replied Amaryllis. “You can understand how that would be very concerning, right?”

“I think it’s the opposite,” I said. “If there’s always going to be some bullshit, then there’s no amount of power we can attain that will make us safe. Therefore, we shouldn’t worry about trying to stack up as many buffs and abilities as we possibly can.”

It was pretty clear that Amaryllis and Grak didn’t find this terribly convincing, but it was also a conversation that we were better off having in another time and place, with more of the main team present. We moved on to other subjects, namely how things were going in the two halves of Poran.

Ask her what arrangements are in place for the other exclusions.

The command had come from seemingly nowhere, not prompted by anything we were saying, and not at a natural transition point.

“Gold bug wants to know the status of the other exclusions,” I said. “Whether we can get money from them, I’m guessing.”

“Oh,” said Amaryllis. “We have a firmer offer for Celestar, and a much better offer for Rove,” said Amaryllis. “Word of who and what you are is spreading, and I took the liberty of insinuating to the general public that we’re looking at closing down or otherwise solving as many exclusion zones as we can, especially if there’s some material interest in doing so.”

Tell her to give specific amounts.

I sighed. “Not that I personally think you’re avoiding the question, but the call of the gold wants hard numbers.”

“Twenty-five million for Celestar, ten million for Rove,” said Amaryllis. “The former comes through ongoing discussion with the elves, which would probably go better if I felt like I were able to negotiate in terms of in-kind exchanges, rather than just money. The latter comes from direct sale of the rights to whatever can be extracted from Rove’s territory. He as good as swallowed a city and its outlying areas, and it’s speculated that he’s keeping entads and other valuables close to him. In my opinion, it’s an overbid, but the contract was signed yesterday.”

“That’s good, I guess,” I said. “I have to admit, the numbers are so large that they might as well be made up.” Amaryllis was worth somewhere in the neighborhood of a billion obols, so ten million obols would represent a single percent of that. Because so much of that wealth was tied up in money-making enterprises, it was all a little ephemeral. At a certain level of wealth, things became unbearably abstracted, the actual dollar amounts fluid and ever-changing. Gold magic didn’t really care about any of that, except for when that wealth was, in some way, translated into gold.

Tell her to liquidate assets and acquire another twenty pounds of gold. Then kill Rove while she does that.

“Alright,” I said. “Looks like I’m going after Rove. Amaryllis, the call wants another twenty pounds.”

“Fuck,” said Amaryllis. “You just got back.”

“Yeah, but the gains in gold haven’t been realized yet, there’s been nothing for me to mark.”

“I meant in terms of missions,” said Amaryllis. “It’s one of the reasons that we can’t depend on the power against Fel Seed, it’s going to ask for things at bad times.”

“Well I’m fresh and ready to go,” I said. “Pendleham wasn’t the kind of thing that I think I need a week of destressing after. It was gross, but the DFEZ was far worse. And once I’m done with Rove, if he takes me longer than a day, then Bethel should be out of Necrolaborem, and at least that won’t be a pain point.”

Quest Completed: Everything Eater - The corpse he left behind was small, but the crypt is immense and dangerous, a countryside shaped into a messy ball that will remain his tomb for as long as it takes the scavengers to remove everything of worth.

Quest Progress: Slayer of Horrors (2/12)

I didn’t know how one was supposed to go about killing Rove, but the way I did it was to crash right into the enormous mound of junk as fast as I could go without killing myself, while burning a unicorn bone. The first time I died because I was going too fast, and the second and third time I fumbled my way around some enormous internal boulders that were too hard to get through at a reasonable speed. The fourth time I had somewhat of a straight shot to the core though, where I began breaking through layers of wood and the occasional sheet of metal, not actually able to see much of anything except by the light that I was casting. I was flying (or more properly, burrowing) blind, right up until the point when I came within fifty feet of a withered old man’s eyes. It wasn’t that hard to find him, once I could see what he saw, and as soon as I’d crashed through an internal wall of junk, I delivered a decapitating strike, moving fast enough that I accomplished everything right as the unicorn bone was at its limits. His head exploded onto the walls as my fist went through his skull.

I started burning a second one exactly as soon as the first was done, wanting to have extra chances to escape, or to react to whatever shenanigans he had waiting for me. There was nothing though, just his death and my own presence. I spiked and bottled that soul, just as quickly as I could, because without him there, his roving ball of stuff was starting to collapse, its coherence lost.

Rove was a hoarder, I was pretty sure, in addition to taking some inspiration from Katamari. Back before he’d come along, the magic had been one of those sedate and low-powered one, the kind that took too much work and yielded too little for anyone to pursue. D&D was littered with prestige classes that no one took, flavorsome little bits of character and worldbuilding that nevertheless never graced a table; Rove was what you got when someone stuck their fingers in a seam and pulled too hard at it. He’d killed tens of thousands in the initial calamity, and while you could probably have blamed that on an accident, the subsequent deaths could not. Not a lot was known about him, but the dominant thought was that he was simply mentally ill, and the exclusion zone was what you got when someone unwell and focused on accumulation got all that power, all at once.

I felt bad about killing him, especially with profit as the primary motive. I had little doubt that he would have killed me, since that was what he usually did to people who came into his zone, but still, it probably would have been possible to leave him alone.

I did my best to shake off the feeling. Maybe if I’d actually met him, he would have been like Doris Finch, a fatally flawed but relatable and redeemable person. Or maybe he would have been like Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle, someone who just got worse the more you looked at him. It was hard to say, with these people, and even if I did buy that they were a part of me in some way or another, that didn’t mean that they deserved to live.

(I wasn’t a hoarder, back on Earth, unless you counted digital files. There were things that I held onto, and things that I threw away, but I didn’t have huge stacks of anything but gaming books and all the various papers that I’d drawn up for campaign settings or notes. I had a few things that I liked, but I wasn’t wildly sentimental about anything, except maybe after Arthur died, when I was keenly aware that the physical things he’d left behind were all of him that existed in the world. When I’d come to Aerb, I had left everything behind, and while I missed my laptop and phone, it was because they had a bunch of useful functions, not because I was particularly attached to them as earthly goods.)

The whole of Rove’s domain would be excavated by whoever we’d sold the contract to, and the matter of whether or not it was profitable would be essentially irrelevant to us. If there was something valuable to be had in there, like an entad or two that had a high i-factor, we would have to buy it back from whoever it ended up with, but it seemed unlikely to me that there’d be something worth millions.

I felt like I imagined Uther must have felt, solving problems with the application of prodigious amounts of power, strong enough that there were a lot of quests that simply couldn’t stand up to me. Granted, the power was temporary, but I was still kind of hoping that I would be able to make it last through a mad dash into Fel Seed’s territory.

It felt good, but also a little bit rote, like we all knew that this was just what was going to happen before the end. It didn’t even need to happen, not really, because it wasn’t like we were getting all that much in the way of new resources or extra powers. I was hoping that rushing through would level me up, but it seemed like a bit of a long shot, especially when I was crushing people in my path. It was pretty standard for both tabletop games and videogames for enemies to stop giving you benefits when you were too high of level above them.

Quest Completed: A Door Into The Soul - The Gatesmith is dead, but his magic lives on without him, the portals with their infinitely sharp edges making the exclusion zone uninhabitable, except for those whose lives are worth the risk.

Quest Progress: Slayer of Horrors (3/12)

That was another one accomplished over the course of a day. Gatesmith was a problem, because he could step from one end of his domain to another in the blink of an eye, make extremely sharp portals nearly instantly, and could (and did) spy on both the exclusion and what he could see from the edges of it through the use of microportals. Beyond just the portals themselves, he was known to weaponize gravity, putting objects into a vacuum and then accelerating them to ludicrous speeds as a way of firing projectiles up to several miles outside the exclusion zone itself.

Thankfully, there was a trump card when it came to magic, and that trump card's name was warding. Normal wards wouldn’t have helped that much, unless you wanted to try to creep forward with them, for which Gatesmith was likely to find some kind of answer, like drowning you in a sea’s worth of water, or shooting you with hundreds of hypersonic rocks. I had a secret weapon though, and his name was Grak. So long as he was with me, we had portal immunity, which was the only reason that I was willing to make a run at Gatesmith at all.

The second major problem with Gatesmith, as encounters went, was that if he was outclassed, he could simply leave to anywhere else in the exclusion zone. Even if he couldn’t somehow win by thinking with portals, there was nothing that said he had to stick around, or engage with the fight, and given that he had portal surveillance, he could watch and see where intruders were.

The obvious solution was to go in really, really blisteringly fast, so fast that he wouldn’t have a chance to relocate. That left only the problem of finding him the first time, but I knew a couple women named Doris Finch who could pinpoint him fairly easily.

We came crashing down at several thousand miles an hour from straight above, and killed Caldwell Gatesmith on impact. It would have been pretty hard to identify him after the fact, given how pulped he was, but the game dutifully gave me a notification that he’d been defeated, and just after that, marked the quest as done.

“Alright, I want to steal the recipe,” said Reimer.

“Okay, you do that,” I replied. “You have the recipe.”

“Just like that?” asked Reimer.

“Yeah,” I said.

“But isn’t that … I mean, something could go wrong,” he said, frowning.

“I understand your character pretty well, mechanically,” I said. “Did you want me to give it some narration? Belivus goes down to city hall in a disguise, looks up the floor plans that have been filed with the city commissioner’s office, talks to a clerk from the company and finds out the shifts their guards are on, waits until the witching hour, then phases through a wall, molds the steel of the safe, and writes down his own copy of the recipe before putting everything exactly where it was, leaving not even the slightest trace that he was ever there.”

“Not how I would do it,” said Reimer.

“Right, sure,” I said. “But that said, no matter how you decide to do it, as soon as you decided that you were going to do it, it was basically always going to happen. Belivus is too careful, too sneaky, and more to the point, has too much in the way of magical power, especially compared with these guys.”

“It also would have meant splitting the party,” said Arthur.

“True,” I said. “Though technically it would have just been a side adventure. Even if it hadn’t though, it’s just … if you want to do something that you’re almost certainly not going to fail at, I don’t see why we should go through the motions.”

“Because it’s fun?” asked Tiff. “For what it’s worth, I would have loved to help plan a heist.”

“If you guys want to do a heist, we can do a heist,” I said. “But this is not that. The stakes are low, the defenses are minimal. Look, if this is what the party wants, we can make a retcon that this unassuming company is like … a front for some larger organization that has the means and motive for keeping their stuff under a heavier lock and key. I’ve got ideas. But within the context of the world-as-presented, it should be absolutely trivial for pretty much any member of the group, but especially Belivus.” I could feel myself at odds with the group, an uncomfortable feeling, and the worst part of being a Dungeon Master. “Okay, let’s take a little break, Reimer, if you want to, when we’re off the break, you can tell us your brilliant plan for stealing this recipe that I’ve already told you is basically free. Deal?”

“Sure,” he nodded. “But that means that I don’t get a break. And I have questions that I’ll probably need to ask.”

“Fine by me,” I said, though it really wasn’t, because I just wanted the stupid plot thread I’d spun up to be done with.

Two full weeks and a number of trivialized quests after I’d killed Perisev, I walked into Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle’s throne room, hoping that it was the last time. We had installed a chair opposite his, at Valencia’s insistence, though we weren’t often in conversation with him, and I had been out of the picture for quite some time, more focused on squeezing utility from gold magic and knocking out quests for hire at a fairly rapid pace. Bethel was back in Poran, the portal to the plane of flesh had been created faster than anyone had thought possible, and the second generation of tuung were working hard to extract everyone from the underground cities.

“So,” I said to Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle. “We’re in the process of winding down.”

“You are,” he nodded. “Impressively fast, so far as I can tell. You’ve deprived me of my eyes in a number of places, which I don’t appreciate, and the lines of communication have been somewhat lacking, except for that girl.”

Valencia was the one who talked to him most often, communicating in a friendly but slightly adversarial way, like old friends of the Second Empire playing some grand game. It was, according to her, the best way to get him talking and position us as someone he could deal with. He would be dismissive and manipulative to a sycophant, guarded around a moralist, but with someone he saw as an equal, he would engage. In this dynamic she’d set up, she was the equal, not me, and not Amaryllis. I was mostly talking to him in order to be the one to deliver him some grim news.

“You’ve been cooperative,” I said. “We appreciate that.”

“Do you now?” asked Blue-in-the-Bottle. “I conceded, and I stay true to my word.”

“You have seven backups around Necrolaborem, people whose essence you’ve manipulated through necromancy, we believe through subjecting them to near-death experiences,” I said. We had evidence for most of those, and thankfully, it didn’t seem like a process he could or did employ with impunity. “As of thirty minutes ago, all of them have been isolated. We don’t know the precise nature of the changes that you’ve made to them, but we know that they offer you something of a second chance, if you were to die.”

The face of the zombie he was speaking through fell. “Ah,” he said. “And I suppose this is the precursor to my death, is it? I had hoped there was too much utility in the zombies, but you are moralists, aren’t you?”

“We’re not killing you,” I said. “We said that we wouldn’t, so we aren’t. In the past two weeks I’ve killed a lot of people. I cleared out the fleshsmiths of Pendleham, either murdering them or taking their ability to practice the magic. I swooped down and killed Rove. I blasted Gatesmith. You, I want alive, mostly to signal to other people that I’m willing to make concessions.” This was a lie. I didn’t want him alive at all, and I was perfectly prepared to murder him at the drop of a hat, if only someone could convince me that it would be a good thing to do.

“Why tell me?” he asked. “You have me dead to rights, my last plans scuttled. Why not let me believe that I could keep things going forever?”

“Because we didn’t want you scheming,” I said. “We want you to know that you have no outs left, so that you won’t try to screw us over, or run some gambit in the shadows.” I’d let Valencia make the call on whether to have this confrontation, and that was, in essence, her reasoning. “If you help us with tearing down what you’ve built here, there’s a path forward for you. The older method of necromancy, the one that allows the soul to be bottled, is still useful. There are voices of dissent on the matter of whether we should keep you alive, but right now, from where we’re sitting, it seems better to reach some understanding.”

“I see,” replied Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle. “By my calculations, it will take you five months at the earliest to remove everyone from the underground cities. You need to secure my cooperation for at least that long.”

“It would be better if we did,” I said. “If we can’t have it, if we think that you’re going to betray us, we have contingencies in place. They’re worse for us though.” It would be a scramble and a logistical problem, but we hadn’t sat down for this without making sure that we could stop a catastrophe.

“And you’ve been knocking out my own contingencies, as I’d thought you might,” said Blue. “Tell me, how did you find the backups?”

“It was a combination of things,” I said. “Methods that you’d have no way of foreseeing. It probably doesn’t feel good to be beaten in that way.”

“Not particularly, no,” replied Blue. “You do seem to have me firmly pinned in place.”

I nodded. “In our ideal world — you’re already a prisoner to the exclusion zone, and you would remain a prisoner here, with some of our members as wardens.” I glanced over at Valencia, who was out of view, watching the proceedings to see whether she could pick up anything from him. He was much tougher than a baseline human, she’d said, because he was operating through a zombie, which affected her ability to read microexpressions and body language, only some of which translated through.

“Very well,” said Blue. “Will I operate in secret, or openly?”

“Openly,” I said. “It’s not just because of the utility you can bring, but because it sends a message, which is that we’re willing to work with despicable people and seek redemption. Hopefully we can get some people to come in from the cold.”

“It’ll be a public relations problem for you, so far as I understand the current mood of the world,” said Blue.

“Yes,” I replied. “We can spin it as hard labor for you, but my guess is that people will still be clamoring for your head on a pike and your soul sent down to the furthest hells.” I shrugged. “Nothing much that we can do about that, because we’re not going to give in to those particular demands. But what we need from you is a guarantee that you won’t try to fight like a caged animal, won’t set things up to be harder for us, that you’ll actually work with us. Can you guarantee that?”

“I can,” replied Blue. “I said, the second time you came to me, that I conceded without preconditions.”

I nodded, then glanced at Valencia. She hesitated for a moment, then gave a very slight shake of her head.

“Okay,” I said. I looked at Grak and gave him a nod. He immediately began moving his hand.

“What have you done?” asked Blue, a moment later.

“Cut off contact with your zombies,” I said. “We’ve done it before.”

“No,” said Blue. “This is different.”

“We’re going to give it a bit, to see if you’ve hidden any surprise counter measures,” I said.

“Was my answer not satisfactory?” asked Blue, gazing at me both with his own withered eyes and the more intact ones of the zombie he spoke through.

“It wasn’t,” said Valencia, coming forward, into his view. “My guess is that your remaining contingency is to set up a new laboratory away from our prying eyes, but it might also involve contact with your infernal allies.”

“You,” he said, looking her over. “How do you know such things?”

“Entads and a long life,” said Valencia.

“No,” said Blue. “No, you’re something else, not a person at all. You’re a curiously proficient liar.”

Valencia shrugged. “Well, I don’t mind what you think of me, because you’ll be dead in roughly a half hour.” She looked at me. “I’m not seeing any active countermeasures, but we can wait until there’s a report from the tuung.”

“Sure,” I said. I looked at Blue. “We’re done here, for now, I’ll check back in a half hour from now.”

“Wait,” said Valencia, looking at Blue. “Stop him.”

I darted forward and laid my hand on him, stilling him completely, and I saw Grak moving to do the same with a ward, cutting down his ability to act. Grak had already cleared him of entads, but that didn’t mean he couldn’t be hiding some other magic, or something mechanical that we couldn’t sense.

“Oh,” said Valencia. “He was planning to kill himself and go to the hells, I think. Maybe.”

“Fucker,” I said, hand still on Blue’s withered skin as he sat there, motionless. “What now?” I asked the question at Valencia, but it wasn’t really the kind of question that she was qualified to answer.

“Disarm or kill him,” said Amaryllis.

“Get me a report from the tuung,” I said. They had been on standby for a general shutdown. Our understanding of the zombies was that most of them would continue on doing what they were ‘programmed’ to do, but we needed to make sure that they hadn’t been programmed into becoming a ravening horde.

It was a tense five minutes as we got reports in from the rest of the exclusion zone, most of them through entads. When they came back clean, I pulled my sword from its interdimensional pocket and sliced cleanly through Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle, separating his head from his neck, then cutting him further, dissecting his body. For good measure, Grak finished a necromancy ward, just in case he had a way to come back to life that didn’t involve taking over those seven we’d identified.

Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle defeated!

Quest Completed: The Z-word - With Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle dead, his zombies will linger on, going through their rote actions until someone comes through to put them out of their misery. The human workforce will be a bigger issue, one that will linger for much longer, a trauma that will never fully be made right, not without godlike power.

Quest Updated: Slayer of Horrors (4/12)

“Alright,” I said with a sigh. “Quest completed. That fucking guy.”

“Not how I’d have asked for it to be handled,” said Amaryllis.

“He was going to work against us,” said Valencia. “It was a matter of time, and you were the one that said we need to stop devoting our time to this.”

“Well, we do,” said Amaryllis. “The tuung can handle it from here, now that food and water have been sorted.” Food was through the portal I had helped to make with a squadron of star mages, but water had been entirely Grak, who had provided the critical wards for a hastily built filtration station at what was soon going to become a metropolis. There were steel mages on site, a whole cadre of them brought in through an arrangement with the Athenaeum of Steel and Sweat, and they had been putting up buildings almost non-stop. “This is a setback though. I’m not entirely convinced that we couldn’t have wrung more utility from him before he had to go.”

“We tried,” I said. “We made an effort.”

“It’s hard to fundamentally change someone,” said Valencia. “Much easier to coerce them into acts they wouldn’t normally do. I could have stayed on top of him, but that would mean that I would have to stay here, watching over him, talking to him, instead of doing anything else.”

She left unspoken what she would be working on instead, who she was working on fundamentally changing. I knew Valencia’s take on things, more or less. Reconciliation would be easier in a month or two, with more groundwork laid, when time had done its work at helping to heal wounds.

“We need to get going,” I said. “The end of gold magic isn’t in sight, not yet, but if we want it available for the endgame, we’re going to have to move fast.”

“There are limits on how fast it can be moved along,” said Valencia. “I’m sorry, but if you want it done properly, that’s how it has to be done. Rushing things … there are lots of ways that it could go wrong, some of which might end with death.”

“And if we use time manipulation?” I asked.

“We don’t have time manipulation,” said Valencia. “Do we?”

“Technically,” I said, trying to think things through. “I’m not sure how the call of the gold would work with the time loop exclusion, but we could maybe do something workable that way.”

“No,” said Grak. “We don’t have a way out of the exclusion, once we’re inside.”

“We would find one,” I said. “With warding?”

“I went there on my own to observe the magic,” said Grak. “From what I could see at the boundary, the resets cannot be stopped.”

“Fuck,” I said.

“Three of the disjoint planes have some kind of time-slowing effect,” said Amaryllis. “They’re only reachable through the elemental planes, but we already have a standing portal open to the plane of flesh, so in theory the cost is already dramatically lowered. There’s also a standing portal to the elemental plane of blood open in the DFEZ.”

“That’s doable, then,” I said.

“I don’t know what we’re going to find when we go into Fel Seed’s zone,” said Valencia. “But I’m skeptical about our group dynamics.”

“You’ll be there,” I said. “You don’t think that you can hold things together?”

“Maybe,” said Valencia. “But if going into the most dangerous place on Aerb …” she let that dangle.

“How much time do you need?” I asked. “Minimum?”

“Two weeks,” said Valencia. “Give me two weeks, and I probably won’t feel like we’re heading toward disaster.”

“I might not have gold magic in two weeks,” I said.

“We have reserves, and I’ve been liquidating assets that we don’t need,” said Amaryllis. “We might be able to swing it. The question is what those two weeks have in store for us. There are plot threads that need wrapping up, but I’m not taking it for granted that we really can just waltz into what should have been important quests and resolve them in a few hours, not if they’re the kinds of things that aren’t especially amenable to punching.”

“Okay,” I said, nodding. I turned to Valencia. “And you’ll work on Bethel?”

“I will,” said Valencia. “But … some of it isn’t her. I’ll need to work on you too.”

“Work on me how?” I asked.

“Work on helping you through it, on preparing for the reconciliation,” said Valencia.

“Oh,” I replied. “Well, sure, makes sense. So … how do we do that?”

“It’s something that you need to talk about and work through,” said Valencia. “You’ve been shying away from it, which is understandable, but when you have to face her, it shouldn’t be with no mental and social preparation.”

“And you’ll help me?” I asked.

“Of course,” said Valencia. “But I don’t think it’s a good idea to use a devil’s power, so it would just be me.”

“Okay,” I sighed.

“It might also be good for you to face some problems that you’ve been choosing not to engage with,” said Valencia.

“Meaning?” I asked.

“Speak to your father,” Valencia replied. “Sit down for a conversation with Tiff. You have good reasons for avoiding those conversations, but it’s part of a bad pattern, one that I’m hoping you can break yourself of. I’m not optimistic that it can be done in two weeks without my help, but … it would make me more comfortable.”

“It’s a suicide mission either way,” said Grak.

“Yes, it is,” replied Valencia. “But if we’re all going to die, then I don’t want it to be because of something that I personally could have prevented.”

“Likewise, the wards will be as sound as they can be,” replied Grak, with a bit more of a grumble than usual.

“We’re not going to die,” I said. “We’re not going against him, just passing through his territory.”

“There’s a good chance that we actually do die,” said Amaryllis. She looked at Valencia. “I think there’s an argument for keeping you out, just in case there’s some kind of pathway through the afterlife that has, somehow, never been used before.”

“I need to be there,” said Valencia. “Not for Fel Seed, but for the meeting with Uther. There’s a strong chance that Bethel will attempt to kill him the moment it’s clear that it’s him.”

“And you can keep her on a leash?” asked Amaryllis.

“You know that I can’t, and you know that’s exactly the kind of language that she hates,” Valencia replied. “Aside from just hoping that the groundwork I’ve done is enough, it’s possible that I can intervene at the critical moment.”

I left the conversation feeling off-kilter. Raven hadn’t been there, and neither had Solace, but we’d need their input too. Two weeks wasn’t a lot of time, but it would mean more to keep the gold bug sated, and more in the way of preparation.

We're Here, We're Deer, Get Used to It

I sat in the domain of the locus, with it beside me, trying to think about how I wanted to approach the plan. Eventually, I got up and clapped my hands together, then drew them apart, wiggling my fingers.

“Layman, I summon thee!”

Nothing happened.

“Welp,” I said, frowning. “That was worth a shot.” I looked around at the trees and wildlife, birds chirping in the trees, butterflies enjoying what was, for Poran, an unseasonably warm day (at least some of that thanks to my command of water magic). “The text of the virtue is that I’m able to sweet talk the Layman while I’m here, and you’d think that would mean actually talking to him.” I sighed again, trying not to be too annoyed.

“What you need,” I said to the locus, “Is power, ideally some kind of enormous battery of some kind. We could take you to Blue Fields and detonate a nuclear device that would be captured by something that used rune magic, maybe, but I don’t know if that’s the right kind of power, because you can already violate energy laws and produce matter seemingly from nothing. Aside from that, there’s the giant laser thing that the lunatics on Celestar are apparently building, but who knows what that actually is, and when they’ll be done, and whether it would even be the right kind of thing.”

The locus was grazing, eating grass and not appearing to pay much attention to me.

“So then the last thing that comes to mind, when I think about enormous sources of power, is the game system that’s attached to me,” I said. “Some of the feats — the virtues, sorry — give explicit violations of the normal way the world works, allowing infinite energy of their own. I’m pretty sure that the Proportional Halting virtue let me slow down Mome Rath, which would be a huge exception to how still magic is normally supposed to work, and would take enormous amounts of power to do, unless it’s manipulating reality at such a basic level that the concept of power doesn’t even apply. That would still work for our purposes. So … it’s just a matter of how to take that power source and get it to interface with you, if only for long enough that you can acquire another druid or two, to get the ball rolling on acquisition.”

The locus looked up from the grass and gave me a single raised eyebrow from among her six eyes.

“For my next trick, I shall turn into a locus,” I said. “One sec, I need to get undressed.”

The Amulet of Five Spirits was one of those magic items that had some incidental nudity involved, which happened a lot with magic if you didn’t want to just say “oh, well I guess clothes are affected too”, a lazy solution that admittedly fixed a lot of logistical issues. It was the kind of thing that made me wince in movies, books, or things like that, a concession to practical necessity that robbed the magic of some of its magic. The Amulet of Five Spirits didn’t mess around with that, and if I wanted to become a locus, especially the kind that the Six-Eyed Doe saw me as, I would need to put my pile of entads someplace safe.

The acquisition process was easy enough, requiring only a hand on the doe’s flank. Transformation was easy as well, as easy at it had always been in test runs with the amulet, and as always, accompanied by the unsettling feeling of my body doing things that my brain had absolutely no way of handling. My fingers and toes merged together and elongated, the nails thickening, my skin thickened and sprouted hair all over the place, and my face underwent a total rearrangement that included four extra eyes and an enormous set of antlers.

I had seen through the eyes of the locus via the Crown of Eyes, but hadn’t counted on how different it would be for me when I was the locus. For the Six-Eyed Doe, I got a sense of an art style that reminded me of Salvador Dali or Hieronymous Bosch, maybe in the way that things would appear ‘flat’, or maybe just arranged. For the locus instance of myself, the style was different, and the perception was much more focused, each individual thing I was ‘looking’ at a sole focus of my attention, reminding me of a still life or portrait, the kinds of things that struck me as very classical, but were probably confined to a relatively small time and place, one I might have pinpointed if I knew anything about art history, which I did not.

When I focused my attention on the locus, it was like looking at a painting of her, one designed to cast her in the best possible light, posed and well-lit in ways that I knew were, if not completely false, then at least cheats. Most likely the locus did look like that, or at least could given the right conditions, but there was something in the presentation that felt even more unreal than it was.

I was still hopped up on all my various sensory enhancements, minus the Crown of Eyes, which meant that there was a lot that I could focus on. It was an odd filter to have put on the world, where everything became framed as though it was the focal point of artistic study. I had to wonder why it was that my own view of things was so dramatically different than what the locus experienced. It might have been because I was a human, or it might have been something unique to me, not written on my soul, but somewhere more ineffable. As a metaphor for how I thought, I didn’t think that it was particularly apt, since it was what you’d expect of someone who routinely missed the forest for the trees, and while I missed things pretty regularly, I felt myself pretty aware of the interconnectedness of all things. Maybe the view was trying to say something different though, and I tried to be open to the possibilities.

As you might expect, turning into a locus, even a fake one, was only step one of the plan. There was no second step though. I had hoped that there would be something obvious, some lever to press or course of action that flowed naturally from the new form, but I felt like this had to be a piece of the puzzle. The only reason that I was able to turn into a locus at all was because of the degrees of reasonableness granted to me by the locus. The entad itself wasn’t even all that important of an ingredient, because there had to be half a dozen different paths to the same end.

The locus moved over to me and stood beside me, touching her fur to my own, then leaning over to touch her neck to my own.

It wasn’t unexpected. The locus had always been physically affectionate. I had ridden her around her domain, and even a bit outside of it once we had that link. I had napped while leaning up against her, feeling the warmth of her body. Whenever I was in the domain, I was a part of her, suffused by her being in some way, my body under her aegis.

That most hated of achievements, “A Key for Seven Locks”, had seemed stupid and cruel, and still did, but it made me think about what circumstances would have to look like for it to actually be fulfilled. Of late, things with Amaryllis being what they were, I had been thinking about sex as it must have looked from her perspective, something done as a method of helping someone else, or as being platonic. If it was a requirement that I have sex with someone in order to save their life through some kind of contrived sex magic or idiotic plot thing, then I would do it. I wouldn’t be happy about it, but I’d do it.

The context for a lot of these thoughts was what I’d talked about with the locus some time ago, how maybe there was no solution, maybe it was a winding path toward eventual death. If you looked at the locus from that perspective, as a creature that had faced its own certain demise, then birth or rebirth seemed like one of the viable endpoints, as though she might be a phoenix rising from the ashes, or a message about how the mark we make on the world will always outlast us, or something like that.

It was while I was thinking about this seeming invitation, and what, if anything, it might mean, that the man showed up.

He was wearing a white t-shirt and loose-fitting jeans, with nothing much to identify him. If I had to describe him to a police officer, I would probably have said that he was 5’10”, average build, plain face, nothing too much to look at, the kind of guy that got put into a lineup in order to fill out the ranks, or who got pulled onto a basketball team because they needed another. Back on Earth, my friends had joked about me looking generic, but if they had ever seen this guy, they wouldn’t have been able to make that joke again. The only two things that were really distinct about him were his haircut, which was cut so close it must have been a buzz, and the can of soda he held, which was ‘Mountain Rush’.

“Did someone summon me?” he asked, looking between me and the locus.

I bellowed at him, forgetting for a moment that I wasn’t human, then made the switch over to my normal form as quickly as I could, leaving me standing there, naked, with just an amulet on. (I had been naked before, but definitely felt more naked as a human.)

“Are you,” I said. “Are you the Layman?”

“Pretty sure I am, yeah,” he said, looking down at himself. “You had a,” he made a twirling motion with his fingers. “A thing?”

“Sorry,” I said. “Where did you come from?”

“I mean, I don’t really think that’s much of your business, is it?” he asked, furrowing his brow. “Was that the question? Because you should know that I’m not really about the meta stuff.”

“You showed up late,” I said, glancing at the locus.

“I’ve got other things going on in my life,” he replied. “Someone gives you a phone call and says that they’re summoning you, do you drop everything to go right away? Nah man, I’m not turning on a dime for you, that’s not part of the deal.”

“A dime?” I asked. “You’re from Earth?”

“Hey look, if you don’t have a real, you know,” he gestured again, “thing, then I’m gonna bounce.”

“The question is about power interface,” I said, speaking quickly, because if he left, I wasn’t confident that I would be able to get him back. It was fucking bizarre that he was, apparently, a real person, but I was doing my best to roll with it. “The locus is low on power, has only one druid, and a limited domain. Through the mechanism of the game interface, which exists above and beyond the level of the soul, I have an immense amount of power or pseudopower available to me, and as we can see from the ‘floating’ domain around me and a few other things, the locus is already directly connected to that power source, and already capable of drawing on it to some limited degree.”

“Alright,” he said. “Sure. But what do you need to talk to me about it for?”

“I mean, you agree with all that?” I asked. “No questions asked, no arguments needed?”

“Sure,” he said with a shrug. “That's it?”

“So how do I, you know, transfer some of that reserve of power to the locus?” I asked.

“Not sure how that’s my department,” he said. “You know who I am, right? I’m the Layman. If you’ve got some definitions, stuff that’s not covered by p-space, or you want a, you know, change of jurisdiction because of prejudice or something, I’m your guy. If it’s more about what should or shouldn’t happen if you try something that’s way off the map, yeah, talk to me. If you want to have someone to knock together a plan with, that’s why you’ve got a party. But that’s meta stuff, which I don’t really do, so I’m out of here.”

“Wait,” I said. “I have a plan, I just need to run it by you.”

“Alright,” he said with a sigh. He took a long drink from his can of soda then raised an eyebrow. “I’m listening, but I swear if this is just you saying a bunch of stuff that doesn’t need my input, I’m complaining to the Big Guy.”

I wanted to ask who that was, and how many other entities there might be, because it was all very exciting, but I also felt like I was right on the verge of losing his attention, and I wasn’t sure that summoning him a second time would be as easy or fruitful.

“Having children is a viable method of transferring some or all of the game layer, which most importantly means all the attendant power,” I said.

“Is it?” he asked, giving me a very skeptical look.

“A child is a product of their parents,” I said. “At least until you start getting nurture stuff involved. And I know that the soul tracks parentage, which it must get from somewhere, which means that there’s a connection between souls. Data transfer, at the very least.”

“Okay,” he said. “But you’re saying that with you and the locus, you’re doing some kind of power transfer?”

I nodded. “The rules are clearly in flux, they’d have to be in order to interface with the locus, all the definitions are loose, the descriptions are images. It’s entirely possible to pass on the game system, or a fraction of its limitless power, enough to expand the domain, or induct a druid, or … or make a new locus.”

“Eh,” he said.

“With the virtues from the companion passives, yes,” I said. “The locus can bend or break rules, that’s in her nature. Hells, I’d argue that she’s outside the rules entirely. If, at that particular moment, she pulls on the connection between us, and I freely give it, she should be able to grab a fraction.”

“Eh,” he said again. “I might need to talk to some people. Give me a second.”

“Sure,” I replied. “What people?”

He disappeared without answering the question, and I was left standing there naked, feeling awkward. I turned to the locus, who had a characteristically serene look. I felt the urge to talk, to explain, to ask questions that I knew wouldn’t get answers, but I swallowed that urge and stayed silent, waiting for the return of the Layman.

I occupied my mind wondering who the people he might be talking to were. The Big Guy was pretty obviously the Dungeon Master, or maybe the Dungeon Master’s boss, if there was a distinction. No one else had been mentioned in the rules text we’d been given, nor implied through conversation with the Dungeon Master or conversations with Reimer about what the game had been like. I had long theorized a Dungeon Master’s Assistant type of role, the kind of entity responsible for making a billion entads, or doing other work that would be too tedious to comfortably fit in with the Dungeon Master’s persona. At least, that's what I would do if I was making a pantheon for this world.

It was interesting that the Layman had talked about issues of jurisdiction, which was another thing that I’d noticed a few times before. Magics needed definitions, because they weren’t actually running on local physics, and there were lots of different ways of handling those definitions. The Layman was one, p-space was another, and some magics or entads seemed to have their own separate definitions about what things were or weren’t. Valencia now had a number of ‘cursed’ entads which were exploited mostly through finding chinks in their definitions, places where certain parts would apply to her while others wouldn’t. One of the things I adored about Aerb was that it was willing to do that sometimes, to have four or five things that were, on the surface, the same, but with different rules to get to that point, which had different knock-on effects, different exploits, and different applications.

I was taking my mind off the matter at hand, naturally.

The Layman returned, still holding the same can of soda.

“We really don’t think it’s necessary,” he said.

“Necessary?” I asked. “Sorry, you — I don’t know what that word means in this context. Or what you mean by ‘we’.”

“Your souls are already linked,” he said. “The thread between souls, and the stuff on the character sheet? So like, sure, maybe I could say that you could link with each other through the magic of having sex — gross, by the way — but how does it change anything? That’s kind of what we settled on.”

“So what are you saying?” I asked. “That if I want to transfer an enormous amount of power over to the locus in order to expand its domain, I just need to …?”

“Problem is, the power isn’t yours to distribute,” he said.

I frowned. “Meaning that all that needs to happen is for the locus to take it,” I said. “Right?”

He thought about that for a moment. “The way I’ve been imagining the system is, it’s got limitless power, right? It allows all kinds of ridiculous crap on top of the regular ridiculous crap, and yeah, and the upper limits just don’t matter. Level doesn’t really matter either, because some of the shit in there is broken right off the bat. But it’s like, I dunno, a house with only a few exits. You can go out the front door or the back, but — you get it? Or it’s like a balloon that has a few holes poked into it, and you’re trying to rip the whole thing apart, but what it wants to do is to make that little annoying sound as the air slowly blows out of it.”

I did get it, kind of, but it was clear that the Layman didn’t get where he was by having great explanations. “And we both know that the locus doesn’t play by rules,” I said.

To my surprise, he seemed to consider that. “Okay,” he said.

“Meaning, what?” I asked.

“I agree,” he said. “So, problem solved, from your perspective?”

“Wait,” I said.

“Nah,” he said. “You made your argument, I agreed, that’s all this needs to be.”

He vanished, without so much as a snap of his fingers.

“Welp,” I said, turning to the locus. “I guess you just … grip onto the business end of the game system and take in the power?”

The locus gave me a blank look, as though she’d just let the words wash over her.

“Aw come on,” I said. “I know that you know at least a little bit of Anglish, or can read emotional or mental states well enough that you can contribute to a conversation. You can’t pretend that you didn’t have some understanding of what was going on there.”

The locus looked away, and I imagined that she was embarrassed at trying such an obvious lie.

“Okay,” I said. “There’s power there to grab a hold of, but you just don’t want to do it. And I guess if you’re not just going to transform yourself into a person and talk to me,” I waited, in case that was what she wanted to do. “Then I need a totally separate conversation with you in order to convince you, without actually knowing what your objection is, or getting much in the way of feedback. I’m going to get dressed first though.”

The locus turned back to me and gave a slight shake of her head, and I felt a jolt of embarrassment at that, then got dressed anyhow, nothing but pants, keeping my bare feet touching the grass.

“Alright,” I said. “Because I don’t know why you’re not just doing the thing, we’ll go through one by one until I hit the right track.” I let out a breath. Amaryllis was better at argument, but she had a much worse understanding of the locus, even if it was mixed with that particular reverence that people of this age had for the loci.

“Option one is that you want to die, or if not die, then fade away, or whatever it is would actually happen, given enough time,” I said. “You don’t strike me as suicidal, but you do strike me as the kind of creature that thinks an end to things is normal and natural. Look at Uther, the way that the narrative just wouldn’t end for him, the adventures that could never truly be brought to a close. It could be that’s how you see your own life, especially in the wake of the Second Empire being shitbags, and being constrained to the bottle, and … I don’t know, the prospect of expansion, which we’ve been taking Solace’s word on, probably seems daunting, or tiring, or just not at all fun. There’s a way that suicidal people sometimes are, where they get peaceful or euphoric, because they’ve made up their mind, and maybe that’s you. Or maybe that’s the wrong frame, and it’s just acceptance that this is the end, with no particular desire to keep going for another thirty thousand years or however long you’re been alive.”

I was watching for some sign that I was on the right track, but saw nothing one way or another. The locus was eating some grass, seemingly ignoring me, but that didn’t necessarily mean anything.

“Let’s set that aside for a moment,” I said. “Option two is that death isn’t really on the table for you, however that would work. When you were in the bottle, you couldn’t maintain the system on your own, probably because everything was so contained, so dependent on itself. It was like … well, I imagine it like running the same tabletop game for twenty years, where every single person has a bio, every single nation has an org chart, every magic is completely explored, and you’re not allowed to introduce anything new, not allowed to just go wild, and all your efforts are put toward hammering everything into shape. I can see how it would rankle. But now that you’re out of the bottle, you don’t have to do that management anymore, it’s not all going to fall apart into death and decay. Even if the biome you have shifts to something a little more appropriate to Poran it’ll still be life, still have plants and animals, still be a natural environment. So maybe you see that, an endless life on Poran, and you think, well, you’re right where you want to be.”

I got no response from that.

“Option three is that it’s the wrong kind of power. The game system … to take it back to tabletop games, you’re pure flavor, you’re that raw, wonderful, inspired creativity and expression that I love in my games.”

Loyalty Increased: Six-Eyed Doe lvl 23!

“Oh come on, you already knew I thought that,” I replied. “Anyway. The term-of-art is fluff, but you’re not quite that, because fluff implies the stuff that’s not important to actually playing the game, and you’re more fundamental than that. But the game system? That’s almost exactly the opposite. It’s the crunch. It’s the numbers, the mechanics, maybe with a little bit of mediation by the Layman, or interpretation by the Dungeon Master, but if it’s power, it’s power that is primarily rigid and structured, at least in terms of how it expresses itself.”

I was watching the locus, looking for tells, some kind of sign that I was on the right track. She was at least looking back at me, six eyes meeting my two, but it was impossible to tell what she was thinking, if anything. Maybe she just liked hearing the sounds coming from my mouth.

“You need both those parts, at least for the kinds of things I love most,” I said. “Strip the fluff out and you get board games, or card games, or … I don’t know, even most of those make some token effort at having nice artwork and flavor text. If you go the other way and strip out all the rules, all the mechanics, you freeform improv, or abstract art, or … there’s something I find unfulfilling about being unmoored, ungrounded. No offense.”

The locus laid down, front legs tucked under her, and stretched out so that her neck was pressed against the ground.

“Reading that back in my head, I know it probably seems, uh, a little bit insensitive, like I don’t value you, or like I think your whole essence could do with some fundamental restructuring, but it’s really not that. I can appreciate the freeform stuff. I’m just trying to say that there’s a particular kind of beauty that you can see in a marriage of imagination and simple mechanics, and if your hesitance is that taking some of this power that comes from a very mechanical source would pollute you somehow, make you less purely the thing you are right now … I don’t know. I wish that we could actually talk to each other.”

On a whim, I took off my pants and transformed back into a locus, hoping that I could put my thoughts in a form that would be more easily transferred. I was convinced that the locus understood Anglish, but I wasn’t convinced that it was entirely the same kind of understanding as how I understood Anglish.

Expressing myself as a locus was, to put it lightly, difficult. I didn’t seem to have much in the way of powers, which made sense, because I had no domain, nor druids, nor any of the other minimal trappings that a locus was supposed to have. Beyond what I’d seen from Solace, the locus had all kinds of magic of its own, and the various effects that it had produced, while generally nature-themed, ran the gamut. This was usually small magic, like having a trail of flowers that sprouted up behind her as she walked, or butterflies that would dance around her, but it was still the kind of thing which, if you showed it to Reimer, would raise a bunch of questions about what the breadth of powers was.

I decided to try showing her something.

Striding with four hooves, I began to circle the domain, moving faster until I was going at a canter, feeling the rhythm of the movement. I wasn’t terribly surprised to find that the locus was following me, but I ignored her for a moment, trying to concentrate on what I was trying to do.

We passed an Amaryllis near the stream, moving quickly as we did, and I had only a moment to take in her stunned face. I had told her that I was going to do something like this, but I supposed that the information hadn’t made its way to all of the clones.

I began to play with the canter. It was a natural three-beat, ba ba bump , and I did my best to hold it there, feeling the way I could naturally speed up into a four-beat gallop or slow into a two-beat trot. I imagined the canter as two sets of three, and began adding things to the timing of my gait. I was limited by being in the body I was in, but I had sounds at my disposal, and after a bit of experimentation, I was able to add them in, something like a grunt or a bellow to go with every third beat.

As music went, it was both crude and basic, and I apparently still had something like physical stamina, because by the time I had made a complete lap around the domain of the locus, I was starting to get quite warm and a little out of breath. For all that, the locus was running steadily with me, and by the time we’d gone halfway through our second lap, she had joined in, making much more musical sounds than I was. The forest around us began to join in, with animals conscripted to our cause, matching the three-beat of our canter, and with a little bit of effort, I was able to amplify it all with vibration magic.

I had never been terribly musical, but it felt like it was working. We were building off a scaffolding, the three-beat gait, putting everything within that framework, adding more to it as we went until it was a forest symphony, chirps from birds, croaks from the frogs in the stream, buzzing of insects.

I hoped that it would help the locus understand where I was coming from, whatever her issue was with not pulling on the thread that had been left dangling in front of her. When I looked over though, I was surprised to see that she seemed to be enjoying herself, throwing her head back to add her own noise to the music we were making. There was a frenetic energy to her, and a kind of beauty that I hadn’t seen before, complemented by my vision, which was showing me things as though they were the sole focus of my attention.

I was, at the very least, happy that I could bring her joy, and on a whim, I let our path circling her domain straighten out. With our path changed, it wasn’t long before we reached the edge of the domain, and the steep grade down to the natural land of Poran. I didn’t have any grand plan for this, especially since so much of my focus was already being soaked up with the improvised music, cantering along uneven terrain, and watching the locus.

When we passed the boundary, the locus continued on, and I felt a tug, one that reached down deep inside me, to a part of myself I had never known I could feel. The domain was yanked with us, like pulling on a tablecloth, and in the wake of the locus, the gray rocks and poor soil of Poran were washed with nature magic. Plants grew in the space of a heartbeat, trees shot into the sky, and there was something more elemental happening to the ground beneath us. It was a massive display of power, terraforming in an instant, and as we moved toward what passed for a beach on Poran, the effect spread. The island was rising up, displacing water in a way that I hoped wasn’t going to end up with the equivalent of a tidal wave some miles away.

The locus herself changed as she ran, rearing up onto her back legs and then staying there as her front legs became arms. The fur fell off in scraps, leaving her naked and pink, and hair grew out all at once from her head, a golden blonde mass of curls. She had to have been nearly nine feet tall, a giant of a woman, close to human, but with six eyes. She was thick, with strong calves and large thighs, and when she launched herself toward me, I was momentarily worried that I wouldn’t be able to handle her, momentarily forgetting that I was a giant buck myself.

We rode around the edge of the Isle of Poran, with her on my back, and I kept up the canter, though I was getting properly exhausted by how far I’d gone, especially with a passenger on my back. It wasn’t long before we returned to the original part of the domain, and after she’d leapt down from my back, I collapsed to the side, almost completely spent.

The locus seemed happy, and for a time, that seemed like the important part.

Amaryllis woke me up some hours later.

“Doing okay?” she asked, once I’d had a moment to drink some water and get my bearings.

“Sure,” I said. “Good.”

“Game system intact?” she asked.

“So far as I can tell,” I replied. “Looks the same from behind my eyelids, HUD is in place, and I would have plenty of warning if I was losing power. The locus didn’t actually need to leech any, to my understanding, it was more like a car needing a jumpstart. If there was a deficit, she could have paid it back, I think. And unless I misread her, the domain is large enough now that there can be more druids, more growth, if that’s what she wants.”

“Good,” said Amaryllis. She let out a breath. “I retract my earlier skepticism and concern.”

“It was reasonable,” I said.

“Did you,” she started, then faltered for a moment, looking at me. “Is there anything that I need to know about it?”

“Uh,” I said. “I met the Layman, as a real, physical person. He kind of hinted at a larger meta-pantheon, so you’ll have to change your religious beliefs.”

“Time stopped again?” she asked.

“Nope,” I replied. “But it was just me and the locus, there was no need to stop time, I don’t think.”

“Huh,” she said. “I would have liked to see it. Him.”

“I’ll try again some time, if we need to argue,” I said. “I got the feeling that he didn’t like being bothered, and he stonewalled me about a bunch of stuff I’d asked about the meta layer. Which makes sense, I guess, if he’s got the personality of an abstracted layman.”

“You caused a stir around Poran,” said Amaryllis. “I know you probably guessed that already. People saw you, took pictures of you … it’s a bit of a mess, but one that I can handle.”

“Is everything alright?” I asked. “So far as I could tell, the locus was blanketing the rest of the island. All the buildings that we had put up for the tuung, the village for all the hangers-on —”

“All fine,” said Amaryllis. “Most with a bit more greenery, and we’re making plans to move somewhere, but that was always a risk with removing the locus from the bottle, it’s just a consequence that’s been realized later than we thought it would.”

“Sorry,” I said. “But not really that sorry, because it’s something that’s been hanging over me for the last however long.”

“And did you … make a connection?” asked Amaryllis.

“Yes,” I said.

“You’re being deliberately obtuse because you don’t want to have this conversation,” said Amaryllis. “And that’s fine, but if it’s something that you wanted to talk about and dissect, or have me, I don’t know, forgive you, as if that’s necessary, we can’t do that with silence. So, did you have sex with the locus?”

“I did,” I said, feeling a little bit of weight lift with the admission. “Sorry, if that’s —”

“It’s fine,” said Amaryllis, waving a hand. “Weird, but if that’s what was necessary for the locus to expand, I’m glad for it.”

“Er,” I said. “It was after that.”

She stared at me for a moment. “Huh,” she said. “Is it valid for me to ask why?”

“Uh,” I said. “Valid, I guess, sure. We were just … happy, I guess, in a moment of understanding each other. There was an energy there. That’s it. Maybe it just happened because that’s the kind of space I try to put my head in when I’m with the locus.” I was trying not to feel flushed.

“Ah,” she said.

“Are you upset?” I asked.

“No,” she replied. “Just … confused, I guess.” She shook her head. “It doesn’t really matter, in the scheme of things, I just — it seems casual, in a way that sex isn’t for you.”

“Yeah,” I said. “I don’t know.”

She was watching me. I had been worried, after it had happened, that she would see me differently, but her face showed only curiosity and concern.

“Well, so long as you don’t have misgivings,” she said, leaning back somewhat. “Can I ask … what forms were you in, at the time?”

“Mmm,” I said.

“I just mean that there were reports of two loci, and a giant six-eyed woman on an enormous buck, and … if the locus was switching back and forth, and you were as well, I just — don’t need to know,” she finished.

“Okay,” I said. “Sorry, if it’s, I don’t know. Weird.”

“It probably won’t go into the chronicles of our adventures,” she said. “But you should know by now that even if it’s not something that I fully understand, I won’t judge you for it. Maybe a fact that it would be better to keep from getting into circulation though?”

“Probably, yeah,” I replied. “I’m sure the press would have a field day.”

“And I hate to ask this, because I have no doubt about the answer, but,” she took in a breath. “Juniper, did you use protection?”

“Ah,” I said. “No. Didn’t even cross my mind.”

“Well,” she said, swallowing slightly. “I’m sure nothing will come of it.”

Homecoming, Part II

The last thing we needed was to bring Bethel back into the fold.

It went without saying that I didn’t want to do it. I didn’t trust her and didn’t like her, but she had nearly unimaginable power, and that was what we would need if we had even a faint hope of surviving Fel Seed. I was skeptical that anything like a reconciliation could take place, but I thought that we had a good enough shot at working together, if only on this single thing. Valencia had been talking to me, when she could find the time, though most of her concern was in Bethel’s direction, rather than my own. After all, I had no mechanism for killing or even hurting Bethel, while she had hundreds of ways to rend me apart, and more with every day that passed as Amaryllis continued the process of entad acquisition.

We met on Poran, which was now blanketed entirely by the domain of the locus. The arranged meeting place was near the tuung campus, which was still undergoing rapid expansion in the wake of the second generation having finished their adolescence and education. How this was going to work with the locus was beyond me, but if the locus wanted to, their steel mage dormitories could have been crushed at a moment’s notice. Earlier that morning, we’d gotten word of a new induction to what was apparently becoming a corps of druids joining Solace, and this one was one of the tuung, selected through whatever inscrutable criteria the locus was using. There were now five druids, including Solace, and not one of them had been one of the hopefuls, which felt like a bit of a rebuke to Solace’s planning.

Our meeting spot was a table that had been set up in a glade, with no one around us and plenty of wards, along with my own defenses. The wards were a bit overkill, and had been a point of contention. Grak had a very specific ward put up that would shut Bethel down almost completely, leaving her with only a fraction of her total power while we met. The heated discussion among the group had been about what kind of message it would send to her to have something like that in place, and whether it might be taken as a threat, or a sign of things to come. Valencia had said that it was fine, and from the way she said it while carefully not looking at me, it was fairly clear that the whole thing was for my psychological benefit, not for strictly practical reasons.

I ended up waiting for her a bit, no doubt because of further manipulations behind the scenes, a calculation based on Valencia’s handle on my psych profile. I tried not to resent it, because I had, after all, given her permission to do what she needed to in order to make this go smoothly, but there was a part of my brain that churned away, thinking about whether the amount of time I was left to marinate was calculated, and on what level Valencia was playing me.

When I saw Bethel coming, I stood from my chair, waiting for her to cross the distance. She had changed since the last time I’d seen her, though change wasn’t unusual for her. The body she wore to this meeting was much shorter, likely even shorter than Amaryllis, and the musculature had been swept away, leaving her on just the wrong side of skinny. Anything ostentatious, which had once been her signature mark, had been stripped away too, and to the extent that I could tell she’d changed her face, I thought she had probably made her jawline and cheekbones less defined. The dress was simple cotton fabric, as big a departure as possible from the diaphanous rainbow dress she used to wear.

For all that, it was her demeanor that had changed the most. She had a delicacy to the way she stepped, downcast eyes, and a hesitance when she moved. If I hadn’t been given advance warning, I might not have said that it was the same person.

It was all fakery, of course. There was nothing that Bethel didn’t control about her appearance. Valencia had talked to me about it and explained that Bethel was using her outward appearance for self-expression. To hear Valencia tell it, you couldn’t fully trust how Bethel chose to look, or sound, or the expressions that she wore, but you needed to give them some trust, and judge her as though they were all real. I wasn’t fully convinced.

She sat down, and I waited for her to speak, but she remained silent, not meeting my eyes. Her hair was shorter than it had been, no longer braided, coming down to just beneath her chin. She’d kept her skin the color of cedar, maybe a touch darker, with a faint suggestion of wood grain in a few places. I was thankful that she had changed so much, since it was harder for my brain to make the connection between her as she was now and the person she’d been before. To my surprise, my mind didn’t go to what had happened between us, but rather, to the time she cut off Raven’s fingers.

When she finally met my gaze, she held it.

“I’m sorry,” she said.

I waited for more, but she was silent.

“That’s it?” I asked, furrowing my brow. “All this time, and that’s what you decided to go with?”

“Anything else I say is irrelevant,” she replied. Her lips were thin, nearly a grimace.

“But you talked with Valencia,” I said. “Surely she gave you some advice? Some … better set of words?”

“There are no words that I can say that would express my sorrow at what I’ve done,” she replied. “There’s no set of words that can repair our friendship. You trusted me, more than anyone else, and I shattered that trust. I can’t explain, because there’s nothing to explain. I feel like shit about it, but I wouldn’t wager you care about my own feelings. All I can do is say that I wish it hadn’t happened, that I’m a different person than I was, and hope that you can forgive me just enough that I can do something to make amends, like becoming a weapon against Fel Seed.”

I watched her for a moment, meeting her gaze. “You could have led with that,” I said.

“It wouldn’t have mattered,” she said. “It’s the nature of things that whatever I say is irrelevant.”

“Not irrelevant,” I said, frowning slightly. “It’s not … there’s a possibility of a working relationship, with some firm boundaries in place. I don’t hate you,” but as I said it, it felt like a little bit of a lie. “You fucked up. You fucked up in ways that — I don’t think there’s any excusing it, but by way of explaining it, maybe we should have been working to help you socialize more than we actually did. Right and wrong is usually a matter of shades of gray, but it’s not all shades of gray. If Valencia’s been able to help you, then we should have had her help you before things went too far. It was foreseeable, if not in the specifics, then in general.”

“Perhaps,” she slowly admitted. “I don’t want you to diminish my ability to choose my own path. I wasn’t some small animal that didn’t know right from wrong, that needed to be led around on a leash. I was in control of myself. It’s just that the self that was in control was, to put it mildly, maladapted.”

“Right,” I said. “And I’ve always thought of you as someone who understood the world.”

She nodded.

“I know that what’s done can’t be set right,” said Bethel. “But I’m willing to do what I can. Whatever boundaries you set, whatever you ask of me, I’ll do it, with no questions asked.”

I watched her. It was supplication at a level that I hadn’t expected. I didn’t think that I could trust it, and obviously she had her own selfish motives, but there was a part of me that wanted to believe that somehow Valencia had turned her around.

On the other hand, it was all entirely academic. We needed Bethel to go up against Fel Seed. She could have swept in making demands, and common sense would have dictated giving in to at least some of them. There were entads we could feed Bethel, entads that Amaryllis was feeding Bethel, and as a tool, she was too useful not to use. The phrase ‘too big to fail’ crossed my mind. She had offered an apology, and I had to accept it, because that was the rational thing to do, and if I had misgivings, then I had to swallow them.

“I was the one going to bat for you,” I said. “I was the one who understood you, or at least I felt like I did. We were almost kind of friends.”

“I know,” she said, bowing her head. “You gave me more than I deserved. Everyone did, but you meant it in a way that the others didn’t. That’s the source of my sorrow, now that I have a better understanding of why I feel the things that I do.”

“But you still feel them?” I asked. “That need to hurt, to humiliate, to threaten people?”

“Of course,” she replied. “It didn’t just go away. I have a deep well of rage and insecurity, one that might always be there. Valencia has helped me to examine my first instinct though, to think about where my desires are coming from. It’s that second look that’s been helping me. Valencia says that in time, it will become second nature, so quick and effortless that it will happen without conscious thought. I’m not there yet, but I’m trying.”

“How many days without incident?” I asked.

“‘Incident’,” she said, giving a faint frown. “It was not long before I came to deal with Necrolaborem,” she said. “I was talking to a man who was abusive towards his wife, and used more force than I should have. Dealing with people like that — it’s difficult for me. Force is enticing.”

“I know,” I said, narrowing my eyes at her. “It gets you what you want.”

“No,” she said. “Usually it doesn’t. The allure is that it’s simple and visceral. I’d call it idiotic, but I don’t think that’s quite it. It’s base. It’s a fundamental expression of will. For humans, it’s more understandable, since you originally come from animals, if what I know of reality is true. For myself … I was a relative imbecile for a very long time, and a core part of my psyche is a sword. Not an excuse, but perhaps an explanation.”

“Sure,” I said. “Sorry, I’m trying to — forgive, I guess, but it’s hard. And if I can’t forgive you, then at least we can work together.”

She nodded. “I don’t expect forgiveness. I wouldn’t forgive, if the same had happened to me. Valencia has been talking to me about that too though.”

“Forgiving Uther?” I asked.

“Yes,” she replied. “And failing that, to at least empathize, to understand what he was thinking and feeling. Forgiveness doesn’t necessarily follow from that.”

“No, it doesn’t,” I said, sighing a bit. I thought I had a fairly good understanding of Bethel, but I wasn’t sure that it actually helped me feel any better about her. If anything, maybe it made me feel worse. “I think I’m done here for today.”

“Okay,” she said. She stood up from her chair and began to leave without another word.

“You’ll protect us?” I asked. “Fight for us?”

She turned to me and nodded.

“It’s a good first step,” I said. “Thank you for not going the other way.”

She nodded again, then walked away. I watched her as she went. I don’t know what I had been expecting from that reunion, but it hadn’t been that. I found myself feeling sorry for her, and was about to remind myself to stay angry before realizing how stupid that would be. Instead, I let the pity wash over me, allowing myself to feel morose and ill at ease.

When I went in to see Amaryllis, I was surprised to find that she had a visitor with her. It was a young girl, probably not more than twelve years old, with the distinctive pink skin and hair of a renacim. It took my brain a moment to catch up to what I was seeing and realize that there was only one person that it could be.

“Hey Pallida,” I said. “Back from the dead already?”

“Juniper!” she yelled, throwing her arms wide and giving me an enormous smile. “What the fuck man, how’s it going? Long time, no see!”

“Do you … remember me at all?” I asked. Based on what I could tell of her age, she was young enough that she’d only have very cloudy memories of all the times she’d been in her mid-twenties, and I had only known her for a single one of those lifetimes.

“Oh, not even a little,” she replied, still smiling. “I kept a journal though, got all caught up, it said you were a dill weed.”

“Ah, so you’re a brat,” I said. “Got it.”

“Fuck off old man,” she said. “I know you love me, it said so in the journal.”

“She’s a little much,” said Amaryllis. “Pallida, now might not be the best time. You and I can talk later.”

“Aww, but this is the man himself,” said Pallida. “Second coming of Uther Penndraig and all that.” She turned back to me. “Ever had your dick sucked by a twelve-year-old?”

“Pallida!” said Amaryllis, her voice sharp. “Out, now.”

“You’re not my real mom,” said Pallida with a roll of her eyes, but she left the room all the same, giving me a lascivious expression as she did. I hoped that she was just trying to throw me off balance, because if not, I was going to have to throw her into a time chamber until I was less weirded out.

“She didn’t take well to the accelerated raising,” said Amaryllis by way of apology. “She didn’t like the tuung, didn’t like the rules, didn’t like the living conditions, didn’t like not being able to raise hell and steal things … not my best call.” She waved to the side. “We can talk about it later.”

“Now would be fine with me,” I said.

“Yeah?” she asked, raising an eyebrow.

I shrugged. “We can talk more about the Bethel stuff later, but it would be good to give my brain a break with some new problem that’s not my responsibility.”

“I’m not sure that I would call her a problem,” said Amaryllis. “The twelve year old version of Pallida … from what I understand, her usual pattern is to leave whatever home she’s in as soon as possible and make her way in the world, sometimes as early as five or six, even earlier if it’s a rough home life. In some respects, she’s still a little girl, but she’s got a lot of experience being a little girl. Most of that experience is being fiercely independent and antisocial in a lot of ways. The Pallida that we knew is a lot more mellowed out, and she wasn’t particularly mellow.”

“And growing up in the time chamber wasn’t particularly great for her?” I asked.

“We gave her as good a life as we could,” said Amaryllis. “But it wasn’t suited to her, no.”

“And you didn’t talk about this plan with me?” I asked.

“I was trying to take it off your plate,” said Amaryllis. “You disapprove?”

“Did she … consent?” I asked. “To the extent she’s able, at her age? Or before, to the extent that you can consent to what happens in your next life?”

“To the extent she’s able,” said Amaryllis, nodding. “Though not to the gold standards of consent that we might want in an ideal world.”

“Ah,” I said.

“She didn’t understand anything,” said Amaryllis. “It took some time to get her up to speed, to educate her on what the stakes were. There were times she asked to leave, and when that happened, we didn’t immediately allow her to, instead taking some time to talk to her. Once she turned twelve, she was adamant and could no longer be persuaded, which is why she’s come out half-baked and in her current disagreeable state.”

“Ah,” I said again. “This is all kind of giving me some bad vibes, and I notice that you didn’t consult me about it.”

“Sorry,” said Amaryllis. “I didn’t think that it was your call, if I’m being frank. I was closer to Pallida than you were, and knew more about her wishes.”

“But this wasn’t what she wanted, was it?” I asked.

“We didn’t specifically talk about aging her up again if she were to die on us,” said Amaryllis. “But I talked with her enough to know that she wouldn’t do terribly well in the kind of environment I could provide for her, even taking her unique quirks into account. She did want to help though. She was on the wrong side when we first met, and once she figured that out, she was eager to make up for it. We can talk about this more, but what’s done is done.”

“Fair,” I said. “I’m just voicing my feelings.”

“I should also say that she wants to come with us,” said Amaryllis.

“Where?” I asked, dumb-founded. “To Fel Seed? Fuck that, we’re not bringing a twelve-year-old there, no matter how precocious.”

“Why?” asked Amaryllis. With the way she was looking at me, I could tell that she was ready to pounce, depending on what my answer was.

“You want her to come?” I asked.

“I sped up the pregnancy and her childhood so that she could come,” said Amaryllis.

“And if I’m trying to think like you, then I guess I have to ask what she brings to the table,” I said. “She’s disposable?” I asked. “If she dies, it’s not a big deal, meaning that she fulfills a narrative function?”

“No,” said Amaryllis. “I was thinking that she has a wide variety of practical skills that might be of use in the Long Stairs. You said that it was, and I quote, ‘Trap City’. She’s got a good claim to being the best thief in the world, even at age twelve. Perhaps especially at age twelve.”

“And she volunteered?” I asked.

“She’s being paid,” said Amaryllis. “But I think she was just demanding money because she knew we had it and wanted to milk us as much as she could. She’s very contrary by nature. Even without lucre, I think she would demand to be a part of it, especially if she knew that you didn’t want her there.”

“Alright,” I said. “I don’t particularly like it, but I’ll defer to you and not complain too much about it. And from what little I saw of her, I’ll probably be wishing for her death within a few weeks.”

I realized it as soon as I’d said it, and watched Amaryllis quirk an eyebrow. “We don’t have a few weeks,” she said. “Based on the provisional schedule, we’re planning to zip through Fel Seed’s zone three days from now.”

“Yeah,” I said. “I know. Slip of the tongue.”

“It’s not too late to back out,” said Amaryllis. “We’ve committed nothing to this venture, not yet.”

“I know,” I said. “But that’s where Uther is, and if we’re going to bring this thing to a close, we have to go there sooner or later. If we don’t, I’m worried about the kinds of threats we’ll see.”

The Fel Seed Incident

Arthur was dead, and everything was terrible.

The campaign world pre-dated his death, otherwise I might not have had the will to flesh it out as much as I did, if you’ll pardon the pun. For the most part, I had taken the words from Jabberwocky and let my imagination run wild. Mome Rath had been the first of the menagerie, invented in the spur of the moment while waiting for a movie to start, and he’d set the stage for all the others: twisted creatures of immense size, usually with some particularly brutal or grotesque aspect to them.

Fel Seed was special. He was evil amplified a thousandfold, and he got meaner and more hardcore the more I thought about him. Campaigns had a way of altering the worlds that I’d put down into notebooks, and for Fel Seed, that meant that he just kept getting built up, mentioned in whispers in taverns, his name wielded to invoke fear and doom. There was a mystique to him, a feeling of deep lore, mostly built up by never saying too much directly about him, never so much as hinting at him having a stat block of any kind.

It might have been nice to think that it was just a matter of circumstances, but The Fel Seed Incident, or something like it, was probably inevitable with the way I’d been going.

“So how is this going to work, mechanically?” asked Reimer. He was the first one there, as he usually was, maybe because he had been instilled with the belief that on time was late, or maybe just so he could get some game business out of the way. I resented it, maybe because he wasn’t my favorite person.

“Does it matter?” I asked.

“I mean, yes, obviously,” said Reimer. “But you’ve been getting sloppy with mechanics, and I wanted to make sure that you weren’t going to, as they say, fuck it up.”

I didn’t reply to him. Instead, I just looked at my notes like there was something worthwhile there, which there manifestly wasn’t. I had a DM screen, something that I’d considered super lame until I’d gotten one for Christmas from Arthur.

“The canonical vorpal blade cuts off a head on a nat 20,” Reimer said, plowing on ahead, as he often did. “Obviously 5E rules are crap, because they mean you can’t use it against something like Fel Seed has been cryptically described as, either because he’s got legendary actions, or because he’s too big, or because he’s legendary, or something, and even if a nat 20 did work on him, sitting around for a bunch of rounds waiting on the perfect roll — I won’t say that it’s not fun, but it’s one of those things that gets really not fun at the tail ends, like if it happens right off the bat, or it takes so many rounds that we outright die.”

“Sure,” I said.

“So?” he asked, insistent. “Mechanically — if you want help with the mechanics?”

“Not really,” I said.

He sighed. “It took us three sessions to get this fucking sword,” said Reimer. “I just want to make sure that everyone has a good time, because lately, you haven’t been —”

But then Tom came in, and apparently Reimer didn’t feel like finishing the discussion in front of him.

“I texted Colin, he’s still coming,” said Tom. “He’s bringing Ana. That’s cool Joon?”

“Yeah,” I said. “Already talked to him about it.”

Colin was on the wrestling team, and apparently something of a prodigy. I’d gone to wrestling matches a few times and struggled to resist the urge to bury myself in my phone, but he’d always won, so good for him, I guess. Wrestling crept into his life a lot, because it seemed like he was always cutting or bulking or lifting weights or doing training. He was the most visibly muscular guy in our high school, more than anyone in any other sport. He was also a huge geek, reading more fantasy than anyone I knew, with a particular affection for dragons. I’d only gone over to his house one time, but his room had a wall of books, a bunch of trophies, medals, and ribbons for wrestling, and a bunch of tacky dragon statues that immediately called to mind the phrase ‘mall ninja shit’.

“This is a terrible introduction to D&D for Ana,” said Reimer. “Terrible introduction for Colin too, mind you, but he’s at least taking to it, and he isn’t quite coming in mid-stream.” This was Colin’s fourth session with us. He’d started right at the beginning of the quest for the vorpal sword.

“We should have five then,” Tom said. “Craig is in, Maddie is out, nothing from Tiff.”

“Thanks for coordinating,” I said. I felt guilty that I wasn’t doing it, not that I was expected to. It had usually been Arthur’s job, except when he was busy.

“Oh, no prob,” he replied. “Tonight is Fel Seed, right?”

“If, after getting this fucking sword, there’s another diversion, I’m going to mutiny,” said Reimer.

“What else is new?” I asked with a sigh.

Tom and Reimer talked about a book series that Tom was reading at Reimer’s insistence, something having to do with superheroes, and I busied myself with my notes, trying to force myself to do some more preparation. I had been giving preparation the cold shoulder lately, but I was good enough at improvising that most of the time it didn’t make all that much of a difference. At least, that was what I told myself.

Colin and Ana came together. Ana was his girlfriend, a fairly quiet girl who I’d never paid all that much attention to. They had been together for a year, and were inseparable in a way that I found obnoxious. I had kind of figured that if Colin was going to play with us, she would eventually join too, because they were never that far apart from each other, and there were lots of displays of affection between the two of them, holding hands, kissing in the hallways, that kind of thing. She was blonde and plain-looking, usually dressed in oversized shirts and baggy pants in a way that was, to my admittedly untrained eye, pretty unfashionable.

Tiff probably would have had a problem with me defining Ana as ‘Colin’s girlfriend’, but that’s what she was to me. Whatever personality she had, it seemed completely subsumed by her relationship with him. I had never talked to her outside of a few group projects and maybe once during a party or something, and she’d never stood out, maybe by choice. It was possible that she had her own rich fantasy life, and that was what she bonded with Colin over, but if so, it was invisible to me.

“Fel Seed tonight boys, right?” asked Colin, smiling as he took his seat. He had brought a case of Mountain Dew and a pack of doughnuts, which was nice, but nice in a kind of desperate way that made me feel sour towards him. This was his fourth session, and maybe there was a part of me that felt like he was drawn to the group because Arthur had died, which I definitely didn’t like. He was close with Tom, and had been invited before, but never shown interest.

Craig showed up late, which I was hopeful would get the random chatter out of everyone’s system, but that hope was dashed against the rocks, and it was another thirty minutes before my attempts to get us moving toward the game got us anywhere. Reimer really wanted to talk about the superhero thing, and Colin had read it, because Colin read everything, which meant a pretty boring conversation for everyone else, even when they tried to pull us in with some worldbuilding tidbits. I was just thankful that Maddie hadn’t been joining us, because I was pretty sure that Colin would have read some of the strange junk from the depths of the internet that she liked to plumb.

“Alright,” Reimer finally said, turning to me like I was the one holding things up. “What do we know about what the vorpal sword actually does, like, is there any way that we can test it?”

“To recap,” I said, glancing at Ana. “Fel Seed is the greatest horror in a land filled with horrors, and by some reckonings, he’s the progenitor of them all.”

“Progenitor?” asked Reimer. “Seriously dude?”

I glared at him. With Arthur gone, Reimer had been taking things less seriously, and whatever I was trying to weave, he would carelessly destroy. We were definitely on the outs, for a few reasons, but he was fucking with the one thing that I looked forward to every week.

“They’re just rumors,” I continued, ignoring him for now. “Fel Seed has his factories of flesh, and while some of the products of those organic madhouses are obvious, some of the factories are so large, their outputs so rarely seen, that people can only guess. Perhaps Fel Seed created the snicker-snacks, perhaps he created the Jubjub bird, or maybe it’s just a way for people to put a name to the ills of the world, to pretend that there really is a single string that can be cut.”

“But the sword cuts the string, right?” asked Tom.

“If you remember when you set out to get the sword,” I said, knowing that they had probably forgotten, “You were told that it was the sword that brought low creatures and men of myth. Supposedly it was the sword that cut through the marvelous creation of Hiawatha’s, killing man and oracular contraption in a single stroke. Supposedly it killed King Hal in a duel the very moment it touched him — not even breaking skin, just grazing the layer of wax that his armor was polished with. And of the Rilchiam, the less said, the better.”

“Dead though, right?” asked Tom.

“There are fates worse than death,” I replied. “And deaths so final they’re hard to speak of.”

“Question,” said Colin. “How does a sword deliver fates worse than death?”

“Probably lots of ways,” said Reimer. “Juniper can be very creative, when it comes to killing.” Reimer had lately made a habit of bringing a backup character to every game, the better to be able to keep on playing when he died. “Okay,” he said. “Joon, because the stakes are high, I’m going to grab a random civilian and attack them with the sword to see what its true power is.”

“Er,” said Tom. “You could just grab a random bandit instead.”

“Sure, sure,” said Reimer. “So, I wander around until I find a bandit, which you said there were plenty of, and I cut him down with the vorpal sword.”

“Do you remember, from last week, when the matriarch said that the vorpal sword was not lightly drawn?” I asked. “Do you remember reading through the scroll and seeing that it said the sword was so powerful that the mere act of unsheathing it put the wielder at risk?”

“I do,” replied Reimer. “But on the other hand, I don’t think that we can go into this battle without a plan, and we can’t have a plan unless we know how the sword physically functions, so if killing a rando bandit — a randit, if you will — means that we have a better chance of success, I’m willing to take that risk.”

Craig snorted. “I’ll be watching from a safe distance.”

“Why is the wizard using the sword at all?” asked Tom. “Shouldn’t it be someone who can fight?”

“It’s in-character,” Reimer argued. “And it’s just a bandit. Obviously on the day of, someone else will use it.”

“I grab the sword from Trentwhistle,” said Colin. “‘Wizard, a sword seems awkward in your hands, and should the worst happen, I fear you would not survive. We’ll need your intellect, going forward, but if I am maimed, there are comparable fighters you might find. Your life is too valuable; if there is risk, let me take it.’” Colin did voices, though only a little bit, in part because he wasn’t actually that far off from being a big, brawny fighter.

“Fine, I don’t contest having the vorpal sword taken from me,” said Reimer.

“Because you’d have lost the roll,” said Craig.

“Never go against a wizard when death is on the line,” muttered Reimer, but he was clearly enjoying himself.

“Gorn takes the sword, and, after a day of asking around the small village, finds a bandit camp,” I said. “They’re no match for him, and he slays all but the last one of them in the usual manner, whipping around like a whirling dervish, his normal sword constantly soaked in blood. Finally he approaches the last man, who is bleeding from the forehead but otherwise fine. It’s only then that he draws the vorpal blade.”

“What does it look like?” asked Colin.

“It’s a double-sided blade, perfectly reflective, but it reflects nothing but death. If you stare at the reflection, you can see a putrefied version of your own flesh, hanging off your bones, the grass behind you dead and brown, the birds resting on the ground, just carcasses, and the sun red and swollen in the sky. There’s a faint blue blur along the edge of the blade, as though it’s projecting a field of sharpness. The most notable thing though, once it’s drawn, is that the world seems to slow down to a tenth its speed. You’re slowed down too, with only your mind and eyes able to move normally, and it takes a few seconds — call it a round — to get your bearings and adjust to how slowly your body responds to your command. Once you’ve adjusted, you realize that your heart is beating at the same speed it normally was, blood moving at incredible speed through your body.”

“I tamp down my discomfort,” said Colin. “Then I raise the sword and bring it down on the bandit.”

“The moment your sword touches his skin, the world seems to stop, only your eyes able to move. You can feel the vorpal sword sucking at your life force, like a leech attached to your very soul,” I said. “You’re locked in now, in this timeless moment, while you decide how much of your life force to give up to the attack.”

“None though, right?” asked Reimer.

“It should be pretty obvious that’s not an acceptable answer,” I replied.

“What does ‘life force’ mean though, hit points?” he asked.

“You’re not even there, Reimer,” I said, keeping my focus on Colin.

“Then the minimum, I guess,” said Colin. “Wait, I can do better. Gorn gives as little of himself as possible, trying his best to resist the pull of the blade.”

“You sense the blade tasting the offer, in this moment of frozen time,” I replied. “Then you sense its contempt at the task you’ve set before it, this blade which has seen the death of so many beings of importance and strength. It takes twice as much as was offered. Roll 2d10.”

There was something that I didn’t like about Colin. Maybe it was that it seemed like he was taking Arthur’s spot, in more ways than one. For Colin, the game was like the books he spent so much of his time on, and doing the characters was an extension of the kind of fantasy life he’d been privately living in his head. On the surface, it was the same kind of energy that Arthur brought, a commitment to character that I might have found admirable in other circumstances. At the time, I wasn’t being nearly so introspective, I just knew that he was annoying me.

“Seven,” he said, looking at the dice.

“You lose that from your max hit points, permanently,” I replied. “It cannot be restored, not even by a wish or miracle.” I saw Reimer frown, but he held his objection. “Time starts back up as the life force leaves you, and you see the bandit sliced apart, not just at the point where the edge of the blade made contact with him, but at every single joint in his body. He falls apart, head falling off his neck, vertebrae disconnected, the knuckles of his fingers making a staccato sound as they hit the ground one after the other. He lays on the ground, completely dismembered. You get the sense that something more has happened to him, some metaphysical dismembering, but it’s beyond your ken.”

I was ready for Reimer to complain that this didn’t actually tell them anything. 2d10 hit points permanently lost didn’t translate into some concrete amount of damage, at least so far as the party was concerned, nor did it give much data about what impact it might have on Fel Seed. Reimer stayed silent though, maybe because Colin took the lead.

“I sheathe the vorpal blade, slowly and gingerly,” he said. “Then I return to the others, weakened but exuberant, because Fel Seed isn’t prepared for what we’re bringing him.”

“When we get the report from Gorn,” said Reimer, thinking about it for a bit, “Personally, I’m cautiously optimistic, but when the time comes, it seems like someone will probably have to make a heroic sacrifice, maybe more than one someone.” He glanced at me. “Juniper, are there ways of boosting hit points in this setting?”

“Yes, probably,” I said. “I haven’t looked at character sheets that much. The sword takes from your maximum though.”

“But we could bring people along and have them wield the sword?” asked Reimer.

“If you’re craven, yes,” I said.

“Not craven, no,” replied Reimer. “Just trying to be smart about it, given that Fel Seed is the worst of the worst, and we need to kill him one way or another, at virtually any cost. If that means getting mercenaries involved, then so be it.”

“No mercenary in his right mind would go up against Fel Seed,” I replied. I was feeling annoyed with Reimer, which was typical. Colin had at least been getting into it, but Reimer was fucking it up, taking something that had a glimmer of the heroic and steering away from it, toward the cold utilitarian bastard route. It was the kind of thing that Arthur was usually good about curbing.

Tom was looking at the ceiling, thinking. “What about people who believe in the greater good?” he asked.

“That’s the five of you,” I said. “Everyone else you’ve met — going through the list, anyone you would try either believes that you’re going on a fool’s errand, or can’t help you in any way. People are looking out for themselves, trying to grind out a living in this miserable world, not daring to dream bigger. The rare person who still dares to dream,” I realized that I’d just said the same thing twice and stumbled forward, “of killing something like Fel Seed — well, I guess you do find one, which is Ellnor, Ana’s character. Ana, are you fine with stumbling across Colin? Maybe you were captured by these random bandits? Or a bandit yourself that’s prepared to argue your case against the certainty of his mindless slaughter?”

“That’s fine, I guess,” she said, pretty much the first words out of her mouth. I wasn’t hopeful that she would stick with the group, but then again, I didn’t really want her to stick with the group. Ideally, she’d have just left and gone back to whatever bland hole she’d crawled out of.

“Ellnor, the only thing that saves you from being killed by Gorn as he descends on the bandits is the fact that you’re in shackles,” I said. “It’s not clear what the bandits were going to do with you, but the best guess is that they were going to sell you into slavery, maybe to one of the corrupt Grand Houses that hasn’t yet fallen to the horrors. How you got captured, or whatever, can be up to you.”

She gave me an unsure look. The last thing I really wanted to be doing with this session was shepherding someone through their first time playing a game like this, and Reimer had been right, this was probably a horrible introduction to D&D.

“I break her shackles with my bare hands,” said Colin. “I can do that, right?”

“Roll for me,” I said. “Add your strength modifier.”

He rolled. “Thirty-six total,” he said.

“That can’t be right,” I replied.

“Strength mod, not score,” said Reimer, without even looking at Colin’s character sheet. He had helped both of them make characters.

“Oh, then, uh, twenty-one,” he said.

“Still more than enough to break the poor iron that these bandits had,” I said. “Ellnor, you’re free. Hopefully after Gorn explains what he was doing out here and his ultimate mission, you demonstrate that you have skills of your own and want to come along?”

“I can shoot a bow,” she said, looking down at her sheet. “And Fel Seed is a bad guy?”

“He’s the bad guy,” said Tom.

“Eh,” said Reimer. “With how long we’ve been in this campaign, better to think about him as the season finale, if it’s like a British season.”

“They say ‘series’ there,” said Craig.

“Well that’s just confusing,” said Tom.

Reimer scowled at Craig. “Did you think I didn’t know that they call a season a series?” he asked.

“Eh, fuck off,” said Craig, not bothering to continue the conversation any further.

“Ellnor, did you want to tell us a bit about your character?” I asked. “Tragic backstory, connections to others, passions, hobbies, things like that?” I had meant to send her a text earlier in the week, but never got around to it. It was really the kind of thing that Colin and Reimer should have helped her with.

“I don’t know,” she said. “I guess I’ve got a dog?”

“Sure,” I said, wishing that she would give me something, anything, that I could work with. I was betting that she had a dog at home, though I knew very little about her. “But like, a personal vendetta against Fel Seed?”

“I guess,” she said. “He killed my father?”

“That’s statistically likely,” said Reimer. “Fel Seed has killed a lot of people.”

“He’s also statistically likely to have raped your mother,” said Craig. I saw Ana wince at that, but maybe I was just imagining it, and I made an effort to move on.

“Do we want to do introductions with the rest of the group?” I asked, hoping that the answer was yes so that I could sit back and zone out for a bit as they talked amongst themselves about character stuff. I had done very little prep for the session, and one of the ways to pad time was to have in-character conversations. It wasn’t just padding, because sometimes that was the meat and potatoes, but Ana was, frankly, sapping my will to live.

The introductions did, in fact, take quite a bit of time. The story of acquiring the vorpal sword was told in full, as well as a few mentions of people who were now dead, whether they were players, enemies, or unfortunate NPCs. It was a common phenomenon in D&D games for a mission originally undertaken by a small group of people to be completed by a completely different group of people, and while we weren’t quite there yet, we were on our way.

“So, are we ready to set off to Fel Seed’s zone?” I asked, when it seemed like the conversation might threaten to turn towards something that wasn’t D&D. After so many years, my sense for the natural breaks in conversation was fairly finely honed.

“He’s basically asking if we’re ready to die,” said Reimer.

“Ready and willing,” said Tom, putting on his exaggerated ‘I’m a cool guy’ voice, which he only ever did when he was clowning around. Tom knew how uncool he was, and joked about it, which I had lately been finding extremely annoying.

“Gorn isn’t ready to die,” said Colin. He smiled at us. “But he is very ready to kill.”

“Any other preparations you want to make before you go?” I asked. “Provisions you need to buy, spells you want to learn, anything like that? You have a 20% discount from Madame Eich, if you want to spend the time going a few days west.”

There was some consulting of character sheets, which eventually led to some murmurs that everyone was fine.

“You set off toward Fel Seed then,” I said. “You take the Marrow Road, once the most important trade route across the Twelve Kingdoms, but now long decimated, with many of the towns fortified against refugees, outlaws, bandits, and monsters, unwilling to help strangers, unwilling to engage in trade, if they still function as towns at all.” This was the first thing that I had actually planned for the session, and we were getting to it an hour and a half after we’d started.

“How do they eat then?” asked Reimer.

It annoyed me that he was asking now, given that this had all been mentioned before, but either he was asking for the benefit of Ana and Colin, or he had just forgotten. “Poorly,” I said. “The fields are going fallow, the farmers working only under armed guard, and the people are starving. Of late, people have taken to eating the misbegotten creations that they find invading their lands, consuming whatever escapes from Fel Seed’s domain, or is deliberately sent out by him. No one wants to, but it’s the only reliable source of food given how unproductive the fields are. It’s not without complications.”

“Create food and water?” asked Reimer.

I was getting pissed off, because this was exactly the kind of thing he always asked about. The truth was, this was the kind of setting that would really benefit from removing that kind of spell, but I hadn’t done it upfront because I didn’t want the hassle, and hadn’t been looking at character sheets, so I had no idea whether anyone was using it. Sometimes I hated D&D for all the unwanted baggage it brought in.

“There aren’t enough clerics and there aren’t enough wizards,” I said. “The nobles are fed, but keeping everyone else fed just can’t happen given the limited resources available. And every commoner that is fed, every sick child given clean water, signifies, in the final sense, a theft from the effort to keep the nobility safe and secure.”

That was a reversal of a famous Eisenhower quote about how the war effort steals from the needy, but no one seemed to get it. Arthur would have: it was one of his favorite pieces of rhetoric. Tiff probably would have gotten it too, but she had stopped coming, and I didn’t blame her for that.

I cleared my throat a bit, when it became clear that Reimer wasn’t going to try to chase us down the rabbit hole of justifying a whole world on the basis of 5E D&D mechanics, which we’d done more than once, calculating and recalculating, justifying and litigating.

“The clearest sign that you’re transitioning into Fel Seed’s dominion are the plants, which vanish entirely over the course of a few miles of the Marrow Road,” I said. “They’re replaced by their own fleshy variants. The grass is replaced by hair sticking up from the ground, the vines become veins, the trees turn into large bony towers with flaps of skin instead of leaves. If you squint, you might be able to mistake it for a natural scene.”

“I look for eyes,” said Colin.

“Make a roll,” I said. “Perception.”

“Twenty-one,” he said.

I nodded. “You see them dangling from a nearby tree, like small fruits, and as you look closer, you can see them other places too, peeking out from a bush, from birds that are barely visible in the distance, and just once, poking up from the road that you’re walking on, half-hidden by a cobble.”

“Well, fuck,” said Craig.

“The question is how many encounters we have to fight until we actually get to him,” said Reimer. “Joon, are you sure there’s no teleportation circle anywhere in his realm?”

“I’m a thousand percent sure,” I said. “Still want to try your gambit of trying for an astral explosion and randomly getting dumped next to him?”

“Nope,” he replied.

“Wait, are we on horses?” asked Tom.

“A horse would buck and flee if you tried to take it into this place,” I said. “They know better.”

“I have phantom steeds,” said Reimer. “As a ritual.”

“Have we always had those?” asked Tom.

“Juniper never pressed us on travel arrangements,” said Reimer. “There’s some rules stuff that makes them less good than normal horses, if you have someone to just give you normal horses, and if you can just treat the horses like motorcycles that don’t need to be taken care of, don’t need to graze, et cetera.”

“Fine, up on the phantom steeds you go,” I replied.

“Takes fifty-five minutes,” said Reimer. “And then I have to keep re-casting the spell, but you can do that mounted.”

“Sure, sure,” I replied, not caring in the slightest. “You all continue down the Marrow Road, with the realm of flesh all around you, riding the unearthly steeds and staying on your guard. It’s just before sunset when you see the first city of Fel Seed’s domain —”

“Which is how big?” asked Colin.

“Eh,” I said. “Sizeable, you’ll be traveling for days. Let’s say, about the size of Kansas.”

“Wait, before we get to the city, I send my familiar ahead to scout,” said Reimer.

“Okay,” I replied. I’d been going to tell them anyway. “You see a city that’s almost what it once was, not terribly big by modern standards, ten thousand, perhaps, with a small stone fort sitting in the middle and merchants and churches around that. The stone wall is broken in several places, no longer serving any defensive purpose. Sitting on top of the stone wall at various intervals are fleshly creatures, each at least nine feet tall, each of a slightly different composition. All of them watch your familiar as it flies overhead. You see similar creatures roaming the streets, some of them tethered to the surroundings by what look like veins as thick as a forearm, others sleek-looking, like someone stripped the skin off a dog, leaving only raw muscle behind. You see humans too, but only women, most of them that you can spot standing at doorways or looking out windows, and one who catches your eye is holding something swaddled in her arms, a lump of misshapen flesh with too many eyes.”

“I need to use the bathroom,” said Ana. She got up before we could even tell her where it was.

“Is she okay?” asked Tom.

Colin hesitated. “Yeah.”

“We can wait,” I said. “You can talk strategy, if you want to, or ask some questions.”

“So,” said Reimer. “Define ‘too many eyes’. Are we talking three instead of two, or like, covered in eyes?”

“Covered in eyes,” I said. “Picture a baby whose limbs have grown in at random, and whose oversized head had the nose and mouth removed to make more room for the eyes.”

“She’s just a normal woman?” asked Tom.

“A human woman, yes,” I said. “As are most of the women that Reimer sees. This was human land, before Fel Seed came along. Sprinkled in among them are a few elven women, gnomish women, some other typical species.”

“Wait,” said Reimer. “If the entire landscape around us has been changed by him, and that’s true for hundreds of miles, then why the fuck is he using these women as incubators?”

“For fun,” I said. “For sport. He could grow whatever creatures he wanted without them, and he did when he was getting settled. This is just his way of keeping himself entertained. It probably goes without saying that these women can’t leave.”

While I was speaking, Colin’s phone had let out a little chirp. When he looked at it, his face was frozen for just a bit.

“Joon, can I talk to you in private for a bit?” he asked.

“Sure,” I said. “We can take five.”

My heart was beating faster. This seemed like exactly the kind of thing that I didn’t want to have to deal with, some kind of social encounter that I just wasn’t built for. I was hoping that I was wrong, and he just had some kind of plan that he didn’t want to share with the group, but I hadn’t missed that Ana had taken her phone with her when she’d gone into the bathroom.

“What’s up?” I asked, once we were out in the hallway and had closed the door.

“Ana’s just,” Colin started. “I guess feeling a little bit uneasy about all the implied sexual violence?”

“Ah,” I said. I could feel my face getting flushed. “I mean, I’m trying not to be explicit.”

“That’s not really helping,” he said. “I mean, the implication is there, it’s, uh, not even really veiled, Fel Seed is kidnapping and then raping all these women, and — you can get why she’s upset?”

“Yeah,” I said. Why the fuck did you bring her along? I didn’t ask, but the thought was definitely going through my head. Fel Seed had been telegraphed about as hard as a boss encounter could be, and no, it wasn’t strictly necessary that Fel Seed was doing terrible things with these women, but to leave it out — well, it would change the texture of the whole adventure. That was what I told myself, anyway.

Colin looked down at his phone, and I couldn’t see what was on the screen, but my guess was that he was re-reading the text he’d gotten from her. “Can we like, cool it a little bit?” he asked.

I tried to think of a diplomatic way of saying ‘No, fuck off’, but nothing came to mind. “Sure,” I said. “I mean, I can try. It’s kind of — I mean, I’ll improvise, no problem.” I felt the weight of that settle uncomfortably on me, easy words that I didn’t know if I could follow through on.

It was kind of a central conceit. You couldn’t say that Fel Seed’s cruelty and depravity knew no bounds and then say, ‘oh, well except in this way, if it makes you uncomfortable’. It all would have rankled less if it had been for someone else, someone I had liked or at least known, but it was for Ana, who didn’t seem to give a shit about the game, and was only there to spend more time with her boyfriend.

We went back into the room, and I sat down, trying to think about what I could do. I was still feeling flushed and anxious.

“So,” said Reimer. “The question is, do we actually have any reason to go into this town? Fel Seed isn’t there, right?”

“It’ll add some time if you want to go around,” I said. “That’s it.”

“Well,” said Tom. “That’s kind of what we were talking about, because there are people to rescue in there.”

“We can’t just leave these people here,” said Colin, jumping straight in, even though he’d missed what they were talking about.

Ana slipped back into the room, so quiet that I might not have noticed her. She wasn’t looking at me, just at what was in front of her.

“Obviously we can leave them,” said Reimer. “They’re living terrible lives, and have been for years at this point, and even if we had the firepower to kill everything, which we don’t, that doesn’t affect the root of the problem, which is Fel Seed.”

“It’s just set dressing,” said Craig. “Juniper just wants to show us how big and bad Fel Seed is, again.”

“They’re still people,” said Colin, ignoring that. “Unless you’re saying that we come back for them?”

“Sure, we could,” said Reimer. “I don’t suppose Juniper will tell us what happens to all the bone trees and hair grass and horrible monsters with footlong dongers once we take the vorpal blade to Fel Seed’s throat? Like, will they all die, or all go berserk?”

“You have no way of knowing,” I replied. “Are you doing anything with the city or not?”

“No,” said Reimer. “Unless we think there’s some loot in it for us?”

“No loot, no,” I said.

“We’re heroes though,” said Colin, furrowing his brow.

“Oh sweet summer child,” replied Craig.

“I just need to know what you’re doing,” I said.

Reimer turned to Colin. “Fel Seed is watching us, yes? The best case scenario right now is that he knows where we are and is letting us be, waiting to see whether or not we try anything. I don’t know if he’s planning on a pivot to tourism or what, but that's the absolute best case. More likely, he’s marshalling forces, erecting — and I do mean erecting — an unassailable position in the metropolis of flesh.”

“City of a Thousand Brides,” I said.

“Really?” asked Reimer. “Metropolis of Flesh has a better ring to it. Plus a thousand seems low.”

“Well maybe when you inevitably get captured, Fel Seed will put you on a Naming Committee,” I said. “Of course, your nervous system will be made into a blanket that gets a flogging at the top of every hour, so I’m not sure how much use you’ll be coming up with clever and evocative names.”

“Yeah, most likely I end up naming everything ‘Agh, ow, stop!’” replied Reimer, grinning at me. He turned back to Colin. “Point being, we’ve been moving through Fel Seed’s land of horrors relatively unimpeded, and I want to keep it that way, if for some reason he thinks that we’re not here to cause trouble. You want to wait to trip the alarms when you’re close enough to strike him down.”

“Fine,” said Colin, with a glance at Ana. “The world forces us to make these choices because the world itself is cruel and unfair. If every innocent could be saved, we would do it, but we are not so blessed.”

“On you go then, skirting around the edge of the village, through eerie charnel woods that are casually littered with the bones of unknown people,” I said. “Maybe left there from the massacre when Fel Seed took over this place, or maybe the remains of his creations that he’s decided don’t make the grade, it’s difficult to say.”

“He sometimes fucks up his creations?” asked Reimer.

I thought about that for a moment. “It would be more proper to say that he uses stochastic processes in making his creations. The, uh,” I glanced at Ana. “Part of the secondary purpose of the incubation processes he uses is that it’s a way of randomizing. He’s a tinker.”

“Stochastic?” asked Reimer. “Jesus Juniper, are you trying to wring as much use as possible from your thesaurus?”

“It was one of Arthur’s favorite words,” I said, staring him down. I didn’t invoke Arthur’s name lightly, and it felt dangerous and unfamiliar on my tongue. Reimer sat back a bit and waved his hand, dismissing that. “Look, you get through the woods and back on the Marrow Road, having decided not to engage with the town. It happens twice more that you see a place like that, one a fair bit smaller and without walls, the other larger, built to ford a river that runs brown. Both times you have the same conversations, but the calculus is always the same, and the conversations become rote.” I took a drink of water, waiting to see whether anyone would challenge that account. “And then you crest a hill along a path that seems to be cobbled with enormous teeth, only to find it splayed out in front of you, the City of a Thousand Brides.”

“Er, ‘bride’ seems like the wrong word,” said Colin.

“Fel Seed seems to think of himself as a god, and it’s possible that he is,” I said. “The marriages are consecrated by him.” I shrugged. “You might compare it to arranged marriages, or forced marriages, similar to what still goes on in other parts of the world. Etymology is difficult even in the best of times though, and the origin of the name isn’t one that anyone knows.”

“I want to roll for it,” said Reimer.

“Of course you do,” I said, rolling my eyes. “History, then.”

“Twenty-six,” he replied.

“You have no clue,” I said. “It’s not like the etymology was recorded in a book somewhere, or like there are libraries where you can find bundles of periodicals, if it even came from a periodical. Sometimes information is just lost, even if you did get a twenty-six. At best, you’ve heard a few contradictory rumors.”

“You do remember that part of your job as a DM is to say yes, right?” asked Reimer.

“I’m saying that you don’t know,” I replied. “No amount of research is going to let you know. Unless you beseech a god of knowledge, or travel through time, you’re never learning the origin of the name.”

“Fine, Religion check to see if I know the god of knowledge,” said Reimer.

“You don’t need a check, because it’s in the worldbuilding doc,” I said. “Go read it there, it doesn’t matter, moving on.” I was feeling flushed, not just because I was annoyed, but because I had no idea what the name of the god was. Probably something from The Hunting of the Snark.

“Can you give us the lay of the land?” asked Colin. “What does the city look like?”

I looked down at my notes, which didn’t have all that much. I had always saved descriptions for the last minute. “It’s a mockery of a city,” I said. “Where a city has central roads that branch out into neighborhoods and districts, this city is shot through with roads seemingly at random, with none of the planning or naturalistic design of a real city. There seems to be no thought given to logistics or aesthetics, to praxis of any kind. The buildings aren’t made of stone or wood, of course, instead favoring different variations on flesh, struts of bone, insulation with sheets of fat, walls held together with strips of flesh or occasionally hair. A real city clusters larger buildings at its center, but here there’s nothing like that, with large and small buildings next to each other at random, veritable skyscrapers next to small huts that look like oversized blisters. Through the city, and visible from your vantage point, the sole concession to practicality is a river running through the middle, one which goes in a murky brown and comes out as a stream of offal, shit, piss, blood, pus, and more than a few bodies, all of which drains into a vast nearby lake created from the sludge the city produces. From what you’ve heard of Fel Seed’s power, this all must be entirely by choice. His power is so vast and fine-tuned that he could have made this into a paradise.”

“And we have no idea why he didn’t?” asked Colin.

“He’s evil,” I said. “He made the city ugly and disordered because he wanted to inflict that on people. The river of excrement running through the city is there because it suits him. The one exception to all this ugly, disorganized mess is the citadel at the center, not the biggest building, but the only one that’s clean.”

“The question is at what point he’s going to try to stop us,” said Reimer. “Assuming that he’s going to try at all.”

“Probably when we produce the vorpal blade in his throne room,” said Craig. “Seems like there’s a lot of city between us and him right now? Like, we would probably die if we had to fight all of them?”

“It’s hard to know,” I said. “There are people moving through the city, some of them in cages made of bone, others monsters of flesh or fleshly fluid. What purpose each serves is unclear.”

“We should rescue the women,” said Colin. “They’ll be able to tell us more.”

“The time has come for us to be proper heroes, eh?” asked Reimer.

“I feel like we haven’t been proper heroes at all this campaign,” said Tom, sounding slightly sad.

“You said cages,” said Colin, turning to me. “Any close to the outskirts? Preferably without armed guards?”

“You spot one,” I said. “A cage of bone trundling along an outer road, transporting three women from one place to another, moving along not on wheels, but legs that seem to be mostly sinew. Walking alongside it are two creatures, one tall and lanky with knife-like claws that drag along the road, the other more portly, mostly made of belly, with a huge mouth and fat lips.”

Combat followed. It was pretty rote. The larger one was revealed to spring across the battlefield, doing swiping attacks with his claws as he bounded from place to place, while the portly one swallowed people whole. Tom nearly died, Reimer was knocked unconscious and then brought back, Ana suffered a serious wound and then got healed, and at the end of it, both of Fel Seed’s monsters were killed. It took a little bit more than an hour.

“But why even have guards?” asked Reimer. “I mean, this is his city, he’s all-powerful, why have guards, or police, or anything like that? According to you, the only reason we didn’t immediately die on entering his domain is that we have poison and disease immunity?”

“You think so, anyway,” I said. “He’s got complete control of all things biological, which means that he can create hyper-targeted diseases and poisons, then use various mechanisms to saturate the air with them. You’ve been breathing in spores and particulates since you entered his domain.”

“So the guards?” asked Colin.

“He likes hurting people, I think,” said Tom, frowning at me a bit. “The guards aren’t to make sure that no one escapes, or to kill people like us, —”

“There’s no one like us,” said Craig.

“It’s kind of like, uh, just a show of power?” asked Tom. “Like North Korea doing a military parade.”

“It’s poisoning someone with polonium,” said Craig, smiling a bit.

Reimer sighed. “You do not, under any circumstances, have to hand it to Vladimir Putin.”

“Is there a way to free the women?” asked Colin. “Break the bones? Are they bound?”

“Right,” I said. I was pretty clearly off my game, since that was the kind of thing that should have been described before the fighting started, or maybe even worked into the fight itself. “The cage is made of twisted bone, and is the first thing you’ve seen that’s almost a little bit pretty. It’s a pure white, looking like the bones of a cancer patient, —”

“Uh, what?” asked Tom, raising his hand a bit. “‘Bones of a cancer patient’?”

“Well,” I said. “I’d need to google a picture, but metastatic bone cancer makes the bones a bit furry, or with petals, or spikes, that kind of thing. So here, it’s not smooth bone in all places, it’s like lace where it’s between the major support structures. The women are hooked in there, by twisted strips of bone.”

“I start freeing them,” said Colin. “Can you describe them?”

“One an elf, short-haired and glassy-eyed, not responding to you, nor responsive to the battle as it was happening, one a gnome, looking angry, spent most of her time calling for help, and the third a human woman, looking withdrawn,” I said. I glanced at my sheet of random names for people, hoping that I wouldn’t be asked, because it never mattered, and was one more thing for me to remember.

“And do I free them then?” asked Colin.

“With a few swings of your sword, you do,” I said. “The elf sits down where she is, not moving or saying anything, while the gnome grabs a shard of bone from the ground, wielding it as a makeshift weapon, though not against you. After a brief pause, the human woman does the same.”

“Do you have names?” asked Colin, doing his voice.

“No response from the elf,” I said. “The gnome says her name is Merria. And the human woman, pausing for a moment before responding, drives her shard of bone straight into her own neck, wrenching it to the side to open as wide of a wound as she can.”

I waited for Craig to make the obvious joke, which was that this sure was a weird name, but he just looked a little uncomfortable.

“As she falls, the clothing slips to the side, revealing that she was pregnant,” I continued.

Ana got up and left the room, not even saying anything.

“She okay?” asked Tom.

“One sec,” said Colin, getting up and going after her.

“Is she okay?” Tom asked again, this time directing the question at us.

“Ana, or the girl?” I asked.

“Wait,” said Reimer. “I should be able to stop the woman from killing herself, right? Like, let’s say for the sake of argument that you can do a coup de grace on yourself, which doesn’t exist in this edition.”

“Massive damage,” I said.

“Well how much fucking damage can a shard of bone do in the hands of a level 1 commoner?” asked Riemer. “How much hp did she have?”

“I don’t want to argue this,” I said, leaning back slightly. I wondered whether Ana or Colin would return. I was feeling drained, not just from the session, but in my life as a whole.

I had been thinking of ending things. It was at the back of my brain, a little thought that didn’t seem like it would ever go away, the easy way out. I hadn’t made plans, but I had thought about what my plans would be, if I ever decided on that option.

Colin came back in, grabbed Ana’s stuff, then left again. I noticed that he’d left his own stuff, and briefly wondered whether or not he intended to stay for the rest of the session. I didn’t have to wonder for long, because he came back and sat down.

“Okay,” he said. The muscles of his jaw were clenched, and he was sitting forward in the chair with his elbows on the table, showing the tension in his arms. “Sorry about that,” he said, but his voice was tight. “Let’s get on with it.”

“Is Ana okay?” asked Tom.

“No,” said Colin. “She’s going home.”

“You don’t need to stay,” said Tom. “We can table this until —” he glanced at me. “We maybe try again later.”

“It’s important to me to see this through,” said Colin, staring me down. I found myself very aware of how easy it would be for him to kill me with his bare hands. Even failing that extreme, I wasn’t a fighter, and he was a prodigy at the closest thing to sanctioned fighting our school had.

A brief moment of fantasy went through my head. I imagined Colin fighting me, things coming to blows, and me somehow winning by being totally ready to go nuts. Colin was a wrestler, but there were rules in wrestling, and I would be able to do all of the things that were normally prohibited, like pulling hair, biting, going for the eyes or groin … it was the kind of fantasy that I could completely recognize as a juvenile one, but it still had an allure to it that was hard to resist. In reality, Colin could probably punch me once in the face, and I would be weeping on the floor through broken teeth.

“Alright,” I said. “What are you doing?”

“We go to Fel Seed’s palace,” said Colin, giving a brief glance at the others. “The women have to be left to their own devices. There wasn’t even a point in saving them from the cages.”

“What are we doing with Ana’s character?” asked Tom.

“I can play her,” said Colin, taking up her sheet and adding it to his own. He looked at me. “We’re going to the palace, right?”

“Right,” I said. In the face of his visible anger, it was hard for me not to be angry. “You walk down the streets of the City of a Thousand Brides, weapons drawn, on full alert. You see more monsters as you go, but they stay back, not making a move toward you. You see more women, sometimes at the windows, other times at doorways, but they’re under guard in some cases, or have been made immobile in others. The whole place smells of flesh and blood, and you cross the Putrid River on a bridge made of ligaments that sways on your passing.” I waited for someone to object, to say that it wasn’t something their character did, but if you waited for explicit instructions on every single thing, the game would grind to a halt. There was supposed to have been an encounter on the ligament bridge, but I didn’t have the stomach for it. “There are no guards at the palace, and the doors are standing wide for you. The insides are fully furnished, with none of the obvious aesthetic that’s outside. You see lanterns hanging from chains, red carpets, tapestries, brickwork, all the hallmarks of the most advanced civilizations you have knowledge of, including the ones that have now fallen.”

A lot of that I had written out ahead of time, or at least written out in my head while falling asleep. I was thankful for that, because it was easy to get back into the flow of things and try to forget. I was already sure that I was going to feel bad about what had happened with Ana for at least a day or two, even if she never should have sat down at the table with us.

“Let me guess,” said Reimer. “All of the stuff we see, everything that we look at, on closer inspection is just some horrible biological thing, right?”

I hesitated for a moment, then nodded, because that was a good idea. “It’s clear now that when people said that Fel Seed had a complete control of biology, they weren’t exaggerating. The lanterns are lit by bioluminescence, the carpets are some kind of cillia, the bricks are keratin, dentin, bone, or something like that, and the places where it looks like wood are some kind of dried or hardened skin that’s been patterned to have a grain.”

“I thought wood was biological?” asked Tom.

“Yeah, but that’s not terrifying enough,” said Craig.

“We go through the palace,” said Colin.

“Armed and ready for anything,” said Reimer.

“You pass through two halls of monsters,” I said. “The first seems to be a museum, with the monsters standing, posed, on pedestals, not fossilized, not statues, just creatures that he made and wanted to display. They’re living out their lives there, unmoving.”

“We continue on,” said Reimer, circling his fingers in the air.

“You come to the throne room,” I said, skipping ahead. “You might have expected guards, but it’s just Fel Seed, sitting on an elaborate throne. He’s —” I hesitated, because what I had planned was a step too far, something that I’d thought up and had been haunting my imagination. I had nothing else though, no other directions to go in. There was too much on my mind to spin something else up. “There’s a woman in front of him, fellating him, but once you enter, he grabs a sword leaning up against the throne and decapitates her with a single stroke.”

“Jesus, Juniper,” said Craig, rolling his eyes.

“Fireball,” said Reimer.

“I wanted to talk to him,” said Colin.

“Roll for initiative,” I said.

“Wait, what could you possibly get from talking to a guy like that?” asked Reimer.

“Answers,” Colin replied.

“Well,” said Reimer. “We certainly don’t have the element of surprise, and we’re not tactically set up, so I guess if you want, I’ll hold off on shooting fireballs. If you get within range of the area of effect, I’m not to blame for what happens.”

Colin stared at me. He’d lost none of his intensity, and while for me it might have started to settle back into a normal session (or what passed for normal in these times), for him it still seemed to be about something else.

“I want to know why he does all this perverted shit,” said Colin. “I want to know what he gets from it.”

“You’re asking him, in those terms?” I asked.

“Sure,” he replied.

“Fel Seed gives you a bored sigh,” I replied. “‘Pleasure, mortal. It’s the reason that every single person does every single thing they do, whether they’re willing to admit it or not.’ He removes the head that’s still nestled in his crotch and tosses it aside, then rises from the throne, standing nine feet tall. ‘I killed that woman because I wanted to see the look on your face.’”

“But the monsters,” said Colin. “The river of shit and blood that runs through this place?”

“‘It’s about power,’” I said. “‘The power to hurt people, to make them feel fear and revulsion. The river is there so that it will loom large in the mind. I drown people in that river, and there is a satisfaction in knowing that they’ve spent months or years thinking about that fate.’”

“And why haven’t you killed us?” asked Colin.

“Fel Seed looks you over. ‘It’s been too long since someone has made any serious attempt on my life’, he replies, ‘I thought I might enjoy watching the hope drain from your eyes. I thought I would like to see the life leave your body as I strangled you, one by one.’”

“Oh, are we doing Big Talk?” asked Craig. He leaned forward in his chair and looked at me. “I tell Fel Seed that when I’m done with him, his bones will be scattered to the four winds, his blood salted, his throat pissed in, uh, …”

“Personally, I’ll fart in his general direction,” said Tom. “But I’ll do it privately and not make a big show of it.”

“Fel Seed won’t just be killed,” said Colin. “He’ll be erased from history and memory, the evidence of his life ground away by directed randomness until it’s lost to even our own minds. There won’t be a scrap of him left.”

“Nice,” said Reimer. “Now we roll for initiative?”

“Sure,” I said.

I added them into the turn tracker that I had set up, then put Fel Seed before any of them. After that, I drew out positions on the battle mat, then let them put down whatever they had for minifigures.

“Fel Seed goes first,” I said. “He reaches out toward Ellnor, standing in the middle of you all, and his fingers split in two, then in four, until the tips of them are barely visible. They shoot out from his hand faster than the speed of sound, and before you can do a damned thing about it, he’s got her tied down in ropes of flesh next to him. Reimer, you’re next.”

“We don’t get reactions?” asked Reimer.

“No,” I said. “It happens too fast, and unless I missed some horrible exploit you’ve got, you can’t react at the speed of sound.”

“Not yet, no,” said Reimer. “But mechanically I can react to lasers, and, eh, nevermind.”

“What happens to her?” asked Colin.

“To Ellnor?” I asked. I stared at her minifig. “She’s going to get added to his collection.”

“Fuck off,” he said, sitting back in his chair a bit. “Why are you such a fucking asshole?”

“You understand that it’s a game, right?” I asked. “It’s not real.”

“It’s your fucking job to make it feel real,” said Colin. “You’re doing everything that you can to bring some sense of realism, or at least emotion to this. The emotions that you choose are calculated to piss people off, or just make them unhappy.”

I wanted someone to step in, and tell him that wasn’t true, but all I got from the rest of the group was silence. “This is because of Ana?” I asked. “You never should have brought her. You understood what Fel Seed was like, and you fucking brought her anyway, because she can’t spend half an hour without you. I’m not going to turn on a dime for you, and I’m certainly not going to do it for her.”

“I wasn’t asking you to turn on a dime,” he said. “I just wanted you to maybe have a bit less rape in the whole thing.”

“It’s the City of a Thousand Brides!” I yelled. “Every single fucking thing that I’ve said about this place has let you know what it’s like! If your dumb cunt of a girlfriend —”

Colin stood up from his chair and for a moment I thought he was going to knock me out. Maybe that was going through his mind as well. Instead, without another word, he gathered his things and left. The character sheets stayed where they were.

“Was it something I said?” I asked. No one found it funny.

Tom looked uncomfortable. “Colin is a friend.”

“Yeah,” I said. “I just — maybe if it were some other campaign, but this is the one we’re in the middle of, and —”

“It’s never stopped you before,” said Reimer. “You drop campaigns more often than you wash a pair of jeans.”

“Oh, so it’s time to gang up on me?” I asked. “Fuck you.”

“He’s a friend,” said Tom. “Maybe not a friend of yours, but he’s a friend of mine. And Ana — I don’t know the full story, and I wouldn’t tell it if I did, but I’m pretty sure something bad happened to her. The kind of bad thing that you never want to tell people about? Which might be why she wanted you to shy away from, you know, that kind of thing?”

That felt like a punch to the gut. “I don’t want to litigate this,” I said. “Reimer, it’s your turn.”

“You still want to keep playing, after all that?” asked Reimer.

“He’s committed,” said Craig, nodding. “Or he should be committed, not sure which.”

“I need to send a text to Colin,” said Tom. “But I’m last in turn order, so, I guess if we’re still playing …”

“We are,” I said.

“Fine,” said Reimer. “Then I blast the fucker with a fireball, sculpting it around Ellnor, just in case she’s not completely fucked by whatever he’s doing.” He reached across the table and grabbed both character sheets that had been left sitting there. “I’ll play these. Colin was the one with the vorpal sword.”

We went through the numbers of combat, saving throws for half damage, a load of dice for the fireball, and some mumbling from me about how quickly Fel Seed recovered from the blast of fire.

“I move as far away as possible, then yell at Gorn to draw the blade,” said Reimer. “And then it should be his turn.” He looked down at Colin’s character sheet.

“Okay,” I said.

“Gorn draws the vorpal sword,” said Reimer. “He charges toward Fel Seed, screaming at the top of his lungs, then puts absolutely all of his life force into the hit, draining himself down to a raisin in the process. Wait, revise that, all but the last scrap of life.” He rolled the dice out where everyone could see it, and it came up a natural 20.

“That hits,” I said.

“And he flies apart into pieces?” asked Reimer. “Every joint disconnected from every other joint?”

“Fel Seed looks down at it, lodged halfway through his arm,” I said. “Then he looks at Gorn, and a slow smile spreads across his face. ‘The vorpal blade would never hurt its master.’”

Reimer groaned. “Come the fuck on,” he said. “We spent fucking ages getting that stupid sword, the effect was at least a little cool, and now this?”

“Maybe we should stop for the night,” said Tom, who was checking his phone way too often for my tastes.

“We’ve barely started,” said Craig. “And if Juniper wants to kill us, it shouldn’t take us that long. Just give Fel Seed a bunch of turns in a row, make every attack insta-kill, easy as that. His turn, right?”

“Tom goes last in the turn order,” I said. There was another chirp from Tom’s phone, and he glanced at it for a moment, biting his lower lip, before looking back at me.

“Uh,” said Tom. “How injured does he look?”

“Pristine,” I said. “Flawlessly clear skin, not even any soot on him.”

“I … try to talk to him?” asked Tom.

“In the middle of combat?” I asked.

“I yell?” asked Tom.

“You yell to be heard over the sounds of swords and fireballs,” I replied. “What do you yell?”

“I yell out that maybe we can make a deal,” said Tom. “Maybe we can show him that it’s better not to hurt people.”

Reimer actually laughed at that. “That’s your plan?”

“I get a 12 on Persuasion,” said Tom, giving me a worried but hopeful look.

I stared at Tom for a moment. “On his turn, Fel Seed grabs the vorpal sword from Gorn’s feeble hands, then leaps through the air, moving thirty feet in a flash, and goes for a killing blow against Featherton.” I rolled a die behind my screen and ignored the result. “The full power of the vorpal blade rips through you, and your skin slides from your muscles, your muscles slide from your bones, and perfect cuts are made at every intersection of your body. You fall to the ground as a pile of disorganized meat.”

“Oof,” said Tom. He looked down at his character sheet for a moment, then back up at me. “Not even a chance for a farewell speech?”

“No,” I said.

“Okay,” he said. He picked up his character sheet and ripped it in two. “Should I bother making a new character?”

“No,” I said. “Craig is right, we’ll be done soon.”

There was another round of combat. I was feeling shitty about a lot of things, and mad at them for seeming to take Colin’s side. No hits could possibly land against Fel Seed, not when I could set his AC arbitrarily high. He wasn’t a creature from one of the books, he was something that I made, so no one could call me out on it. I don’t know why I was even worried about that, given how far off the rails we were.

“Fel Seed flings the vorpal sword, spinning it like a scythe,” I said. I rolled more useless dice. “It hits Killiam and Rost, killing them instantly. His hand was still attached to the handle of the blade though, and it drags the sword back to him.”

“Welp,” said Craig. “Good game, if I’m being polite.”

“Wait,” replied Reimer. “Gorn is still technically alive with a single hit point. Technically he’s not dead, he just dies from a papercut. Technically that shouldn’t affect his ability to do combat.”

“Why even drag this out?” asked Craig, rolling his eyes.

“If Juniper wants to ruin a session, that’s on him,” said Reimer, nodding at me. “But I’m going to play the game how I want to play it, and that means taking every advantage I can get, not just giving up because I know that I’m going to lose. And besides, if Juniper’s going to fudge in some bullshit to make us lose, then he’s perfectly capable of fudging in some bullshit to give us a chance at winning.” He looked at me. “So, Gorn summons up what strength he has left, bellows out a defiant battle cry, then rushes at Fel Seed with his axe and aims for the vulnerable core that all supremely powerful beings have.”

“Make your roll,” I said.

Reimer rolled, out in the open. “Nat twenty,” he said, leaning back in his chair. It was the second one he’d gotten in combat.

“That’s double damage,” I said. “But the axe bounces uselessly off Fel Seed’s chest. Fel Seed reaches forward, crushes his C2 vertebrae with one hand, and tosses Gorn down to the floor so that Gorn can watch Ellnor be raped.” I pointed at Tom. “There, Tom, you can tell Colin that’s how we ended things.”

“Fucking Christ, Joon,” said Reimer, rolling his eyes. “There’s really no need to be so dramatic.”

“Well, I’m done here,” I said, getting up from the table. I hesitated. There was a ‘sorry’ on my lips. Tanking the session, and the whole campaign with it, was something that I regretted as soon as it was done. What little satisfaction I’d gotten from it had evaporated immediately.

“I have bad news,” said Tom, looking down at his phone. “It looks like Colin might not want to play with us anymore.”

Reimer and Craig laughed, and I chuckled a little. It broke the tension, and for at least a little bit, there was catharsis.

When it was all over though, I felt a knot in my stomach, and typed up apologies to various people that I never ended up sending.

“Thank you for sharing,” said Amaryllis, once I’d finished. I was sitting with her and the others in one of our larger rooms, everyone gathered together for story time, including twelve-year-old Pallida, Solace, and yes, Bethel.

“I assume there’s nothing actionable in there?” I asked.

“No, nothing,” she said. “Though given that we’ve talked about Fel Seed so much, I would be surprised if the more personal side of things had actually revealed anything.”

“So it’s bullshit, right?” I asked, looking around at the group. “I don’t actually know his weakness. He doesn’t have weaknesses, that’s the whole point. There’s nothing you can do against him.”

“We’re not trying to do anything against him,” said Grak. “We just need to go past him.”

“Easier said than done,” replied Raven. “The entrance point is below the palace, and it’s been very hard to get any information on if there’s any method of getting down there.”

“Overwhelming force might work,” said Bethel. It was the first thing she’d said. She was still presenting as meek and humbled, which I found faintly annoying.

“Let’s say that we end up having to fight Fel Seed,” said Amaryllis. “Based on what Juniper recounted, what we’ve heard from him before, and what we know from other accounts, what is the best approach?”

“Why don’t you just tell us?” asked Pallida. “It’s pretty clear you’ve got all the answers.”

“I want to hear opinions,” said Amaryllis. “Obviously I’ve already come to my own conclusions.”

“We invent a weakness,” said Grak. “Then we hope that the Dungeon Master is in a good mood.”

“I really don’t think that hitting his weak point for massive damage is going to fly,” I said.

“I can give him an argument,” said Valencia. “I’ll just argue him into not killing us. Easy, and also peasy.”

“We would be at the mercy of the Dungeon Master,” said Raven. “Given that Fel Seed has created a living hell that’s continued unimpeded for nearly five hundred years, I don’t think mercy is on the menu.”

“Just as a note, in case anyone is thinking about it,” said Amaryllis. “I’ve been searching for the vorpal blade for subjective years, and have come up with nothing, and Raven has had no luck either. I’ve put in a bounty with the goblins but gotten nothing back from them, and the last option for information is the Infinite Library, who we’re not on good terms with. That said, it’s Fel Seed’s sword to begin with, so finding it, if it exists, doesn’t seem like it would help us.”

“I have an embarrassing question,” said Grak.

“Go ahead,” I said.

“What is canonical?” he asked. “Your notes, or the world as it appeared in the games?”

“So far as we can tell, it’s a mixture,” said Amaryllis. “There exist features that were only in worlds that never had campaigns, but there are also characters and entads that were created either by or with the players.” She gestured in Raven’s direction.

“Why do we think that Fel Seed is the game version?” asked Grak. “Why would he not be as on the page?”

“Does it matter?” I asked.

“How did you plan for him to be beaten?” asked Grak.

“Oh,” I said. “I didn’t.”

“The vorpal sword was always going to fail?” asked Grak.

“It was never going to be the full answer,” I said. “Can you imagine hyping up a villain for a whole campaign only for them to die in a single hit from a magical sword? I mean … maybe it would have weakened him enough, but … I didn’t plan for that, no. I planned for him to be a terrible, unbeatable monster, the kind you only think you can beat because he’s only shown a fraction of his full power.”

“The players were always meant to die,” said Raven.

“Yeah,” I said. “Kind of.”

“So what’s the queen’s solution?” asked Pallida, looking at Amaryllis. “What does her majesty intend to do?”

“Diplomacy,” said Amaryllis. “Done at as long a range as possible, mediated by Valencia. People have tried it before, but they didn’t have Valencia’s abilities, nor were they the chosen ones of the One True God.”

“That loses us the element of surprise,” I said. “Besides, no way you could ever negotiate something with him. He would betray you.”

“Betrayal isn’t what he’s known for,” said Amaryllis. “But if you insist, then we can attempt complete radio silence.”

“No,” I said. “Go ahead. He’ll know we’re there the instant we enter into his territory, and he’s always ready to attack with fifty different kinds of insane countermeasures. That’s from reading about attempts on his zone, but it was true when I thought him up too.”

“Good,” said Amaryllis. “Conditional on that, we’re planning to go tomorrow.”

“Great!” shouted little Pallida. “I don’t know about everyone else, but I’m ready to get raped to death.”

“We’re going to need to age her up,” I said, pointing at Pallida. “Another five years or so, at a minimum.”

“Oh fuck you,” she said. “And in another five years I’ll be too much of a pussy to go with you.”

“I’m not going,” said Solace. “I would also encourage you to do whatever you can to keep the locus from going with you.”

“No one controls the locus,” I said. “Even if I pleaded, I think she would still come, if only to keep us safe. And with her domain expanding, she’s got a lot more power, which isn’t necessarily going to help us, but … if the gods consider her to be essentially a god, then that’s enough of a chance that I wouldn’t want to try very hard to dissuade her from joining us.”

“Does anyone else want to bow out?” asked Amaryllis. “There will be no judgement or argument. Whatever your utility to the party, we’ll find some way to make up for it.”

There was silence all around.

“I do wish you the best,” said Solace. “The locus should be able to return to Poran if things go poorly. I’ll be waiting and ready.”

With that the meeting broke, and it began to set in that this was really going to happen.

The Palace

Fel Seed’s palace wasn’t biological in nature, not built with bricks of bone and beams of muscle. In the session I’d run, that had been improvisation on the part of the players, a suggestion that I ran with because it was better than what I had thought up on my own. There was a red carpet laid out for us, and it very much appeared to be actual carpet rather than bits of tongue or something.

“I’m worried about how far down the FSP we are,” said Raven. “We’re into contingencies on contingencies. And we don’t actually have a good plan to beat Fel Seed, not if he’s as unbeatable as promised.”

“I can see the doorway,” said Bethel. “It’s down deep, and highly structured. Juniper, you’ll need to confirm with star magic once we’re there.”

“Is there a lock?” asked Pallida. “Because if there’s not, you can stick me in with the comatose chicks. I’m not even an actual member of this party.”

“Unclear if there’s a lock,” said Bethel. “But it does seem like what we’re here for.”

“The FSP says to go see Fel Seed,” I said, glancing at Amaryllis. “But I’m not sure that’s wise.”

“Every time we’ve tried to circumvent his will, he’s pulled out the big guns,” said Amaryllis. “There’s a good chance that if we try to go there without the final showdown, he’ll void bomb us, or something worse.”

“You’re engaging in religious thinking,” said Valencia. “I won’t say that it’s wrong, but you have this idea in your head of an all-powerful god who will do what he wants regardless of what you think, feel, or do, and that’s impacting how you think about Fel Seed.”

“Well, so long as I’m not wrong,” said Amaryllis.

We continued on. We were in Fel Seed’s domain, undoubtedly under his watchful eye, compelled to walk this path by the implication of overwhelming violence. There was a grim inevitability to it. We all knew there was a good chance we were walking to our deaths, or that someone would die. There was no grand plan for defeating Fel Seed, because the level he existed on, at least in my mind, was one where clever tricks and last minute solutions simply didn’t work. We had those tricks, we would try them, but I had no faith in them. There was nothing clearly and obviously good about anything we were walking in with.

I looked over at the locus. She barely fit within the hall. There was a faint disgust on her face, but it was hard to read her expressions in the best of circumstances. I wished that we’d gotten some armor for her or something, but I doubted that she’d have deigned to wear it. If Bethel couldn’t overpower Fel Seed, then the locus was our next best shot. Fel Seed cheated, or at least was expected to, and the locus had cheats of her own.

It took us some time to get to the throne room, in part because the palace was huge, in part because we weren’t rushing it.

When we opened the final set of doors, Fel Seed was sitting there on his enormous gilded throne, propping his head up with one hand. The other was idly pushing the pommel of a sword from side to side, with the point of it digging into the stone. The blade had a blue glow around it, and while I couldn’t quite see what was reflected in the mirror finish, I had a hunch that it wasn’t reality as I knew it. There was no one else with him, just the entity himself, waiting for us. Tall pillars, each as thick around as a car, went up to a high ceiling, but there was no place to hide tricks unless they were under the floor or inside the pillars themselves. It was a wide, open area, just the kind that you’d pick for a boss fight.

I’d never described Fel Seed, during the one session where he’d appeared. I’d been too angry, too full of emotion. The Fel Seed that sat in front of us was just as I’d imagined him though, tall and slightly red-hued, physical perfection, with all the monstrosity reserved for his creations. He had a crown of horns, and claws instead of nails, but for all that he was human enough, like a human might imagine himself. He was naked, making no effort whatsoever to cover himself.

He looked like me. I don’t know if that was quite what I had imagined, when I’d thought him up, but the resemblance was undeniable.

He got up from his throne and smiled at us, lifting his sword up and swinging it once through the air.

“Juniper, was it?” he asked.

“You don’t know me?” I asked back. We were pretty far away from each other, talking across the length of the expansive throne room, but I was certain that he could blink forward to be standing next to me in just a moment. Then we would fight, and I would lose.

“I know of you. It’s not everyday someone comes into my domain,” he replied. “I broke out the red carpet for you. I hope it was appreciated.” He had a wide grin, and his hand never left his sword, though it hadn’t gone into a position to threaten us.

“Where’d you get the sword?” I asked.

He held it up, gazing at himself in the false reflection. “You’re starting to bore me,” he said. He flipped the sword around with a practiced motion and pointed it at the locus. “You brought your own little god.”

I wanted to say something heroic, to call him on his shit or tell him that we were going to kill him, but I was afraid. All of the puns I’d prepared seemed to leave a bad taste in my mouth, not that I was supposed to start rattling off a list of puns. Maybe that was the point of the gauntlet of grotesqueries we’d gone through, to sap me of any will to make jokes.

“What will it take for us to pass through?” I asked.

“You can go,” said Fel Seed. “Leave the girls.”

“Women,” I said, gritting my teeth slightly.

“Take the deal,” said Amaryllis.

“Fuuuuuck that,” said little Pallida.

“He wouldn’t keep a deal,” I said.

“Am I not known for keeping deals?” asked Fel Seed. “Betrayal, now that’s Doris’ bag, isn’t it? I’ve heard that she’s taken a turn, thanks to you.” He clucked his tongue and looked at Amaryllis. “Word travels through the grapevine.” He looked back at me. “The second coming of Uther, they call you.”

I stayed silent. The battle was going to start, and I still didn’t know his weakness. He was talking more than I had expected, but Fel Seed was a little bit of a talker. Part of it was wanting to savor the kill, part of it was wanting to inflict pain and exercise power in a more diplomatic way.

“One of the great regrets in my life is that I just missed Uther,” said Fel Seed. He pointed the sword into the ground and rested both his hands on top of the pommel.

“You wanted to see how you stacked up next to him?” asked Amaryllis.

“Oh, no,” said Fel Seed. “He would have stood as little of a chance as you do, even with your little god.” He nodded in the direction of the locus. “I’d have loved to have killed him. There’s something about a strong man slowly dying that I love.”

Amaryllis gave me a look. “Take the deal, Juniper.”

“No,” I said. I hadn’t yet called my sword to my hand, but I could feel it itching.

“I’d listen to your wife, Juniper,” said Fel Seed. “I do honor my deals.”

“You don’t,” I said. “You trick people. You fake weakness so that they’ll attack, then turn on them.”

Fel Seed grinned at me. “You’re considering it. You’re thinking that perhaps it would be worth it. The things you say now are your way of allowing yourself to be convinced.”

“You have no incentive to offer a deal,” I said. “It’s all part of the game to you, a way to crush my spirit before you kill me. And if there is incentive, then you actually do think that I could kill you, in which case, I should try.”

“Such a low opinion of me,” said Fel Seed. “Was it seeing your wife raped that did it?”

“It wasn’t her,” I said.

“True,” he replied. “I suppose I’ll have to do it for real.”

Little Pallida stepped forward. “Are we going to kill this chucklefuck or what?”

"Take the deal,” said Amaryllis. “Go complete the mission. If it’s a question of whether you’ll sacrifice us for the greater good —”

“No,” I said. “There’s another play. I don’t think it will work, but it’s worth a try.”

“Okay,” said Amaryllis. I knew that there were plenty of grenades she was willing to jump on, and being repeatedly violated by Fel Seed, even incubating his monstrosities, was something she would do without question, if she thought that it would get us to the good ending. Of course, she was missing that any world where that happened wouldn’t be the good ending.

“There’s something you need to understand about the nature of the world,” I said. “We’re all here at the pleasure of a higher power. Here to —” I thought back on the thirty-two miles of gore we’d walked through. “Here to live, to have fun, to be entertainment of some kind. It’s all got to come to an end though. All that time that Uther has been alive, and the few months that I’ve been here, all of that is the point of this world. The deal is this: if you let us through, then I’ll make sure you have a life in the remade world.”

He stared at me for a moment.

The attack came at the speed of light. The only way I would have been able to block or dodge was if I had some kind of precognitive ability. Instead, the sword bounced off Grak’s ward, and Fel Seed flashed back to where he was.

“Just testing,” he said, smiling. “Fancy warding.”

I was confident that he could get through. Maybe he could change the entad signature of the vorpal blade, or maybe he could make something wardproof, or maybe he’d just use something that Grak couldn’t ward against. He had void weapons, lots of them, and my guess was that he had a gun or bomb hidden somewhere, just in case he needed it. If he could move with that speed, it almost didn’t matter.

“It looks like we’re going to have to fight,” said Amaryllis.

“Oh, it won’t be much of a fight,” replied Fel Seed.

He attacked again, slow and languid by the standards of the speed he’d used earlier, and I had just enough time to pull out a unicorn bone and start burning it.

I could feel the weight of the vorpal blade as it struck Grak’s ward, the sheer energy of it, and the ward fell to pieces, broken apart at its natural joints. The second attack followed the first, not from the sword, but from Fel Seed himself, firing off pieces of himself at us, wriggling bits of finger and flapping pieces of flesh. I sent out a sterilizing blast of fire, a combination of fire magic to kickstart oxidation and rune magic to raise the temperature, but while it killed the projectiles, it was fruitless. The air was undoubtedly full of spores, and we were all sealed as much as we possibly could be.

Raven opened up a specially prepared book, blasting him with every high-powered meme we had, and he didn’t so much as blink.

I attacked back, my sword in my hand with a thought. I had swapped the reflection sword for something with a bit more brute strength, one that was magically sharpened, capable of passing straight through almost any armor. It didn’t seem to work on Fel Seed though, as his biology was strange enough that whatever heuristics the sword was using didn’t count as armor. Instead, it just took a chip from the skin over his hardened muscles which regrew in an instant.

He killed Raven, gripping her force field helm and twisting it all the way around, not seeming to feel any resistance. Pallida was next, her wards shattered by the vorpal blade. She was grabbed around the torso by a long tentacle and dashed against one of the pillars, sheared in half by the force. In my mind’s eye I recalled seeing the same thing on my first day in Aerb, a girl hitting the side of a dumpster.

Bethel sprang forward, out of Valencia’s grip, turned to cloth, and wrapped herself around the vorpal blade. It took a moment to realize that I knew that entad, though I’d never seen it used before; it was the dress that Zinnia had used to wrap up Raven so they could make their escape. Wrapping completely around the sword would have allowed Bethel to use the power, but she went a step further, eating it entirely, then zipping away, having deprived Fel Seed of his weapon.

I wasn’t able to process it all in the moment. Everything was happening in fractions of seconds, Grak doing something with his wards, probably an annihilation attack, Valencia bounding away to a safe distance, Amaryllis moving to flank — we’d trained and practiced together, but there was no real way to prepare for Fel Seed, not even if we’d assumed he was limited in his abilities.

I dropped my own sword and Bethel zipped to my hand in the form of a sword, a moment of uncomfortability at holding her quickly washed away. Short of a nuclear weapon or antimatter runebomb, I was fairly sure that Bethel was the most powerful weapon of destruction on Aerb, and unlike Onion’s stupidly powerful sword, she wasn’t limited to one effect at a time.

When I sliced Bethel through the air, there was a crackle of ripped molecules and a gout of plasma, the combined effects of who-knew-what powers ripping the very air apart. I was faster, holding Bethel, stronger and more sure of myself, with what felt like a minor ability to see things before they happened. Time was slowed to a tenth its usual speed, and when the blade made contact, time seemed to stop. I gave over a part of myself, only a sliver.

Critical hit!

When I struck Fel Seed, he exploded outward, torn apart at the seams, pieces of limbs and fingers flying backward and clattering against the walls, bones slipping free of their surrounding muscles, all of his pieces wetly slapping around.

For a moment, just a moment, I thought maybe that had actually worked.

There was no message of defeat.

The doors behind us were slammed open, and Fel Seed was standing there, as though he hadn’t just been killed.

“Let’s try that again, shall we?” he grinned.

I let go of the timeline and looped backward just as he was ripping through Amaryllis.

I felt fatigued even with the timeline restarted, reduced by what the vorpal sword had taken from me. Of course blasting him apart hadn’t actually killed him, the being we’d seen was just an avatar. But if that hadn’t worked, hadn’t even bought us a reprieve, I had no idea what would.

The second attempt went like the first, with no sign that Fel Seed was doing anything differently, no awareness that time was looping. The vorpal blade struck against Grak’s ward, breaking it, and I didn’t bother trying to counter his biological attack when he made it. Instead I called to Bethel, shouting for her to avoid the sword, to pick us up instead. She did as she was instructed, zipping around the room, with Valencia gone in an instant, then Raven, who just avoided having her head twisted off, Amaryllis, Pallida, Grak, and finally, myself. The last thing I saw was the locus, which was just standing there, watching, as she had been the entire time, not lifting a finger to help us, but also not the focus of Fel Seed’s attention.

In an instant I was elsewhere, facing an enormous door, with the others around me. The order of pickup and dropoff had been ordained by the FSP, and Pallida was first out, looking at the door that blocked our path. It was large and ornate, the focal point of the room, with a bas relief on the side of it, too intricate and detailed for me to take it in, not when Fel Seed was surely coming for us, if he wasn’t already —

And then there he was, coming through a side door, and that was surely an affectation too, something he did because he felt like it, or because it helped to maintain some plausible deniability about the scope of his powers.

I popped a metal squirt gun out from my personal extra dimensional storage and sprayed him with fluoroantimonic acid. It was the deadliest acid I knew of, and it melted away at him almost at once, helped along by a liberal application of fire magic to speed up the reactions. It actually worked, to the extent that it killed that particular body, but another came through the door right afterward and picked up the vorpal blade, which was completely unharmed, from the floor.

“Bethel, grab the vorpal blade,” I shouted as I switched to a different squirt gun, this one with the chlorine trifluoride, the same chemical I’d used in the fight against Onion.

She went forward, grabbing it from him again, eating it again, both of them unaware that we’d done this before. This time though, Fel Seed held out a hand, and Bethel came to him, zipping to his hand and forming a blade there, the same one I’d used against him. The vorpal blade was his, tied to him more tightly than entad connections usually were. I made a mental note not to have her do that again.

“Pallida!” I screamed.

“High magic!” she screamed back. “It’s fucked!”

I glanced over and saw Grak there, trying to work his own magic to get us through the door, but I had no way to gauge whether or not he was anywhere close. If it needed star magic, then I was going to have to be the one to do it, and it might take hours, because star magic was glacially slow. Dilation would help, but —

My ability to hold the timeline was waning, and I made a judgment call, letting it loop back again.

Even if we got through the door, what good was that going to do us? Fel Seed could simply follow, unless he was prohibited by whatever force of the universe was responsible for exclusion zones (the Warden, presumably, if there really was a pantheon). It was our only hope though.

“Doorbreak,” I called out. “Back in a round.”

Bethel grabbed Grak and Pallida, scooping them up as Grak’s primary ward fell apart, then disappearing in a brief flash of light as she used one of her short-range movement options. Ten seconds wasn’t enough, but that was as far as I could stretch the time loop and still have time for a sentence of infodump, and even then, I wasn’t entirely sure that I could survive ten seconds toe-to-toe with Fel Seed.

I blasted him with vibration magic, a single pulse that used up almost all my breath, but it wasn’t strong enough to do anything but push him back and blast off most of his skin. I aimed a volley of gem magic at him, and it struck him squarely in the head, but I didn’t even know if that was where his brain was, if he had a brain. I had so much magic, but so little of it was at the power level I wanted it to be.

Raven stepped in to follow up on one of my attacks, slicing with her blade of stopped time, and to my surprise, she cleaved right through him, cutting him from his collar bone right down to his hip. Her seafoam green orbs sprang to life around her head, and as his body fell, she was already turning to the door, launching one of them squarely at him. He made no attempt at dodging, and when the orb burned a hole straight through the center of his chest, he collapsed to the floor, only for another of him to step into the room right afterward. He was smiling at us, not seeming to mind the ‘deaths’. He was playing with us, but that was fine, because it was buying us time for the doorbreak team to figure something out. The seconds seemed to be going by like minutes.

Raven’s second orb burned straight through another of his bodies, which again collapsed to the floor. When yet another body stepped through the door, she fired off the third and final orb, but this time he held up his hand, and though it shouldn’t have been remotely possible, he caught it. He smiled at us for a second, enjoying it, and then flicked it back at Raven. It traveled at triple the speed it had gone at him with, straight through Raven’s head, leaving a gaping hole where the center of her face had been.

It was down to me, Valencia, and Amaryllis. I didn’t know how many seconds we had left before the doorbreak team would be back, but I was already feeling the strain on the loop, and the bone didn’t have much power left in it. We had more of them, but we were making no progress, finding no weaknesses. All that was happening was that I was getting an ever-lengthening list of things that didn’t work and different ways he could and would blatantly cheat.

The locus still hadn’t done anything.

Amaryllis had heard my instruction to the doorbreak team, and she moved in Fel Seed’s way as soon as Raven dropped. She was sacrificing herself, at least in this one instance, so that I might be able to hear the answer. She was decked out in entads, and when Fel Seed attacked, she exploded into a cloud of flower petals, forming back up into herself behind him, then attacking with a sword that flashed with lightning when it struck him. Black smoke rose from his body, but it didn’t kill him, and he whipped around to face her, catching her in the head with a furious right hook that smashed against her personal ward and knocked her off-balance, even with her stilling it. His second attack followed right after, and this time the wards didn’t seem to matter to him, because he wrapped a thick flap of flesh around her midsection and started to squeeze. She should have been able to stop it, or just ignore it, she had all kinds of defenses, and no way did I accept that mere flesh was strong enough to defeat her, but Fel Seed didn’t play by the rules. He squeezed tight and her midsection gave way, causing her top half to topple down to the ground with a splatter of viscera.

Bethel returned to us, crashing up through the floor, and spat out a sentence so fast that I almost had trouble following. “Door locked, triple protection, high magic, password or key.”

I reset the loop for a final time, dropping the bone as soon as I did, then pulling another one from the same extradimensional space. This loop was later, after the vorpal sword had broken Grak’s major wards, but I was hoping that we weren’t past the point of no return. There were limits to how much the micro time loops actually helped us, and there was a cost, beyond just the bones, because I needed to spend a thread on it and hold onto the bone.

“Door, now,” I called to Bethel, and she took me, leaving the others behind.

A moment later I was standing in front of the door, looking at the relief on it. I spent a few precious seconds staring at it, trying to quickly make sense of the work of art, hoping it was a clue. It reminded me of the one we’d seen on the front of Kuum Doona, the representation of Uther’s life, but while the art style might have been similar, the subject matter was quite different. It showed stairs, a set of them leading upward, growing smaller as they did, with all manner of beasts at the bottom, and landings along the way. I recognized most of it, because I had spent a few weeks designing it all.

There shouldn’t have been a password, nor a key, none of that was part of my design. Really, it shouldn’t have connected to Aerb at all.

“Password,” I called out. “Open sesame.” I would have been upset if that had worked. “6aUaQ1gF,” I said. It would have been fucking stupid if my default password had worked, but seemed like something the Dungeon Master might have done. “Bethel, be a key.”

There was a moment of hesitation, but she zipped forward all the same, attacking the door, trying to find some hidden crevice she could wedge herself into. The Anyblade could be used as a key, and Bethel had both that ability and others, but there was no obvious keyhole, no place you could even put a key. It was likely that she’d done this in the other timeline, and given that the old loop had ended, she should have the memories, but as I watched her probe, it was clear she had no better idea what she was supposed to be doing than I did. They would have already tried void weapons to break through, and if they weren’t mentioning them, then they’d been found wanting.

I wracked my brain trying to think about what the key would be, what keys I had heard of, what passwords I had heard, things from earlier that there could be a callback to, some clever or extremely unclever way of solving the riddle. I thought about the teleportation key, which Amaryllis had, and resolved to get that in the next go around. I called out a few variations on the keyring that we’d used before. I thought briefly about the achievement, ‘A Key For Seven Locks’, but the phrase seemed meaningless in this context. Had this door been here in Uther’s time? How had he managed to open it? It felt like there was something I was missing, some hint or clue. Or maybe it was a joke, or a pun, or a fucking anagram, and I just wasn’t in the right mindset to latch onto it.

Fel Seed appeared at the doorway, holding the heads of my companions by their hair, their bodies missing. He himself was drenched in blood and smiling.

I ended the loop and returned to the moment of the ward being cut by the vorpal blade. I needed more time, more firepower, more than just seconds of frantically trying to figure something out.

“Bethel, dilation one,” I called. Time, at least, I could handle.

She zipped around, picking up everyone but me and the locus.

The time dilation effect inside Bethel wouldn’t work on me, not with the unicorn bone: I would be limited to the same subjective loop duration. For everyone else though, dilation would work, and they had memories of the first set of loops. For every second that I held out, I was giving them something like an hour of time to think things through, to go over their memories of the door, something that would help us. I had faith in them. I could go in too, outside the loop, and hope that I could think of something, especially something specific to me, but that was more costly. I needed to give them a chance. All I had to do was hold against Fel Seed.

“You’re doing something with time,” he said, swinging his sword up and resting it against his shoulder. It should have been cutting into him, but he showed no reaction.

“You’re not going to fight me?” I asked, holding my sword ready in front of me.

“I’ll fight you when it matters,” he replied. “Take all the time you need.”

No one had come out of Bethel, who was hovering nearby, the size of a pin. I held on as long as I could, but they didn’t come out, which had to have meant that they hadn’t found an answer, or even anything they thought had a shot of working. I’d get the answers when the loop set was finally finished and all those memories came crashing back together.

“Bethel, dilation two,” I called as the loop restarted.

“You’re doing something with time,” said Fel Seed once everyone was collected.

“What’s behind the door downstairs?” I asked. If he didn’t know we were trying to go there from the previous loop set, he would know from this one.

“If only I knew,” he sighed. He was speaking in a languid way, as though we weren’t constrained by the urgent passing of seconds.

“We need —” I began, but I could feel the tug of the loop, and let it end.

“Bethel, dilation three,” I shouted as the vorpal sword went through Grak’s ward.

“You’re doing something with time,” said Fel Seed, resting the vorpal sword against his shoulder once more.

“We don’t want to fight you,” I said. “We just want to get through the door.”

“It’s impossible,” he said. “I’ve tried.” He pointed his sword at my hand, which was holding the unicorn bone. “As soon as you’re done with that, I’m chopping your arm off.”

I didn’t acknowledge him. There wasn’t any point. I was hoping that the repeated loops were actually helping things, that some progress was being made, but as the seconds burned away, I was losing hope. If they had something, they would be trying it. Grak had gotten a good look at the door in the previous loop set, Pallida had touched it, there had to be something, but we were here, stalled out, and Fel Seed was going to kill us.

The loop reset, and I ended it again, as soon as I could, right as the vorpal blade was going through Grak’s ward. I was already pulling a third unicorn bone from extradimensional space when Fel Seed’s sword flicked forward, thrown, and sliced off my arm at the shoulder. I’d tried to still the attack, but that had done nothing, either because of the blade, or something Fel Seed had done, or just because it was a cheat.

“Amaryllis, sitrep!” I called.

“Doorbreak!” she called out to the team, and Bethel began the same series of pickups and dropoffs that she’d done before. I was thankful for the FSP, which we were far down, because at least some of this had been mapped out ahead of time.

Every fucking loop we’d had someone die, and my arm had been chopped off, along with my access to the relevant extradimensional space. If there was a plan, I didn’t know it.

The loops were safe, and we were now well outside of them.

Fel Seed reached out for Raven, likely hoping to twist her head off again. I moved in, using blood magic to stop the flow of blood from my left arm, and moved to hack at the muscular appendage he was reaching for her with, but I was too late.

That was when the locus, finally, stepped in.

I’d never thought of deer as being biting animals, but the locus brought her mouth down on Fel Seed’s appendage, then pulled with a power that I hadn’t thought she had. The appendage ripped apart, crumpling, and Raven cut away what remained on her.

The locus faced down Fel Seed for a moment, who was rapidly regrowing what he’d lost. He was sans sword, which he’d thrown to take my arm off, but I didn’t think that made him substantially less dangerous. The locus just didn’t look particularly threatening, even with her large size.

Her fur momentarily glowed, and then she opened her mouth to let out a gout of lightning as thick as my arm. When it hit Fel Seed, he instantly vaporized, in a way that I was pretty sure wouldn’t have happened with real lightning, but I wasn’t about to complain.

“Sitrep,” I said to Amaryllis as we all turned to face the door.

“There are things to try,” said Amaryllis. “Retreat is one of them.”

“Retreat?” I asked.

The locus stepped forward to meet Fel Seed, and they wrestled together for a moment, with him trying to grapple her. He managed to get on her back, away from her head, and her fur stood up on end. I was worried for her, but the fur shot out like long spikes, lancing straight through him in hundreds of places, and he fell to the ground as another body came in through the door. The locus had a long scratch on her flank, and as good as she’d done, I was sure she was going to be worn down over time.

“The door needs parts,” said Amaryllis, yelling over the sound of the fight. Raven had moved to join, fearless despite how many deaths she’d experienced. “It needs Pallida, Grak, star magic, but something else as well, a key we don’t have, a password we don’t know. I prepared a dictionary attack, but —”

Fel Seed had gotten tossed off the locus and towards us, and I ducked beneath him as he twisted around in the air with inhuman grace. I blasted him with vibration magic to get him away, then followed it up by bringing out some of the acid again, which had worked well enough the first time. From the sounds behind me though, he’d elected to stop playing around, and was no longer pretending that he was limited to one avatar at a time. They were streaming into the room, dogpiling the locus, and Raven was in among them, hacking away at them, but it was only a matter of time before she got killed again, this time for good.

Bethel returned to us and unceremoniously dumped out Grak and Pallida, both of whom were heavily bleeding. Something had happened to Pallida’s eye, and Grak wasn’t moving.

“Sitrep!” I called.

“Nothing!” Pallida screamed. “No fucking time!”

Bethel had joined the fight and was letting loose. Wherever she passed, Fel Seed’s bodies died, sliced apart with precision cuts, burnt out by lasers, electrocuted, or simply blasted. She moved over to the locus, freeing it, and saved Raven’s life.

I looked to Amaryllis, and saw her giving me a tense stare. Retreat was on her mind, but I didn’t know what that would accomplish. Even if we were allowed to leave, the door would still be there, and if it needed all of us and something else, if it needed time, then we just weren’t going to be able to do it. We had to kill Fel Seed, and we had no way of doing that. He had no weaknesses, he just hadn’t been built with them.

“Full retreat!” I yelled, feeling in the pit of my stomach the weight of those words. All this for nothing, nothing gained, barely anything learned.

Bethel zipped through, grabbing Valencia, Amaryllis, and Grak, storing them away, but as she moved to Raven, Fel Seed reached out and grabbed her out of the air, nevermind that she should have been too fast for him.

She struggled against him, deploying all the tools at her disposal, but he was finally showing how much of his weakness was a lie. The cuts barely penetrated his skin, which healed instantly anyhow. The burns she inflicted were gone in a moment, leaving nothing but smoke in the air. She tried to grow, and he squeezed tight around her, tight enough that I started to hear things break or pop, which should have been impossible, except that he was cheating, making his flesh stronger than inviolability.

Left with no other options, she disappeared entirely.

Fel Seed went after me, moving faster than before, no longer holding back enough that I stood any chance. I unleashed what I had, tried to shoot him with the acid, but he regenerated through it, as I’d always known he could.

From the corner of my eye I saw the locus disappear and then reappear, teleporting over to first Pallida, then Raven, blinking in and out of existence, taking them with her. Had the locus understood the call to retreat? I hoped so, because she was my only way out unless Bethel came back.

The locus appeared in front of me, and I reached out with my one remaining hand. She was battered and beaten, bleeding from all kinds of wounds, and two of her six eyes were a bloody mess.

Fel Seed grabbed my wrist and yanked me to the side, away from the locus. There were maybe a dozen of him running around, and lots more corpses lying on the ground. The locus suffered another attack, then disappeared, blinking back into existence next to me. I was being held by Fel Seed though, and he pulled me away, breaking my remaining arm in the process as he twisted me.

A second time the locus took a hit and moved to some dimensional elsewhere, then appeared next to me. I lunged forward as best I could, and we made contact — but nothing happened. I looked to the side, and saw that Fel Seed hadn’t just grabbed me, he had run some kind of biological wire into me at the point where he’d cut off my arm.

I screamed and flared up blood magic, driving up the heat and trying to burn him out, but that was a fool’s errand. The locus was trying to help, but taking more attacks.

“Go!” I shouted at her, barely able to get the word out. Bad enough that I was going to die, but I didn’t want her to die too.

The locus stared at me for one long, forlorn second, then disappeared.

I was all alone with Fel Seed. He had me held in place.

If there was some sort of miracle from on high, now seemed like the time.

Instead, one of his bodies picked up the vorpal blade, which had been lying on the floor, and casually walked over to me. I tried to say something, but that only got me some fingers in my mouth, and when I tried to bite down on them, I chipped a tooth.

Calmly and casually, Fel Seed drew back with the vorpal blade and cut my head clean off.

GAME OVER

Post Game Statistics

Playtime (objective): 172 days, 13 hours, 22 seconds
Playtime (subjective): 262 days, 0 hours, 11 seconds
Highest Level Earned: 19
Quests Completed: 29
Companion Quests Completed: 4
Enemies Killed: 421
Companions Acquired: 7
Exclusions Created: 2
Forge Frenzies: 0
Planes Visited: 3
World Explored: 0.0007%
Distance traveled: 497,931 miles
Steps taken: 1,032,071
Trains Taken: 1
Calories Consumed: 602,600
Fast Travel Used: 0
Save Games Loaded: 0

Achievement Unlocked: Game Over Man, Game Over

Achievement Unlocked: Helldiver

Hellfall

I was naked and falling, the cold air stinging my skin. By reflex, I tried to use still magic, but nothing happened, and with a terrible awareness, I realized that I didn’t have any of my extra senses either, no sense of water, no ability to feel the vibrations around me, nothing. There was no familiar HUD keeping track of my vital statistics. My body, at least, was intact, my arm back in place, but I had little else.

I slammed into the ground after not too long, and immediately felt a sensation across my skin like sunburn. I’d landed in something like snow, except it was slightly yellow, clumped up without being wet, and wasn’t nearly as cold. I slowly got to my feet, groaning, knowing that I would be bruised and scraped up the next day, if there was a next day.

“Good thing you picked Helldiver,” said a voice. “Otherwise we wouldn’t have gotten a chance to have this talk.”

I looked up and saw a familiar face. It was the Dungeon Master, standing in the midst of what I decided would be called yellow-fall. More of the strange substance was drifting to the ground all around us, obscuring my view of what was ahead, leaving him as the only thing to look at. The yellow-fall stung, like there was some salt or acid in it, and it clung to my body in every place that I touched it. It was cold, but not as cold as snow.

“You’ve changed,” I said. His beard was thicker and longer, and his hair was shaggy, unkempt. He still had on one of his idiotic hooded sweatshirts though. This one said ‘Tortured for Eternity in Heck’, which I suppose he must have found funny. Some of the yellow-fall was getting on my face, making it hard to see, and on my mouth, where it tasted of ammonia. I used my hand to wipe some away, which was only partially successful, and seemed to make the stinging worse.

“We had a good run, you and I,” said the Dungeon Master. “I guess we’re done then?”

“Guess so,” I replied.

“Come on,” he said. “I know you want to make some snarky comment. You want to compare yourself to Jesus and say you’ll be back after three days. You want to defiantly tell me that Mary is going to rescue you. Go ahead, you can say it, I have some time set aside for this conversation.”

“Why?” I asked.

“I guess it would be to highlight your megalomania,” said the Dungeon Master, which hadn’t been what I’d meant at all. I’d wanted to know why we were having the conversation. “One of the problems with making someone the center of a whole world is that they start to think like it. I suppose I can’t fault you for it too much. But you failed, and so we’re here.”

“I failed because you wanted me to,” I said. “It was never not going to be like this. You want me to grovel? I’ll grovel. I’ll beg.” I stopped myself, because I could feel a well of anger inside me. “Please. Please! I don’t want to be here, I want to keep playing your game,” it wasn’t coming out right though, there wasn’t enough honest emotion behind what I was saying. I wasn’t a good liar. It wasn’t convincing. I felt too much anger toward him. On the object level, I wanted to give him whatever I needed to in order to get out of the hells. On an emotional level, I wanted him to fuck off and die.

“I never wanted you to beg,” said the Dungeon Master. He waved a hand and a metal folding chair appeared behind him. He sat down on it and crossed his legs. “Though I did want you to suffer, at least a little bit.”

“A little bit?” I asked, feeling a rising indignation. “I was tortured, in so many fucking ways.”

“Not really a conversation that I’m here to have,” replied the Dungeon Master.

“So why are you here?” I asked. “To reveal your grand design?”

“Nah,” he replied, looking off to the side. “It just seemed appropriate to see you one last time. I told you there’d be a third meeting, didn’t I? Rule of three and all that.”

“What was Fel Seed’s weakness?” I asked.

“There’s an entity that exists above him,” replied the Dungeon Master. He pointed to himself. “But you already knew that.” He had already heard my prayers on the matter.

“So all I had to do was convince you to let us through?” I asked. “Convince you that he shouldn’t have killed us? That it wasn’t fun or entertaining?”

“Maybe,” he shrugged. “What would have convinced you, when you were the DM?”

“At the time, nothing,” I replied. “Except maybe if the characters had been thinking, feeling creatures, not just avatars.”

“That didn’t stop you from doing your best to inflict harm on the players,” said the Dungeon Master. “Anyway, it’s all academic, because you’re dead now, and there’s no escape from the hells.”

“Yeah,” I said. I tried to wipe more of the yellow stuff from my face, to keep my eyes and mouth clear. “What the fuck is this stuff?”

“Oh, I have no idea,” he replied. “I only spent any time on two of the hells, Alpha and Omega,  and had the Architect handle the rest.” He looked around. “Seems like some kind of worse version of snow. It’ll stop in a bit. And I’m sure there are some plants and animals somewhere, and some infernals, since there usually are. That’ll be fun for you, huh?”

“You’re an asshole,” I said. I looked around at the yellow-fall, wondering how deep it would end up getting.

He looked me over. “Are you just going to keep standing there, or are you going to get moving?”

“You said we were kindred spirits,” I said. “I’ve got no idea what I did to make you do all this horrible stuff to me.”

“There are plenty of reasons to hate you, Juniper,” the Dungeon Master replied. “And I do hate you, maybe even more than I care about you. There’s something so contemptible about you, so weaselly. It makes a person want to grab you by the back of your head and bash your face into the pavement.”

“And here I thought I’d been doing better,” I said.

“A bit,” he nodded. “I’ll give you that.”

He showed no sign of moving. I was surprised. It felt like he would show up, mock me for a bit, drop some knowledge, then leave. It was what I expected of him. That this was apparently a long sit-down chat made me think that maybe he was serious about this being the end.

“I have questions,” I said.

“Go on,” he replied, nodding.

“Was there a DMPC?” I asked. “And who was it?”

He laughed. “Arthur put that idea into your head,” he said.

“You’re not denying it,” I replied.

“Did I sometimes take control of people, or put on an infallible disguise?” he asked. “Oh, certainly. I was never anyone close to you though. There was no need. You know the rules, and so do I. A DMPC is there to fill a role in the party that they were lacking, but they’re also meant to coast along, to not interfere, to have no grand moments of their own. There was never a need for that, with you.”

“And with Uther?” I asked.

“Arthur,” the Dungeon Master replied, regarding me with cold eyes. “I’ll admit to making some mistakes with Arthur. I wasn’t thinking clearly.”

“Vervain,” I said. “He was a DMPC.”

“Arthur wasn’t like you,” replied the Dungeon Master. “He didn’t want to go on an adventure. He didn’t want to fight. On Earth, he would have lived a relatively simple life, would probably have gone to law school and worked in some boring part of the legal sector, might have found a wife and had some children, watched the usual movies and television, gone on a few vacations … he was a thinker, in some respects, like you, but he wasn’t much of a dreamer. It made coming to Aerb difficult for him. Of course, some of the mistake was in not pushing him right away, but he would have collapsed, I could see that. Early on, I gave him so many opportunities, so many chances for adventure, so many clarion calls to do something about the Dark King and his armies. What he latched onto instead was a theater troupe.” He frowned. “He noticed that he was special. He noticed that he was getting in shape faster than he should have, that he could handle a sword with ease, or bounce back from injuries, but he didn’t do anything with it. In his mind, he thought that the Dark King’s reign would end on its own, and he could be with the sprightly girl he’d met in the troupe. There was a bit of a love triangle, not my original intention, but there because he refused to make a move.”

“I hated it,” the Dungeon Master continued. “He had seemed destined for greatness. I mean, he was, I had made that destiny for him, all kinds of powers ready to be awakened, all kinds of opportunities, and my will on his side. Instead, when I put him on Aerb, he was just … a person. A flawed person more concerned with the petty than the grand. I’d thought — well, I’d thought that he would like the adventures. I’d thought that it would be like playing out the campaigns. Instead, he seemed to just want to pine after some girl. The girl wasn’t even all that special, she just showed him attention and — do you understand how frustrating that was? It wasn’t why I’d made Aerb for him.”

I filed that bit of information away for later. “And thus, Vervain,” I said.

“Oh, no,” replied the Dungeon Master, looking at me in faint surprise. “I tried to kickstart things. The Dark King got wind of their subversive plays, something that Arthur had written to impress the girl, and sent a small attack force to put it down. A pitifully small attack force, truth be told, there more for intimidation than conflict. Arthur could have stopped it. He knew his own impressive skill with a sword, knew the athleticism he had. The moment was there for him to rise to, there was healing on hand, everyone could have made it out alive, with the orcs and dwarves the Dark King sent slaughtered, or at least driven off. Instead, he hid, then ran away. It made sense, I suppose, but it was so,” he clenched his fist. “I was offering him the part of the hero, the part he’d always loved to play. But to take it, to actually be that person, wasn’t, at the time, him.”

“You were running a sandbox,” I said. “But you weren’t listening to what he actually wanted.” I had to wipe the yellow-fall away from my eyes and mouth again. It was stinging all over, and I was worried I was going to suffer some kind of damage because of it, but I wanted the Dungeon Master talking for as long as possible. The more he talked, the more worried I got that he was going to leave me stranded there, that it would really be over.

“It’s true,” sighed the Dungeon Master. “A classic mistake, really. Amateurish. But Vervain was created out of a need to get Arthur back on track. He was a mysterious old wizard who was supposed to die early on, to explain the facts of the world that Arthur could have found out himself if he hadn’t spent three years hiding himself away and hoping that the problem of the Dark King would just solve itself. I didn’t want to give up Vervain though, and as a mysterious old wizard it was possible to step away on unspecified business at a moment’s notice. Vervain was real enough that I didn’t need to be there all the time. Through Vervain, Arthur learned that he was the true heir to the throne of Anglecynn. He gathered allies and fought against the Dark King, loved and lost, wept and raged, and — it was everything I had hoped for, really. You should have seen it when Arthur took the Dark King down. It was a thing of beauty.”

I stared at the Dungeon Master. I didn’t know why he was telling me all this, except maybe that he’d been wanting to share it with someone. Maybe he’d thought I would understand, because we were, after all, kindred spirits. I did understand.

“Then you kept going,” I prompted.

“I wasn’t satisfied,” said the Dungeon Master. “The Dark King was defeated, and … for a bit, that was enough, and then, it wasn’t. I wanted more. More of Arthur, more adventures, more companions, more stories.”

“Degenerate cycles,” I said.

“Yes,” the Dungeon Master replied. “I was still enjoying myself though, and Arthur was growing into the role. I could see into his thoughts, naturally, so there was nothing he could hide from me, and I would peek at the future from time to time, making course corrections.”

“But then what happened?” I asked. “He killed Vervain, he went insane, he’s been lost down the Long Stairs, he wanted to go home —”

“You didn’t get to that part,” said the Dungeon Master. “It seems unfair to tell you.”

“Then back up,” I said. “Zona.”

“Oh, I’m not going to lay out every twist and turn of his life story, and the part I played in telling it,” said the Dungeon Master. “You think of it as torture, but he was happy, for the most part, truly and genuinely happy. He didn’t have an itch for adventure, necessarily, but through it all, he took joy in it, barring a few bumps in the road. You understand he wasn’t insane, don’t you? There really was an entity above everything, pulling the strings, forcing his life into these narrative arrangements. I’m admitting to that. Though I did step away from the wheel a few times, especially in the later decades, letting the adventures happen without me. And as for everything else, I suppose it will have to remain a mystery, because you didn’t get there on your own.”

“I fucking tried,” I said. “We fought like hell against Fel Seed, we tried to get past your door, down the Long Stairs ourselves, you can’t say that was my fault. Fel Seed fucking cheated. I mean, I figured he would, but he did cheat. Look, if Arthur was something to you, I can understand making a world for him, setting him up on adventures, acting out fantasies, but why me? You don’t even like me.”

“Meh,” he said, turning away. “Does it matter?”

“Feels like it does,” I said. “Or am I going to get tortured in heck for an eternity without even knowing why?”

“That’s what everyone else gets,” he replied. He stood up, and his metal folding chair vanished. “I have regrets about how things have gone with you, too,” he said. “But I guess it’s all over. Ta ta.”

“Wait!” I shouted, and to my faint surprise, he stopped and looked at me, arching an eyebrow. “Second round against Fel Seed, if I get there. You’ll make it a fair fight?”

He regarded me for a moment, then tilted his head slightly and vanished.

I stopped for a moment, staring at where he had been. He hadn’t even left any footprints.

“Say sike right now,” I said. The joke felt weak coming from my lips, and it didn’t make me feel better.  “Come on, this can’t be it.”

There was just the sound of my own heavy breathing and the sting of the yellow-fall.

I had always thought there was a decent chance I would end up in the hells. I had ticked the Helldiver option, after all. Even beyond that, the katabasis was a central part of the Hero’s Journey. It was one of the most clearly identified parts in Hero With A Thousand Faces, and you could find examples in Sumerian, Greek, Egyptian, Roman, Norse, Buhddist, Christian — it was probably easier to list mythologies that didn’t feature a hero having a trip to the underworld at some point or another.

We had, of course, talked about it. It hadn’t been a part of the FSP, but we’d had conversations earlier, making at least the skeleton of a plan.

“In theory,” said Amaryllis. “If one of us dies and Val is still alive, she might be able to find us. She doesn’t have proper eyes into the hells, but she could kill her way around and hope to kill someone who had seen you. If you’re high enough, we could use infernoscopes, and we might have a chance of finding you if we knew where you died. I also think the infernoscope restriction can probably be overcome, given how simple of a device the infernoscope is, but that would take time and some engineering challenges. Which hell you enter is semi-random, distributed on a bell curve that’s centered on the upper end, but the actual location has a fairly tight, if complicated, correspondence. So, Val would know where to start looking. It would be a massive security risk, but not as massive as one of us getting caught and tortured for information.”

“And from there?” I asked. “We have no way to pull someone from the hells. We have no way to leave the hells if we find ourselves there. If we had either of those things, I’d have already used them to bring Fenn back to life.” It had been an obsession of mine for quite a while, but had never gone anywhere. There were stories, but none of them panned out.

“It’s impossible,” said Raven. “Flatly impossible.”

I nodded. “I know,” I said. “Death is permanent. The hells are permanent. Everyone says.” I couldn’t help but let a touch of sarcasm creep into my voice. Everyone had said that going to Earth was impossible too.

“What about the locus?” asked Grak.

“Even if she had more power,” I said. (This was before the expansion of her domain.) “It’s not something that a locus is ever on record as having done. That doesn’t necessarily mean a whole lot, but it’s hard to imagine that we would be able to coerce or convince her, or just have the locus do it on her own. I mean, right?”

“Infernals can travel to Aerb,” said Raven. “Part of our work at the Library was stopping them. Imps and lesser infernals can even do it without terribly much effort, but they’re poorly adapted and can wind up worse off than if they’d stayed in their mild hell.” The Apocalypse Demon was one notable example.

“So what stops the same thing from working on a person?” I asked.

“Power and risk,” said Amaryllis. “Risk, because to open up a portal for people would mean also opening up one for infernals. Power, because the reason infernals don’t do it all the time is that it’s incredibly fucking difficult, even if you have a society of billions devoting whatever resources they have to the problem.”

“Even then, it might not work,” said Raven. “There’s some indication that people can’t pass back into the real world at all. There’s something having to do with changes in the soul. Souls don’t decay or degrade in the hells, people regenerate beyond what’s possible on Aerb, and there’s the principle of planar disjunction.”

The phrase rang a bell. “Fallatehr mentioned it,” I said. “Only in passing though. He said … that the soul was incapable of crossing the planar boundary. I never really understood the implication of that, and at the time, we had more pressing issues.”

“The theories were never fully baked,” said Raven. “And the scholars were wiped out, along with a lot of the research. The basics I understood, at least. Entads and certain magics could access ‘the soul’, but that didn’t match what could be observed in the hells of the same test subject. There was an entad that could access a specific slice of a person’s memories, but it wouldn’t grab their memories that should have been generated in the hells. There were some other experiments that showed the same. It’s possible that the soul that exists in the hells isn’t like the souls that exist on Aerb. That might have some unfortunate implications for trying to get a soul out of the hells.”

“Why is Fallatehr the solution to every problem?” asked Grak.

“It’s a funny joke,” I said. “Hilarious.”

“We’ll work on it,” said Amaryllis. “I’ll put some clones towards it, talk to the goblins, see what can be done, but I’m not even remotely hopeful.”

Now I was left hoping that Amaryllis had found something and kept it in her back pocket, but it didn’t seem like the kind of thing that she would have done, not in the modern era, at least. If she’d made it out, which I desperately hoped she had, maybe she would figure something out. Who knew how long that would take though, and in the meantime, I was probably stuck in the hells unless I could find my own way back to Aerb, which … well, I wasn’t counting on it.

I had no idea where to go or what to do. With the yellow-fall, it was hard to see more than a hundred feet away from me, and all the directions seemed to be the same, except maybe for some slight changes in elevation. If they were searching for me with infernoscopes, or Valencia … but there were lots of hells to search and ground to cover. For Valencia to find me would require some kind of infernal to see me, and I wanted to put that off for as long as possible. To get myself noticed by an infernoscope, it would be best to write something on the ground, but with all the yellow-fall, that wouldn’t work, since it would be covered in just a moment.

I was naked. The yellow-fall stung and was leaving my skin red where it touched. I could barely see anything. I closed my eyes for three seconds and no interface showed up. I was still tall, still strong, and my arm was back, but I had none of the magic that I’d had on Aerb. Magic mostly didn’t work in the hells, but I’d been hopeful that I’d get something. I tentatively tried to summon the tuung spirit blade. I’d never really put in enough time with it, not when there were so many other skills to work on, but I’d been able to summon it on a few occasions. It was supposed to work in the hells, that was one of the reasons that the tuung had spent so much time and effort on something that was outclassed by a steel sword in most ways. After a few seconds of effort, I was able to make it appear in my hand. The other thing to check was spirit, but that didn’t seem to function in the hells. The pain I was feeling was enough to let me know that the modifications I’d done had been undone when my transition happened.

I took a few deep breaths to calm myself and went to work meditating on the spirit blade. Blade-bound, and the rest of the pseudomagics, worked in the hells, and I was going to take every advantage that I could get. With the spirit blade bound, which took some time, I was able to summon and dismiss it with a little more ease, and having it in hand meant that at least I had something.

I picked a direction and trudged forward. The yellow-fall clumped up until it was an inch thick on my feet, slowing me down. It was coating my hair and getting all over my body, caking on, and while it was possible to wipe away, there was always residue left.

After an hour of slow movement in what was probably the wrong direction, if there could be said to be a right direction, the yellow-fall started to let up. I wiped more of the crud away from my face, and tried to peer out through bleary eyes to see what was on the horizon. To my left, I saw a structure, one that I might have gone straight past if the yellow-fall had kept up. There were spindly trees next to it, their limbs caked in yellow-fall, and the whole thing had a crudeness to it, built of jagged chunks of something, with a roof that was caked in yet more yellow-fall, like some bastard version of snow, almost looking like play-doh. I stared at it for a moment, trying to decide.

I was somewhere in the upper hells, at a guess, a place where the infernals weren’t terribly powerful. I’d been able to make it an hour or more without being horribly mutilated, so that was something, but even in the lowest hells it was usually possible to have a bit of a grace period, at least from what I’d read. It was definitely horrible, don’t get me wrong, but most of the horribleness came from the infernals, who used the natural environment to inflict their tortures. I hadn’t met one yet, and wasn’t looking forward to when I did. I was still tall and strong, and while I had no magic and none of the usual tools, there was a good chance that I could take on a very low level infernal, especially with the spirit blade.

I went for it, trying to keep low to the ground. I had no idea what kind of tech level to expect in this hell, what kind of amenities they would have, and who I would find in there. If there was an infernal, there was a chance that I could overpower it, possibly even trap it, then hide out, or figure out a way to make a message that could be seen from an infernoscope. There were stories of people doing things like that, though they only tended to work in the short term, and it wasn’t like you could carve out a good life in even one of the upper hells. Eventually, you’d get caught in routine sweeps, or the major powers of the hell would learn about you, or something, and then you’d get captured and become part of the mortal economy, with the right to torture you sold to the highest bidder, your suffering commodified and utilized. In the short term though, it was a halfway decent plan, assuming that I was able to temporarily take down an infernal while naked, using the spirit blade and nothing else.

As I passed by the spindly trees, I could feel them sucking at my skin, like they were trying to rip off pieces from a distance. I made my way around them, keeping my distance. With the yellow-fall basically stopped, it seemed like things were starting to wake up and shake some of it off, and I saw crimson bushes pushing their way up through the yellow-fall, spreading out red leaves as they did so. There was no sun in the sky, just a slightly dull ambient light, which made me wonder what any of this stuff was feeding on. As I got closer, I saw more buildings off in the distance, maybe a football field away, and only two of them. I decided to avoid them, at least for the time being.

The house itself, if it was a house, was made of jagged bits of metal, each bit of metal a foot or so across, all sharp edges, stuck together with a mustard-yellow mortar I assumed had something to do with the yellow-fall. There were bits of the spindly trees used in the construction too, sparingly, with evidence that the wrist-thick trunks had been straightened out, cut to length, and bound together. There were no windows, and only a single door, which was made of a heavy metal and had no obvious handhold. I waited beside it, wiping off as much of the yellow-fall as I could, hoping that something would change.

In the distance, I heard an unearthly scream, long and high-pitched. I steeled myself. They had trackers in the hells sometimes, creatures that would seek out any defenseless people they could find, and naturally, the infernals used them. I’d been in hell for maybe an hour and a half, and I hoped that I had a lot more time than that left.

The door to the house creaked open and I got ready to lunge forward and attack whoever came through. Infernals came in all shapes and sizes, and fighting one while naked didn’t appeal to me in the slightest, but it seemed like a necessity. I needed clothes, at the very least, something to keep the yellow-fall off me, and I needed a place to stay while I waited for rescue, or at least for Valencia to get a bead on me.

Instead of an infernal, it was a man. He was dressed in simple, ill-fitting clothes and carrying a bucket that was filled with something thick and brown. He didn’t see me, maybe because he was intently looking at the yellow-fall in front of him. As I watched him, I realized how broken and beaten he was, not just in the downcast eyes and grim expression, but scars and wounds wherever his skin was showing. He was missing fingers, and something was wrong with his eye. His hair was messy, with scars going through it. With a grimace, he stepped out, barefoot, into the yellow-fall, carrying his bucket with him.

I waited until the door closed to approach him.

“Hey,” I said. “Hey!”

He turned around and looked at me with wide eyes, slop coming out of his bucket.

“Zu ɦa a?” he asked, though I could only assume it was a question. His eyes kept going to my spirit blade, which was held at my side.

“Do you speak Anglish?” I asked.

“Bi ɦa a khu i wa? A r̊eni kha oma?” He asked.

I tried the languages I knew, Groglir, Gimb, even Kindeh, which so far as I knew was a dead language (that I still knew those languages was another sign that while the game system was gone, the changes it had made to me persisted). There was no telling where he was from, nor how long he’d been down here. I didn’t even know if this place had days or years. For all I knew, he’d been there for centuries, maybe even millennia. If he was here, in this geographical location, it was entirely possible that he’d been one of the many killed during Fel Seed’s initial takeover. Or maybe even earlier, before anyone had known much about the hells.

“Daṭide ɦita zura gi we a ḷama,” he said. “We olau ḷaḷukha ṭa o olau r̊ane.”

“Hey, it’s okay,” I said. “I’ll overpower the infernal in there, if I can, and we can be free. We can help each other.” Talking to him wasn’t doing an ounce of good, but he was letting out a string of words at me, so I was answering back. “Juniper,” I said, pointing at myself.

“A ḷaḷukha,” he answered.

“Lalezhe,” I said, trying to match his pronunciation. He nodded vigorously. “Stay out here, I’ll — go look at the door.” I tried to back that up with pantomime, but there was no way of knowing whether it stuck. I had hoped I’d be able to pick up his language, but there was no notification, and no click of sudden understanding.

I crept toward the door, wishing again that I had something besides just the sword, and feeling fortunate for having that. I diverted closer to one of the spindly trees, and found that it was, in fact, covered in both small needles and a dark red sap that the yellow-fall was now sliding off of. It was pulling, sucking at my skin from a distance, painful but in no danger of actually making a tear. I opted not to spend my time trying to turning it into an off-hand weapon, not if the needles or sap were going to fuck up my hands.

I opened the door slowly, working my fingers into the crack, as it didn’t have any handle. The interior was bathed in a red light, so completely red that it washed out every other color. I saw a table, chairs, and a counter filled with strange oblong shapes, and beyond that, a door to another room. I moved in quickly, keeping low to the ground, looking for the infernal. How many would I be fighting? One? Two? Even one might be a problem.

There was a knife sitting on the table next to a small puddle of something that was almost white in the red light, maybe blood. I looked the knife over and picked it up. The blade was a faint green, which meant that it must have been making its own light. I tested holding it in my offhand, then set it down again, because the weight and balance was off. The spirit blade was a single handed weapon though, and I didn’t have a shield or something else to complement it. I was worried. You couldn’t kill an infernal, but at least in the upper hells, you could injure them badly enough that you could restrain them, at least temporarily. There was infernal magic that made that not a great idea in the long term, at least most of the time, but I was still hoping that this was a short term kind of situation.

I found him in the next room, back turned to me. He was doing something with a set of ceramic jars.

I ambushed him, rushing in quickly, and as it happened, I realized that I might have fucked up. He had known I was coming, either because he’d heard me beforehand or felt my emotions. He turned to face me even as the blade moved toward him, revealing a face that opened like a flower to show off hundreds of teeth in uneven rows. Maybe he was expecting me to startle and back off, but I had faced worse, and I jammed the blade into his neck, which looked plenty fleshy. The gurgling hiss he’d been making turned into a bit of a scream, and I wrenched the blade free, backing away. If he’d been human, it would have been enough to decapitate him, but whatever was going on with his biology, it had only given him a wound.

The light was red, so it was hard to see him, and fuck if I knew what colors he actually was. In appearance though, he was surprisingly humanoid, with knobbly knees and turned-out toes, two long arms that seemed like they might reach the ground, a cluster of eyes behind the flower-head, and something at his crotch like a bunch of grapes that was all swollen, black, and shiny. He was a devil, I was guessing, because he didn’t seem to have any natural weapons except what I was generously calling his mouth.

“Zu wu ṭa?” he asked, his mouth parts moving in impossible ways to make the sound. He was clutching his neck, which was seeping out something viscous.

Step one in dealing with devils was not talking to them, and luckily, he didn’t seem to instinctively know the language I spoke. He could probably feel my confusion though, probably got off on it in some sick way, and if he spoke Anglish, it wouldn’t take him long to figure out that he could use it to speak with me. Infernals were famously good with languages.

I lunged at him again, slicing with the blade. It cut through his skin easily enough, but at least in his chest there seemed to be a lot of bones that stopped me from going further, not orderly bones like a rib cage would be, but like moguls on a ski hill hidden under his flesh. I tried piercing him from the side, but that did nothing but get my spirit blade stuck, and I was worried that I wasn’t good enough at summoning it to dismiss it and call it again.

He lunged for me again, trying to snap at me with the flesh-petals of his mouth, and again he misjudged me, because I blindly grabbed the knife from the table behind me, reared back, and then drove the knife straight down his throat. He was trying to snap around my arm, and I was cutting him up on the inside. It fucking hurt, the first time I’d felt that level of pain in a long time, and shoving a knife down someone’s throat, especially a guy with that many teeth, would probably have been a smarter move if I’d still been as durable as when I was alive.

I pulled my bloody hand from inside his throat, still holding my knife. He was looking worse than I was, choking on his own viscous fluids, clutching his throat. I let go of the spirit blade, which was still sticking in his side, then switched the knife to my uninjured left hand. I started stabbing him wherever looked least defended, occasionally slipping the knife between bones, more by luck than skill. After just a moment’s hesitation, I started stabbing at the black grapes where his crotch was, popping more of them with every thrust. They were juicy, bursting with a liquid that smelled so bad I almost stopped. The devil was losing energy though, so I continued on, over and over, until I was driving the knife into a patch of juicy black flaps.

He never actually stopped moving, just slowed down enough that I wasn’t in any real danger. You couldn’t kill a devil, not unless you were Val or something equally scary, you could only injure or incapacitate, and I had to remind myself of that as the haze of adrenaline fell over me. I tried to break his arms, but they were beyond what strength I could bring to bear, especially as I was without clothes. The resistance of the infernals to incapacitation varied wildly across the hells, and in this particular hell, it seemed that relatively rapid regeneration was combined with a nearly indestructible skeleton and joints that were stronger than anything I could bring to bear, even once I’d retrieved my spirit blade. He was down, but I would have to keep up the assault. There would be no way to leave him alone for any period of time, not unless I could tie him down and bury him, and there were probably some kind of defenses against that, even if they were slow defenses.

My arm was bleeding heavily, and I was feeling the blood loss. I was still totally naked, without any tools but the spirit blade and a very small knife. The hells usually came with some level of regeneration, but the upper hells had less of it, and I wasn’t sure that I was actually going to make it. If you died in hell, you ended up in a lower hell, and as a general rule, lower hells were worse. It was also probably not where they expected to find me.

I laid the devil out on the floor, then flipped the table over and pressed it down on top of him before piling as much junk as I could on top of it. I didn’t think it would hold him for long, but I didn’t have many other options.

I wondered how long it would take either Valencia or someone with an infernoscope to find me.

There was a chance they wouldn’t save me. Valencia could kill the infernals around me, but doing that would send up a red flag to the infernals, and keeping the secret of so many deaths contained — well, I didn’t know that it was impossible, but it would be difficult. There had been other buildings in the distance, and I assumed that they had infernals of their own, but it also seemed like we were in the middle of nowhere. If the party could find me somehow, then maybe it would be safe to kill those infernals. Eventually though, someone would come out to this place, either attempting to track me or trying to get in contact with someone they expected. Maybe that would be fine, in the short term, days, not weeks. That would still leave me stranded in the hells though, with no way home.

I picked the knife back up from the floor and walked to the front door, peeking through the crack slightly to see whether the guy I’d seen before was still there. He had vanished. I didn’t know how long it would take the devil to come fully back to life, nor whether it would be able to move the weight on top of him, but I couldn’t just hole up in there indefinitely. I went through the house as quickly as I could, eventually finding a cloak that I could wear and some pants that I couldn’t fit into. There wasn’t much in the way of clothing, just another cloak that seemed sized for the infernal, and I put it on as well. I tore off a leg of the pants and wrapped it around my arm, which was already clotting. I looked for something to wash up with, but eventually settled for wiping off as much yellow-fall as I could with what was left of the pants.

I stepped outside, looking in the direction of the other buildings. The remainder of the yellow-fall had cleared, and I could see that I was in a valley of some kind, though there was no river. At the tops of the hills were more buildings, and I wondered how many had infernals inside them. Probably a lot. That didn’t bode well for me, especially not with how comparatively badly that first fight had gone. With the blood loss, I wasn’t sure that I could win another.

I heard a screaming sound from above, and looked up. I couldn’t remember how long I’d fallen, but it had seemed like a long time, though the impact hadn’t been nearly as hard as it should have been. Instinctively, I expected it to be another person falling, and I could vaguely see the shape. They were far away, back the way I’d come, and I started walking toward them even before they hit the ground. Most of the yellow-fall was gone, evaporated, or whatever had happened to it, but what remained quickly caked my feet again, stinging the skin, which didn’t do much to take my mind off the cuts all over my arm.

I was worried about the new arrival. If this rough geographic area corresponded to Fel Seed’s domain, then someone who arrived was likely to be someone killed there. Lots of people lived in the City of a Thousand Brides, but I was pretty sure he didn’t often kill them for sport. I counted myself lucky to have been killed by him, in fact, if that was what had happened. Someone arriving here meant that it might have been one of my people. I couldn’t account for the time difference though. It had been two hours, or something like it, maybe as much as three. I had been the last one left, or I should have been. Bethel would have needed to dump the people we’d tried to pick up, so it was possible she’d done a short-range transport before teleporting out, if she hadn’t just killed, bottled, and incinerated them during the fight. Had Fel Seed made a capture I hadn’t seen, then waited to murder one of my companions? Had no one else actually escaped? Was the hope of rescue from without actually doomed?

Whoever it was had landed in what was left of the yellow-fall and gotten coated with the stuff, same as I was. She — obviously a she, given the lack of clothes — let out a groan and got to her feet, then let out a primal scream of anger. I had sped up, because I knew that scream of anger. Even if I hadn’t, I wouldn’t have missed the pointed ears or the scarred arms.

“Fenn,” I said as I reached her. “Fenn!”

She looked me over. “You look like hell,” she said.

Department

“Fenn,” I said again, not believing it. Fenn Fenn Fenn Fenn. She looked exactly like I remembered her, minus the yellow-fall all over her and the grim expression. If infernals had illusion or shapeshifting power, I might have questioned whether she was real, but outside of some unknown and powerful magic, always a remote possibility, the only explanation was that it was really her.

“I guess I should get the I-told-you-sos out of the way before we get tortured for all eternity,” said Fenn. She pointed a finger at me. “We should never have gone in for a meeting with those assholes.”

I stared at her. “You never said that,” I replied, trying to find my footing. I knew, almost soon enough to not say it, that it was the wrong tack to take.

“I did, Joon,” replied Fenn. “Or maybe not in so many words, but I did my part to raise doubts, and I got brushed aside, as usual. And now, unless I missed something very obvious, we’re dead.” She looked me over again. “Seems like I died after you did. Give me a cloak.”

I handed it over, and the knife as well, meager defense though it was. “They’re mounting a rescue effort,” I said, as my brain caught up with the situation. Fenn was the last person I would have expected to drop right next to me in the specific hell that I was already in, but if that was what was happening, then it was the hand of something or someone who was, presumably, on our side. I didn’t know how, or even who, but this was proof that something was happening. The last I’d checked, the bottle containing Fenn’s soul had been in Sable, but Amaryllis took it out whenever she went into the time chamber so that it wouldn’t run down faster. That had been at my request, just in case.

“A rescue effort?” asked Fenn, still walking through the snow. “Fucking who, because I’m pretty sure I watched us get our asses handed to us. We’re not stacked on allies.”

“You — you missed some stuff,” I said. “They’ll be looking for us with infernoscopes, I think, or maybe they already know where we are, but —” I stopped where I was, looking after her. “Where the fuck are you going?”

She stopped and turned to me. “I never wanted to end up in the hells,” she said. “Really, really, never. That said, I’m a clever girl, and I thought about it some, and I decided that if it ever happened, probably because someone royally fucked up, or I pushed the limits one too many times, I would have a plan. I would go do my best to find a cosy little hole somewhere, bury myself deep, and go as long as possible before the infernals got their hooks into me.” She turned back and began trudging again.

“Amaryllis is going to rescue us!” I shouted. “It won’t be another — I don’t know, half hour, less.” I had very little confidence in that estimate.

Fenn turned back to me. “Juniper, I know you have a fuckload of faith in her, and I do too, but she’s a fucking teenager, and besides that, I watched her get fucking drowned out just before we died. If she’s alive, how’s she going to manage a rescue from the hells in a half hour?”

“We didn’t die there,” I said. “Fenn, against those guys, we didn’t die, it was — it was only you. I’m sorry. It’s been … I don’t know. Months.”

Fenn stared at me. “Did you seriously plan a rescue mission to grab me from the hells?” she asked. Her eyes had gone wide.

“No,” I said, wishing that I had, if it turned out that there had been a way to do it. “I died fighting Fel Seed.”

She stared at me some more. “If you keep talking, is this going to get more confusing or less confusing?” she asked. “Also, what happened to your arm?”

“Stuck it in a devil’s mouth,” I said, glancing down at where the blood-soaked pant leg was painfully stuck to me. “Not actually important, I don’t think. Like I said, there’s some kind of rescue effort going on up top. That’s the only reason you’d be here right now.”

“I died and … you bottled me,” said Fenn, staring at me. “And then, months later, you went to go fight Fel Seed, because you’re obsessed with getting Uther back, and you died. So … someone took the bottle with my soul in it, and dumped it on the ground, and that’s why I’m here?”

“Probably,” I said. “It seems plausible.”

I heard a howl from in the distance, long and guttural. Fenn and I stared in the direction it came from.

“How’d we end up in the same hell?” asked Fenn. “In the same place in the same hell?”

“Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle had a method,” I said. “Some way of injecting souls right where he wanted them to go, perfected as a means to sell souls to the infernals. Which means,” I frowned, trying to think.

“Wait, why’d —” she lowered her voice, “the zombie guy?” asked Fenn.

“A dragon made us,” I said. “Can you give me a second to think?”

“We’ve literally got eternity,” said Fenn. She looked in the direction of the howl. “Or about five minutes until we get captured.”

“There’s a rescue attempt,” I said. “Or there should be, unless — unless they sent you here to help me, and they don’t actually have a way out. If they were using soul injection, that means that it’s been a while, enough time for them to come up with a plan —”

“You think they’d just casually come up with a plan to do something that no one in history has ever done?” asked Fenn.

“No one we know of,” I said. “No one who’s publicized it. We might not be the first though.”

“So you’re saying we can’t split up?” she asked. “I can’t find my own corner of this hell, I have to be with you?”

I raised my hands, trying to verbalize my confusion. “That’s the part of being in hell that you don’t like?” I asked. “The fact that you’re with me?”

“Don’t make me sound like a child,” Fenn replied, folding her arms. She had started moving again, away from the howling, but it was hard to go very fast, and probably a bad idea given how likely we would be to step on something nasty. “I specifically and on multiple occasions asked that if I died, my soul would be bottled up until it went to oblivion. And now I’m here, and you’re saying that this is all part of some plan.”

“I’m not saying that,” I said. “I have no idea, Fenn, I died, and me dying wasn’t in our planning document. I’m just saying … if they did find some way to get me out of the hells, then obviously they would use it on other people as well, if that were possible. If it comes to people that Amaryllis wants brought back to life, you and I are at the top of the list.”

“And who else is dead?” asked Fenn. “Who else should we be looking for?”

“Uh,” I said, trying to think. “Gemma, I guess?” She had been bottled though.

 “The fox?” asked Fenn. “Was she … part of the team?”

“Yeah,” I said. “Pallida was too, and Heshnel, at least for a bit. Pallida died but is back already.”

“Fuck,” said Fenn. “You said it had only been what, a few months?”

“Yeah,” I said. “Hard to track time, since I’ve been in and out of a time chamber.”

“Seems like you got a lot done,” said Fenn. She cocked her head to the side. “Which of the girls are you sleeping with?”

Again we heard the howl off in the distance. It seemed closer than before.

“Maybe we should do something about that,” I said, summoning my spirit blade to my hand. I looked around for a better weapon for Fenn. The paring knife wasn’t quite worthless in a fight, but it was close. If I’d fought a devil, I didn’t like my chances against a demon.

“Stop avoiding the question,” said Fenn.

“Really?” I asked. “You understand that we probably need to stick together, right? That we also probably need to avoid dying? If we die, we go down to another hell, and there’s no guarantee that we go down to the same hell. We don’t know what form the rescue is going to take —”

“You know I’m smart, right?” asked Fenn. “Maybe not a genius, maybe not even that smart, but I’m not a dumb baby moron you need to explain everything to. I understand. I understood the first time you said it. I’m sticking with you. I also don’t know how you expect to outrun whatever that thing is, or how we’re going to fight it given that we’re both basically naked. So why don’t you just tell me who you’re fucking, and we rip off the band-aid while we wait to be mauled to death by something we can only hope is as puny as a wolf.”

I tried to understand where she was coming from. For her, it was a few days after we’d broken up, and less than an hour after the fight where she’d been killed. It made no sense to focus on the personal stuff, but I was doing my best to understand where she was coming from, and maybe it felt more real to her, or at least like it was easier to focus on than what she was assuming was a lifetime of being abused by infernals.

“Amaryllis and I got married,” I said.

“Lucky guy,” sighed Fenn. She was still looking at me as we trudged forward. “Whom else?”

I resisted the urge to correct her use of  ‘whom’, which I knew she had done just to needle me and divert me from the conversation. It was classic Fenn, even, or especially, in the middle of a serious conversation. Even, or especially, when we were both nearly naked and walking through hell while something that was hopefully just a kind of wolf was howling and getting closer.

“Bethel got handsy with me,” I said.

“Wait,” said Fenn. It took her a moment. “No shit?”

“No,” I said. “Not the kind of thing I would joke about.”

“Fuck,” said Fenn. Her face softened. “You okay?”

“I’m literally in hell,” I said. “Lost a fair bit of blood, though it seems to be a bit better. But as far as the Bethel stuff … it was a while ago. We needed her, for the big final battle against Fel Seed, and … we made peace, I guess.” I was never going to be her friend, but the sick feeling has faded, a little.

“There,” said Fenn, pointing off in the distance, back the way we’d been. The thing on the hilltop didn’t particularly look like a wolf. It had two legs and a long tail, with fluted horns, and even from a distance its exterior shell looked like it was made of glistening, crusty dirt. A long, narrow mouth was dripping ochre liquid onto the ground. On either side of him were large infernals, demons from the looks of them, and with all the trouble I’d had taking on a devil, I didn’t think that I was going to be able to beat both of them, not with the wolf thing too, not even with Fenn’s help.

“We should have run,” I said.

“With this shit?” asked Fenn, gesturing at what remained of the yellow-fall. “They’ll be on us.” She looked at my injured arm, then at the spirit blade. “You killed one?”

“Not one as strong as those,” I said. The wolf-thing was being held back by a long lead, and the demons were staring down at us. “And you can’t kill them.”

“You take the left one, I’ll take the right,” said Fenn.

“You think we can?” I asked, looking her over. She was still completely nude, save for the cloak, and smeared with the yellow-fall, same as me. She was holding the pen knife in her fist, its small blade sticking out two inches. A part of me couldn’t believe that she was really back. There were so many things about her that I had forgotten, or if not forgotten, that weren’t actively part of my memories of her. There were little features of her voice, a very slight accent that might have betrayed the alternating months at the Isle of Eversummer. There was the way her muscles tensed, and the way she stood so that the ritual scars on her arm stuck up from the surface.

“You’ve got your sword,” said Fenn, “And I’ve got mine.” She gestured with the little pen knife. She looked at the demons. “If all else fails, I’m going to bite them.”

I was worried she would run ahead and attack them, but she waited, the same as I did, tensed and ready for an attack. I didn’t actually know what they were waiting for.

Eventually, they let the wolf thing go, and as soon as his lead was unhooked, he bolted for us. I crouched down, trying to figure out a plan of attack, holding my spirit blade in front of me. When it came close enough, I rushed towards it, trying my best to slice up its face. The blade bounced off though, like hitting metal, and I skidded backward, trying to grab the wolf-thing by its horns as it attempted to bite me. A glance at the demons on the hill showed that they were still there, still watching. Maybe it was bloodsport for them.

I got bitten in the thigh, his long snout rubbing wet and rough against me, but I got a handle on first one horn, then the other, and maneuvered myself around so that I was behind him, out of the way of him. My cut up arm felt weak, and I was bleeding freely from the leg, but I was still really fucking strong, and I had fought all kinds of creatures before, including a week of clean-up in Li’o.

“Blind him!” I shouted, and Fenn moved forward, more tentative than I remembered her being. She grabbed the creature’s head as I held it down, then started stabbing her knife into various parts of his eye clusters. Once that was finished, I was able to situate myself on top of his back. I tried twisting the horns, but my hands were covered in both blood and the yellow-fall, making it too difficult to maneuver the head. I didn’t even know if this thing could be decapitated, or whether it had a nervous system, or veins we could puncture. It was thrashing around, trying to get me off, so I let it and tumbled to the side, getting freshly covered with yellow-fall and scrambling to pick my spirit blade back up.

The wolf-thing limped off away from us, badly wounded and whimpering.

“You go right, I go left?” I asked Fenn, looking at the two demons still standing on top of the hill. They could probably feel my pain, which was like ecstasy to them.

“Yeah,” said Fenn.

The demons descended down from the hill, moving slowly. They were wearing large cloaks that partially obscured their forms, but I could see large clawed feet beneath the one on the right, and something more like a chicken leg from the one that I was going to be after. I had never fought a bird before.

I glanced at Fenn. She seemed nervous.

“They’re impossible to kill,” I said. “But we should be able to hurt them enough that —”

The demon that I’d called dibs on launched himself off the side of the hill, leaving his cloak behind. He had barely any torso at all, just a long, sinuous spine with metal barbs coming out of the side of it that made a shape like a rib cage, all of which led up to a head like a baby’s. Instead of arms, it had a coiled tentacle in the center of the ‘ribs’. The other demon was chunky, with eyes on stalks that looked pretty vulnerable, and a thickness everywhere else that seemed like it was going to pose a problem.

I focused on my own demon though, trying to think of ways to hurt it given its unique physiology. It was faster than me, taller than me, and fairly likely to be stronger. The tentacle in the center of its chest looked vulnerable, like a prehensile tongue, but it was coiled up in there, and behind sharp bits of metal.

When he got within five feet of me, I held the spirit blade in front of me, waiting for an opening. The plan was to stab the tentacle and hope that I didn’t get too sliced up in the process. Whatever healing factor the hell provided — the one good upside, and only there to make the tortures endless — it didn’t seem to work very fast.

I lunged forward, and while I got my blade through the sharp bits of metal, I did nothing but give the tentacle a nick. Worse, the metal bars had a substantial difference from ribs, which was that they could move independently of each other. They clamped down on the blade, so hard that it felt like it was going to break, and I lost my grip.

The metal ribs opened up, save for the ones that held the spirit blade, and the tentacle snaked out. It was longer than I’d thought, long enough to wrap around my neck and start squeezing the life from me. I’d known that demons were strong, and exceptional fighters, but I hadn’t been prepared to have my ass handed to me quite so quickly. I tried kicking, hoping to bend one of the chicken legs the wrong way, and I had my hands free, but punching the appendage around my neck seemed to do nothing, and it was cutting off my blood flow.

I never really gave up, but at a certain point my body stopped cooperating. I looked over at Fenn and for a horrified second thought that she was dead, but it was an overreaction, because there was still some life left in her. Infernals didn’t kill people if it could at all be helped. We were valuable, so rare and precious that these two finding us would be like a person back on earth coming across a stack of gold bars.

I blacked out, and when I woke up, I was in a room with much better furnishing than the house I’d been in before. For the most part, it was all the same materials, but they were put together much more competently. I was mildly surprised to see straight lines and square edges, given that it must have been made by infernals, but I supposed some of that was practicality and engineering considerations that weren’t substantially different in this hell. It wasn’t clean though, and looking down, I could see a considerable amount of dried blood on the floor. Some of it was probably mine, but not all of it.

I was in a chair, bound with my hands behind my back, something metal in my mouth, and my legs affixed to the floor in some way that seemed quite firm and wasn’t visible to me. It was the third time I’d been in this kind of situation, and the last two times hadn’t been a cake walk. The room had a single door, a single overhead light of the same red variety as before, and no windows.

I’d been conscious for about five minutes when a devil slithered into the room and hunched himself across the table from me. He had small, presumably vestigial wings on his back, and a surprisingly human face with drooping skin and jowls like Richard Nixon. His forearms were thin and his hands were like claws, but they carried something that very much looked like a folder.

I kept my mouth shut. The longer it took for them to figure out what languages I spoke, the better. Clearly they had questions for me. I had read enough of Valencia’s reports on the state of the hells to know that they were checking over every mortal. What they didn’t know was that I was the one they were looking for, but that was only a matter of time. Eventually, I would crack and tell them about Valencia, or tell them enough that they would be able to figure it out on their own. Devils were very good at talking to prisoners.

“I’m here to extract answers from you,” the devil said, its speech perfect and strangely feminine. Infernals didn’t really have genders, since they had variable physiology and no need to reproduce.

I said nothing, of course. Silence was the best policy, because speaking would gain me nothing.

“You’re recent,” the devil said. “You’ve been here a day, most of that blacked out.”

I said nothing. I wondered what the purpose of letting me know what they knew was. A false sense of security? To read something on my face? They didn’t need to tell me how long I’d been out. It seemed to me like it would have been better not to say. Of course, it was also perfectly possible that it was a lie.

“You have a connection to the killings,” said the infernal. “How and why is unknown, for now. Speak, and be spared.”

I couldn’t speak, not with the metal thing in my mouth. I wondered why that was there, if they wanted information from me.

As though reading my mind, the devil moved around the table to me and undid a clasp that allowed it to pull the metal bit from my mouth. I contemplated trying to bite off and swallow my tongue, but I didn’t particularly think that would work, and most likely, the devil would just end up giving me a rapid and unpleasant tracheotomy to keep me from dying. Besides, Fenn had probably been brought in with me, and I wanted us to stay in the same hell.

“You are here for an eternity,” said the devil. “Your spirit is not yet broken. You understand that it will break, in time. This is as inevitable as your death itself. And when your spirit is broken, still you will continue on, without even the comfort of insanity or catatonia.”

“Okay,” I said. “I don’t really see how saying that helps you. As yet, my spirit is not broken.”

“Tell me what you were doing in the Fel Seed exclusion zone,” said the devil.

I was sorely tempted to quip, or at least be flippant, but I stayed quiet, because speaking gave me no advantage. Saying, ‘I’m not answering any questions without a lawyer’ or ‘I know my rights, I’m entitled to a phone call’ would have been fucking hilarious though.

“You think that there’s a chance of rescue,” said the devil, his beady eyes watching me. “You think that this is … false, the reality of your eternity here.”

“Where’s the woman I was with?” I asked. I was measuring my words carefully, trying not to give anything away. It was pretty clear that the infernal was doing its best to cold read me. But in order to cold read someone, it’s best if you test them, give them small scraps of information that they can respond to, and I was hoping to get the better of the deal.

“It’s unusual for mortals to know each other,” said the devil. “Even if they died at the same time — which you didn’t.”

“You know something about the killings,” said the devil. “There’s some unknown power, and you know enough to think that it will save you. It doesn’t work like that — or it does, and you know more than I’ve been told, or more than has been revealed.”

“Okay,” I said. “Sure. And those people, the ones responsible for the murder of hundreds if not thousands of infernals, they’re watching this right now —” it occurred to me that the devil could probably tell when I was lying. I wasn’t a very good liar. “Or if they’re not, then they’ll be able to get a report from me at some point in the future, because as you said, I’m here for eternity. You think that I have some relation to the weapon that’s been killing infernals, and you locked me up. Do you think that’s wise?”

“You want to offer me a deal,” the devil nodded. “You would not honor the deal. You hate me and would not spare my life.”

“I would,” I said. “I’ve spared the lives of people I hate.”

The devil stared at me for a moment, possibly weighing things. It was hard to say.

“What will you do once I release you?” it asked.

“Nothing,” I said. “I’ll hang tight in here for now, you’ll tell me some vital details, and then I’ll work out a way to get my friend out of wherever she’s being held.”

The devil nodded, then went over to where I was sitting and began undoing the restraints, but it took some time. I didn’t know whether this was a part of my plan or his, which worried me. Still, devils weren’t exactly known for their fanatical loyalty.

“What does your weapon need in order to kill?” asked the devil.

“I’m not going to answer that,” I said.

“How do you deliver it instructions?” asked the devil, rubbing its hands together.

“I’m not going to answer that either,” I said.

“You cannot instruct it unless they’re watching you by infernoscope,” said the devil. “How will you tell them not to kill me?”

“Oh,” I said. I’d thought that it was trying to pump me for information, or that releasing me had been part of the interrogation, and maybe it was, but that was a very valid point.

“There is a chance that I will die from the weapon,” said the devil. “Even if you keep your end of the bargain.”

“Yes,” I said. “I guess that’s for you to weigh. In the meantime, we don’t have to go anywhere. When are you expected to report to your superiors about the interrogation?”

“My superior is fifteen hells away,” replied the devil, rubbing its hands together even more. “I have complete authority.”

“And where are we?” I asked.

“By Anglish accounting, this is the 78th hell,” replied the devil. “We are in the Seam of Scars, south of the Putrid Pass, a small city of some eighty thousand infernals and a thousand mortals. The city is called Rezire Kilmeros.” The devil tapped its small claws together. “This does not help you in any way.”

“No,” I said. “Probably it doesn’t. Tell me something that does help me. And remember, I’m here for an eternity, and eventually the people with the weapon are going to find me. Better that I’m able to communicate with them so that they don’t just lay waste and get you caught in the middle of it.” I was trying to say ‘weapon’ in the way that I normally said the word, but I thought even a normal person would probably have picked up on the ‘weapon’ being a person.

I was talking too much, but fuck, I had him on the ropes, didn’t I? I really did have an all-powerful weapon, one which he wouldn’t have asked about if it wasn’t still steadily and randomly killing infernals. The whole plan to keep Valencia as unknown as possible was for her to kill a whole lot, using the time chamber to sleep so they wouldn’t know she needed sleep. Thousands might have been on the low side.

“You are in a fortress of the Prime Lochan, Thyrakir, Weaver of Tongues,” said the devil. “You were brought here when you were discovered among the fallen, and I was dispatched from elsewhere in the hell to question you before more damage was done to you. Your companion is still blood-choked, waiting for my attentions in the other room.”

I had to keep in mind that the devil could read me really well, above and beyond how bad I was at lying. I felt worse at lying, somehow, and I wondered whether it was because something had happened to Amaryllis, or if my death had affected the sharing of skills we were supposed to get. If I stopped believing that I would spare this devil, then the devil would probably know, and whatever tenuous leverage I had would be lost.

“You can stay in here with me indefinitely?” I asked. “No one will interrupt us?”

“No one who values their skin,” the devil replied.

“Good,” I said. I rubbed my wrists and ankles where the restraints had been, but stopped when skin started sloughing off. I was in better shape than I’d been before the fight, thanks to the low-level healing effect of the hell, but my skin was apparently fucked up from the yellow-fall. The 78th hell though … that was shallow, and I’d still barely been able to take on that first devil at what I thought of as being a farm. He must have been rich, to have a person, so maybe it was more like a gated community.

I tried to think. I wasn’t just in a hell, I was in a hell with Fenn, who had died months earlier. That pointed toward soul injection using Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle’s technology. In theory, that could have been done as soon as ten minutes after I’d died, if Amaryllis had been working on the tech with one of her clones, and she’d had Fenn’s soul in a bottle there. But to inject the soul would mean that they knew where I was, and if they knew where I was, then they should have been able to have Valencia clear the infernals around me. They wouldn’t have put Fenn in with me unless they had a plan, I was convinced of that, but they wouldn’t have been able to have a plan until I died, and it would take time.

All that left me with the question of what the next step was. I was hoping that it wasn’t something that I had to do, because even if this devil was taking my threat seriously, if it wasn’t just a ruse, I was seriously constrained.

“Alright,” I said. “Take me to see Fenn.”

“I cannot,” said the devil. “I have authority, but it is not ultimate. If —”

“Find a way to make it happen,” I said. “I need to speak with her, to … I don’t know.”

“You are expecting rescue,” said the devil. “Failing that, you are expecting your weapon to lay waste.”

“I am,” I said. “Your job is to make sure that you’re not killed by accident when the shooting starts. The best way of doing that is to make sure that I’m together with Fenn.”

The devil watched me for a moment, then gave a little head bob. “Stay here.”

I was hesitant to do that, but I didn’t really have a choice. I was fully aware that perhaps I was being manipulated, and that this ploy of threatening the devil might have the unintended consequence of revealing more — too much — about Valencia and her capabilities. I was more worried about my own situation though, and the unknowable conditions on Aerb that had led to Fenn being down here with me. I thought I had put together most of the puzzle pieces, but I couldn’t figure out why Valencia wasn’t helping, not unless she was dead, but if that were the case, then what was the plan? Actually, even with Valencia helping, what was the plan? It wasn’t like trying to pull someone from the hells was a new problem, but to my knowledge, it had never been done successfully, and I had searched after Fenn died, spent my time reading the literature, even talked to some of the librarians about it when I was there. It was well-trod ground, and nothing in the game system so much as hinted at a solution, not that the game system was making itself known.

The parts of my skin where the yellow-fall had been were now red, which meant virtually everywhere given that I’d fallen in the stuff and then trudged through it while it was falling. It was worse in some places than others, itchy on my legs, which had it thoroughly caked on, and I reached down to scratch while I thought about our situation. I stopped as soon as I realized that was a bad idea. Beneath the layers of skin I’d accidentally removed it was wet and red, stinging against the open air.

I was astonished by how high in the hells we were, given how terrible it already was.

The devil, whose name I hadn’t gotten and didn’t care about, came back into the room, carting Fenn on a dolly. He closed the door tightly behind him, then took something off from around her neck and undid the rest of her restraints.

The devil watched her, and me.

“How long is it going to take?” I asked.

“It is painful for me to be around you,” said the devil. “Hope, courage, and relief are anathema for a devil.”

“I know that,” I said. I also didn’t care.

“I need to stay here,” it said. “It is necessary for me to be in this room so they do not understand what has happened. Neither of you can leave, even under my supervision. They would see through you in an instant.”

“But you could convince them,” I said. “Convince them that I only thought I was in control of things.”

The devil gave a non-committal bob of its head.

“We,” said Fenn. “We got our asses handed to us, didn’t we?” She was blinking and looking around, until her eyes fixed on the devil. “The fuck is going on?”

“I told this devil we weren’t going to kill him,” I said. “They know that we have a method of killing infernals, and that the weapon would, ultimately, listen to me if I begged for a reprieve.”

Fenn watched me for a moment, then nodded.

“There is no escape from the hells,” said the devil.

“Yeah?” asked Fenn. “Then I guess we’ll just have to set up a little villa somewhere around here, get waited on hand and foot, and murder anything that comes within twenty miles of us.”

“The power does not work on beasts or magic,” the devil said. It was a probing statement, said not because he thought it was true, but because he wanted to see what we would reveal in our expressions.

“Is this fucking guy threatening us?” asked Fenn, looking at me.

“That, and gathering information,” I said. “Our leverage over him is limited and he’s planning for the future. Best way out of getting permanently obliterated for right now is for him to do the unpleasant work of listening to us, but I’m guessing that as an interrogator he’s got plenty of experience with that.”

“Huh?” asked Fenn.

“Interrogators can’t just rely on torture and tricks,” I said. “They need positive emotions from the people they have captured. Someone who’s in a haze of pain and discomfort won’t necessarily be as pliant, or not in the way you might want. But the emotions that it might need a person to feel aren’t necessarily ones that are pleasant for an infernal.”

I waited for the devil to nod in agreement, but it sat there, stoic. It probably didn’t want to give me the satisfaction.

“So we’re just sitting here?” asked Fenn. “Waiting for rescue? You’ve got that much faith in Amaryllis?”

My eyes moved to the devil. I wondered whether that name was familiar to him. So far as he’d told me, he was someone high up in the infernal hierarchy, tasked with this interrogation because it was important. There were a buttload of infernals, something like two and a half trillion of them, but most weren’t actually part of any grand organization, either ‘commoners’ who had no mortals of their own, or part of a small fiefdom in one way or another, answerable to each other only through threats of force or occasional taxes, but not actually ‘unified’ in any real way.

“I do,” I said, turning back to Fenn. “She wouldn’t have put you down here with me unless she had a damned good plan. She cares too much about you for that. And even if I didn’t think she was coming, what can we do? We’re stuck down here, unless there’s some secret way out of the hells that the infernals have kept hidden for thirty thousand years. Given that Aerb has had infernoscopes trained on the hells for a long time, it seems like we would have found it.”

“Infernoscopes don’t go all the way down,” said Fenn, crossing her arms.

“Okay?” I asked, shrugging. “I’m just saying — if you have a plan that you like better, let me know, and we can implement it, but we want to be highly visible and findable on the infernoscopes, if they don’t have eyes on us already.”

“We’re in a room with no windows,” said Fenn. “Not very visible.” Infernoscopes could look inside walls, but it was hinky work, and she was right.

“You’re right,” I said. “Better if we were clearly visible from an aerial view.” I looked at the devil.

“I cannot move you,” it said, shaking its head, wobbling its jowls. “I am not above suspicion.”

“It’s also not in your interests to help us,” I said. “And the only thing we can threaten you with is death.”

“Not true,” said Fenn. “I mean, we don’t just have threats. You could make him king of the devils,” she said. “Kill everyone in line ahead of him, or whatever,” she made a ‘yadda yadda yadda’ motion with her hands.

“Doable,” I said, frowning.

“You intend to kill every infernal to the last,” said the devil. “You intend to create nine thousand hells full of people with happy, comfortable lives.” His expression was impossible to read.

“Yeah,” I said. “I mean, I have no way of actually doing that right now, but —”

“You might,” the devil replied. “You have reason to think it is within your power.”

I nodded, not seeing the point in a deception he would see through. “But I wouldn’t actually need to kill the infernals, if I could make the hells into anti-hells. I don’t believe that retribution for the enormous crimes of the infernals is good or necessary. All I’d have to do is silo all two and a half trillion of you away, then change what you respond to so that you could, I don’t know, have some flourishing trade in cultural products or simulacra.” I wasn’t set on that, and in theory, a heaven, even for infernals, wouldn’t make either resource gathering, materials processing, or labor a necessity.

“So we’re seriously just waiting?” asked Fenn. “Just hanging out in a jail cell with this dude, hoping that they find us, that Amaryllis opens up an impossible door back to Aerb?”

“I guess,” I said. “Ideally, we’d paint some kind of sign on the roof.”

“Impossible,” said the devil. It might have been a lie, but I had no way to force him. “I need to step out. Do not leave under any circumstances.”

“Why do you need to step out?” I asked.

“The people who own this place will want an explanation,” said the devil. “They were promised they could have you after the interrogation was completed. The sooner the explanation happens, the longer I can keep you here.”

It sounded suspect, but I naturally distrusted everything this devil said, just by its nature. What was he going to do if he left though? What did keeping him here actually gain us? It would be nice to have a conversation in relative privacy, and if Valencia went in chewing through infernals, it was actually better that there be breadcrumbs for her to follow.

“Okay,” I said. “Go.”

It left the room, and I breathed out a bit.

“The fuck happened to your leg?” asked Fenn.

“Oh,” I said. “Don’t try to scratch where the yellow-fall is. Skin came off.” It was already glossy though, starting to slowly heal in a way I didn’t think would have happened up on Aerb, and the damage I’d done to my ankles and wrists was more or less undone, still itchy but not stinging. I couldn’t use bone magic even if I’d had bones to spare, so I was stuck with accelerated natural healing. It was the first time in a long time that an injury couldn’t just be wiped away with a thought.

“Fuck,” said Fenn.

“Do you want the chair?” I asked, standing up. “It’s probably marginally more comfortable than the floor.”

“Sure,” she said. We traded places, and I sat down on the floor.

“You were not kidding when you said ‘marginal’,” she said after a moment.

“I mean, they are infernals,” I replied. “The less comfortable we are, the more comfortable they are.”

“No clothes,” she said, looking down at herself, then at me.

“Not the sexy kind of nudity though,” I said. “And I guess they wouldn’t have all that much reason to have lots of human or elf clothes around.”

“Suppose not,” replied Fenn. She ran her tongue over her teeth. “I guess at some point I’m going to need you to tell me everything I missed.”

“Sure,” I said. I drummed my fingers against the floor. “Were you thinking now?”

“Not like we’re doing anything else,” she said. “You can give me the short version. Punch up the boring parts, please. Explain how you went from mourning my death to literally marrying Mary in like two months.”

“It was a sham marriage, at first,” I said. “We,” I thought for a minute. “There was some boring shit with Anglecynn about our supposed crimes and the best way out of it was to get married in the middle of a court session. I asked for a trial by combat, which was a whole thing. But after —”

“Wait,” said Fenn. “Did you … fight Onion?”

“Yeah,” I said. “Then it turns out that Hyacinth was —”

“Sorry,” said Fenn. “Onion Penndraig, the greatest swordsman alive, survivor of two separate trials by adversity, and the leader of the Host? That Onion?”

“That Onion,” I nodded.

“Using Bethel as one of your entads?” asked Fenn.

“Oh,” I said. “Uh, no. We were on the outs.”

“Shit,” said Fenn. “Right. Was that … bad?”

“Which?” I asked. “Things with Bethel, or fighting Onion?”

“Whichever you want to talk about, I guess,” said Fenn.

I sighed, trying to think. “Fighting Onion was … I don’t know,” I said. “I was nervous as hell, but I also hated him, and it felt like the fight went on forever. He had a ridiculous sword that could copy the powers of other swords, and an armor that kept bringing him back to life, and I had to break out a lot of tricks of my own. I was hopped up on a whole bunch of souls that were giving me advantages … if I’m being honest, and it makes me feel a little bad looking back on it, I loved it. I loved the mastery, the dominance, I loved clowning on him, the close calls, coming out on top … Raven talked to me afterward, saying that it wasn’t the kind of thing that Uther would have done, that he would have approached it with grace and dignity. I tend to agree.”

“Raven,” said Fenn. “Meaning … Uther’s knight, that Raven?”

“That Raven,” I nodded. “I guess you never met her. Weird to think about. She, uh, looks just like Maddie. Older though, I guess, not just because she’s an Ell. A bit morose, kind of humorless. I don’t think you’d like her very much. We get along though, in our way.”

“Onion was one of my favorite guys,” said Fenn. “Huh.”

“Favorite … why?” I asked. “I thought you had a healthy hatred for nobility.”

“Yeah, but you probably heard the stories about him,” she said. “I mean, I assume you talked to him enough to know his whole deal before you killed him. That wonderful fucker would go up to people, spit in their face, then murder them when they tried to fight him. I really envied that.”

I frowned. “I read your letter, by the way,” I said.

“Letter?” she asked.

“The one you wrote for if you died?” I asked. “Amaryllis gave it to me, once she knew I would accept that you really were dead.”

“Ah,” said Fenn. “I’m going to be honest, that was so long ago that I’ve got no idea what was in it. Maybe some sappy stuff about wanting to be your girlfriend forever, which, looking back —”

“I meant more stuff about you trying to be a better person,” I said. “Hearing you talk about Onion, that maybe you being a better person seems a bit more aspirational than I was thinking?”

“Ah,” said Fenn. “You know, good thought.” She nodded, then leaned forward onto the table, spreading out so she was flopped down against it. She looked at the door, as if weighing whether it was worth getting into, but we clearly had time. “Onion was a fantasy, I guess. I imagined myself as him, in those stories they told. There are stupid fucking pricks all around you, you don’t fit in with their uptight shit, you get the better of them through grit and determination. You can see how it would appeal, right? Especially to a teenage version of me? For a woman of a certain age, Onion was — and I hope you’ll forgive me — the sexiest thing on two legs. All the prestige and power of a noble, all the rebellious bad boy spirit you could ask for, strong and skilled. Just, really fuckable. And well hung, they said.”

“Yeah,” I said. “Now that you say it, I can see your perspective. Not the well hung bit, I guess.”

“Amaryllis never told you I had a thing for him?” asked Fenn.

“No,” I said. “I … I guess she always did know you better than I did. And maybe she knew I was going to end up facing him.”

Fenn shrugged, lifting her shoulders briefly from the table. “So you married Mary in order to kill Onion. Raven was, I assume, a companion?”

“We’re way out of order,” I said. “But yes. Uh, before that, I went to a place called the Infinite Library, which had every book ever published. That was not long after you died. Then we went to Li’o, to get me still magic and vibrational magic, and it turned out to be a ploy by Figaro Finch to get me to look into some conspiracy or something. We didn’t figure it out in time, so this giant antimemetic monster came down from the clouds and killed thousands of people before I murdered it.”

“You fought a kaiju?” asked Fenn. “Nice.” She was still laying across the table.

“Everything in Anglecynn was after that,” I said. “Oh, and after the fight with Onion, Hyacinth, if you remember her —”

“We killed her husband!” Fenn exclaimed, briefly raising a weak fist of triumph.

“She summoned the Cannibal,” I said.

Fenn sat up. “No shit? How’d that go?”

“Paper bag over the head,” I said. “Not before he punched out a dragon and killed hundreds of Penndraigs though. I got all the credit for that, somehow. The punching out a dragon, not the killing Penndraigs.”

“So you’re saying when we get back, we’re going to have a pissed off dragon?” asked Fenn.

“Nope,” I said. “I killed him. And the other one.” I smiled at her, feeling a little better, despite all the various pains I was in, and our general circumstances, and the fading horror of Fel Seed’s domain. There was a little part of my brain going Fenn Fenn Fenn. It was helping to distract from the hells, which was part of the point of talking. Rescue was taking longer than I’d thought.

“Shit,” said Fenn, raising an eyebrow. “So that’s why you thought you could take on Fel Seed.”

“No,” I said. “No, we thought we could take him on because it felt like … I don’t know. We had permission to do it, I guess, or like it wouldn’t actually get easier the more we put it off, or the exclusions we were racking up were going to kill the planet. It felt like you’d have to be a fucking moron to think that ‘more power’ was what was going to do it against Fel Seed. I still think that’s correct, it just didn’t pan out.” I thought about the ambiguous tilt of the head that the Dungeon Master had given me.

“Fucking exclusions!” said Fenn, flopping back down. “You said months, how much did I miss?”

“Lots,” I said. “I’ve got a ways to go, even with the punched up stuff. We met Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle, who was producing souls to be sold to the hells, among other things, and we met Doris Finch, who actually wasn’t so bad. I was a gold mage for a bit, and smashed my way through a few exclusions on the basis of raw might. I met a god, but he was useless.” I tried to think. “I missed you, a lot. Even with how we ended things, or maybe because of that, it felt like I had been dealt a devastating blow, or like I was never going to recover. You had this whole thing about me not putting you on a pedestal, and I tried my best, but … it was sometimes hard to remember.”

“It’s been two hours for me,” said Fenn. “So, you know. Glad to know I was missed and all that, but I feel like I never actually left. And all of a sudden you’re hooking up with Mary.”

“Is that the thing that gets to you the most?” I asked. “Not me killing two dragons?”

“It’s easier to focus on the stuff with Mary,” said Fenn. “Easier to grapple with something you saw coming a mile away. Did you fuck Valencia?”

“No,” I said.

“Grak?” she asked.

“No,” I replied, rolling my eyes. “Jesus, to think that I actually wanted you back.”

“I feel like there’s something you’re leaving out, and I’m going to get it out of you,” said Fenn. “Truly, this is your personal hell. Was it Solace? Please tell me it wasn’t Solace, not unless she was old lady Solace.”

“She was never an old lady,” I said.

“She felt like an old lady, being my point,” said Fenn. “Like an old lady who was up for anything. And that wasn’t a no.”

“No,” I said. “Oh, wait, I have bad news.”

“A change of subject, I see,” said Fenn, grinning at me.

“Guilty,” I replied, holding up my hand. “Do you want the bad news or not?”

“Oh, I love bad news,” said Fenn. “Pile it on, please.”

“Skin magic got excluded,” I said.

Fenn stared at me. “What the fuck?” she asked. “Scars too?” She gestured to her arms.

“Scars too,” I nodded.

She let out a little laugh. “Oh man, that’s going to piss off some elves.”

“Maybe,” I shrugged. “I haven’t really had much interaction with the elves at all, which I think is for the best. Oh, I did visit Celestar though.”

Fenn rolled her eyes, then looked at me. “You actually visited Celestar?”

“Yup,” I said. “While I was a gold mage.”

“I think you could tell me just about anything and I would believe it,” said Fenn. “Seems like you saved all the wild times for after I was dead though.”

“Hmm,” I said. “I had sex with the locus.”

Fenn laughed, then looked at me, then laughed some more. I gave her a faint smile, and then that set her off again, until she was clutching her sides and rocking from back and forth. Maybe it was the stress more than the humor, because I didn’t think it was that funny. In the process of grabbing her sides, she sloughed off skin that had been under the yellow-fall, and she held her hands up to me, halfway between screaming and laughing.

“Fenn,” I said. “Hey, Fenn, calm down, it’s going to be okay.”

“No,” she said. “No, no, Joon, no, it’s not, we’re in fucking hell, we’re going to be tortured forever and ever, they’re not coming for us, it’s all just a part of it. That’s what they do in the hells, you have these nice moments and they’re just so that the bad moments feel worse, they’re feeding us for the slaughter.” She was crying and holding her hands out in front of her, breathing too hard. I wished that I had something to offer her, something to say, but I was as helpless as she was.

“Amaryllis is coming,” I said, keeping my voice firm, hoping that this approach would work. “She wouldn’t have put you down here if she didn’t have a plan. There are plenty of reasons that she would bide her time, and we can chew her out about it when we see her. Okay?”

Fenn gave me a weak nod.

Five minutes later, there was a knock on the door. I got up from the floor and moved over to it, unsure who it could possibly be, or why they would be knocking. The earlier fight with the demons showed me that I wasn’t a match for them, at least not without some kind of weapon. If the devil had run off to tell someone, then we were in trouble, and maybe a lot of trouble, depending on the circumstances of the presumed rescue attempt.

The door creaked open, and it was, of course, Amaryllis Penndraig.

Tartarology

She was dressed in a cloak and simple clothes, barefoot, but she held a spirit blade in one hand, and looked set and determined, as she often did. She slipped into the room before I could say anything, in part because I had no idea what I was going to say, and she dismissed the spirit blade before looking us over.

“Alright,” she said. “We’re light on time and things topside have gone south.” She turned to me. “Juniper, it’s been nearly three years.”

“Shit,” I said. “My questions can wait.” She’d said we were short on time.

“Good,” she replied. She looked at Fenn. “Are you okay? Because I have a big ask coming.”

“Does it get me out of the hells?” she asked.

“Probably,” said Amaryllis. “Ideally, we’d have had another year of planning. I’m going to lay out the plan and its constraints, and I’ll take questions at the end.”

“How’d you get in here?” asked Fenn.

“I don’t really have time for your horseshit,” said Amaryllis. “I love you, and I’ve missed you, but shut your fucking mouth, ask only mission-critical questions, and then do exactly as I say, because there’s a good chance that things are going to get fucked.”

“She wasn’t this prickly when I was on Aerb,” said Fenn. She looked at me. “I’m sure it’s a coincidence that she also got married to you in the meantime.” She looked back at Amaryllis. “Sorry, that was the last time.” She made a motion like she was locking her mouth and throwing away the key.

“There’s a way back to Aerb from within the hells,” said Amaryllis. “It was extraordinarily difficult to find, and we’d wanted to use other methods, but there were some last minute problems. Unfortunately, our method is sitting at the very bottom of the hells, in the Omega Hell. Our weapon can provide cover and we have an array of infernoscopes to help monitor our descent in order to facilitate, but odds are we’re not going to be able to do this quietly. The plan is for each of us to kill ourselves as many times as it takes to get to the Omega Hell, then take conveyance to the Fortress of the Gilded Behir. Depending on the specifics of the fall, that’s going to be some ways away. When you get to the Omega Hell, someone will be inserted to help you. From there, we’ll break into the armory where the magical construct is and make our return to Aerb. This will be easy, because every infernal in a twenty mile radius around us is going to be killed, and it will be difficult, because there are other deterrents. It’s also unclear how quickly we can go about suiciding our way down to the Omega Hell. Now, any mission-critical questions?”

“What’s the best way for us to kill ourselves?” I asked. “The hells are variable, and if we wind up in hell 8999, we should be virtually immortal. If the weapons crew is on top of things there won’t be demons to kill us, and they probably wouldn’t anyway.”

“Destroying the brain usually works,” said Amaryllis. “Which hell you go to is random, a curve centered on roughly four hundred hells below, meaning an average of twenty-two suicides to bottom out. The lower ones will be more difficult, because blood loss or even major shock won’t kill you. Find something extremely heavy and squish your head, that should work. If you need help, we have volunteers who will be dropped in and assist, but that brings more people in, and there’s a risk that this doesn’t work. The spirit blade will stop being effective at a certain distance down, and it won’t be equally ineffective for every hell, because regeneration and resilience rules are different.” She was speaking quickly and precisely. I wondered what was going on topside, but it wasn’t mission-critical, so I kept my mouth shut.

“Why the time pressure?” asked Fenn.

“The short version is that it took us time to find Juniper,” said Amaryllis, grimacing. “Once we did, we scanned the area and found that word had somehow already gotten out, not just within the hell, but through all the hells, to a level that we couldn’t contain. They didn’t know much, but virtually our only method of interacting with the hells is killing infernals, and doing that puts us at risk. The infernals have had three years to put their systems in place, and they’ve gotten better at using methods that can survive our attacks. We’ve been in a state of cold war for most of this time, but they’re essentially at unification, and we don’t have the killing power to stop them if they mount an attack on Aerb. Keep security protocols in place, not that you need to be told. Infernoscopes might be pointed at us from higher hells at any moment.”

“How do they know about me though?” I asked. “I met one guy and one devil, and I beat the crap out of the devil. We should have had more time.”

“It was the person you met, we think,” said Amaryllis. “He ran off to report you. By the time we’d found you, you were already in the system.”

“Then why put me in?” asked Fenn.

“We thought the other extraction method would work,” said Amaryllis. “We thought we would be able to grab both of you without having to get the Omega Hell involved. I’m sorry, Fenn, I know you never wanted to go to the hells, but I’m not actually that sorry, because we’re very likely to be the first people to come back to life after dying.”

“You’re dead?” asked Fenn.

“How do you think I got here?” asked Amaryllis. “I killed myself and then had my soul injected. We have volunteers to do the same in any of the other hells, if we have trouble. They understand the importance of the mission. If possible, we’ll take them with us, but they signed up for a temporary eternity in whatever hell they go to, just to help us.” She summoned her spirit blade. “Do you two understand? Which hell you end up in is random, but the geography will be mostly the same. The suicides will separate us, but we’ll be able to meet back up in the Omega Hell, or if separated, meet at the Fortress of the Gilded Behir. Grak will be injected there to help Fenn.”

“Kill myself twenty or so times,” I nodded. “Got it. I just hope this isn’t fire magic all over again.”

“I’ve got a bad feeling about this,” said Fenn, grimacing at the blade in Amaryllis’ hand. “I picked a bad time to stop sniffing glue.”

“Wait. There’s a devil I made a deal with,” I began.

“Already dead,” said Amaryllis. “As is every other infernal in this compound who has any knowledge of you. There might be others who know though, if the interrogation was monitored by infernoscope.”

“Oh,” I said. I really had intended to honor that deal.

“Are you ready?” asked Amaryllis.

“Yes,” I said.

Amaryllis stepped towards me, and it took every ounce of my willpower not to move out of the way as she swung the blade at my neck.

The hells weren’t quite mix-and-match, since each was a coherent whole, but it was hard to see that from a distance, and if I’d been a DM tasked with designing nine thousand hells, I would have just whipped up some kind of random generator that pulled from long lists of plants, animals, and geographic features, then paired them with things that were gross or dangerous. A sea of mucus, a river of acid, a bunny crusted with scabs, grass that was sharp enough to effortlessly cut flesh … simple enough, if you didn’t want to create a new ecosystem from whole cloth. Maybe I was a simpleton, but the results seemed roughly the same as if it had been done that way, rather than having more work put into it.

In the second hell, I dropped into the midst of a small town surrounded by red moss with tongue-like things coming up from it. There were no more than twenty or so buildings, all made of a dull green brick. I got to my feet at once, and even as I did, I saw demons and devils around me getting burnt out and falling to the ground as though they’d had their strings cut. I summoned my spirit blade and tried to figure out the best way of killing myself. Eventually I settled on cutting my throat and wrists, and if I thought that standing still for Amaryllis to cut off my head took some nerves, that was nothing compared to running a sharp sword across my throat, then doing the same to my wrists as great quantities of blood were pouring out of my neck and down my naked body.

If this didn’t kill me, it was going to severely wound me, enough that I would need time to heal in order to figure out a different solution. I was only at one of a projected twenty-two ‘jumps’ until I bottomed out.

Thankfully, I lost consciousness pretty quickly, and the next thing I knew, I was falling down into a blue hell, with water surrounding a small island farm.

I had time to think about how fucked up it was. It wasn’t just fucked up in the usual sense, killing myself and descending through the hells, it was fucked up because I’d tried to commit suicide back on Earth, I had survived that experience, been marked by it, and grown, at least a little bit. I had a relationship with suicide, and suicidal thoughts. Now here I was, trying to commit suicide over and over, because it was the only way for me to live. If things had been a little less fucked, or if I had been watching it from a distance, maybe I would have appreciated the reversal, or taken some pleasure in the irony, but I was mostly trying to get through it as quickly as I could.

(If I was being charitable, and I definitely wasn’t in the mood for that, then the message was that you had to get through some heinous shit sometimes, and that was a part of life, of getting to the good stuff, but it wasn’t a message that resonated with me. It was a message I’d heard a lot, but that had never landed for me when I was in the depths of suicidal depression. Being told that you have to wade through shit while you’re wading through shit isn’t actually helpful, and I didn’t know why people thought it was.)

I drowned myself in what passed for the sea around the island, carrying a heavy rock with me until I was deep enough, then setting it on top of myself and taking in giant gulps of water. The blue sands shredded the skin of my feet, so I was inhaling some of my own blood as well, and by both smell and feel, the water wasn’t proper water at all. I managed to get the rock off me in my panic, and though I started vomiting ‘water’ back up, I still managed to choke enough that I lost the strength to get myself out of the water again. I’d hoped that it would be better than bleeding out, and it really wasn’t.

The problem with the hells, from the perspective of someone doing their best to die down to the bottom, was that nothing really wanted to kill me. The various ecosystems of the hells were arranged around human suffering in one way or another, or at least human bodies, and actually killing a mortal meant that they would leave the hell forever. Given how comparatively rare mortals were, anything that killed one was almost certainly maladaptive.

In the fifth hell I landed in, I was almost immediately set upon by a pack of scaly chickens with red skin and sparse feathers, their beady black eyes bulging from their heads and their pecks razor sharp. They stripped flesh from me, ripping out chucks, and I screamed at them, which did nothing to deter them. I summoned the spirit blade and cut at them, injuring a few, but not enough, and a sword wasn’t the kind of weapon you wanted for killing small things that were low to the ground. After I’d bled out enough to get weak and fall down, the chicken-things slowed their attack, not wanting to kill me, whether that was through instinct or a conscious choice on their part. I was worried that I wasn’t going to be able to stand, but after three attempts I lunged to my feet and looked around. The chicken-things were still there, backing away from me so they wouldn’t get hurt, but staying close enough that they could nip at me, ripping away more flesh as they did. I had dropped my spirit blade, and was feeling weak, which gave me trouble summoning it again. I stumbled forward, blood streaming down from all over me, until I got to a building that was close by. There were three infernal corpses in there, clustered around an elf that was strung up in some kind of horrible device that was holding him still. He was screaming and crying, and I briefly thought about trying to save him, but I had lost a lot of blood, and the chicken-things had followed me in. There were torture implements on the table, and I grabbed the sharpest looking on, then stabbed myself in the throat as many times as I could before losing strength and falling down.

In the ninth hell I landed in, there was nothing and nobody around. It was a vast expanse of rock, looking like it had been worn away into interesting shapes by strong winds, but without any evidence of those winds. I summoned the spirit blade and cut at my wrists, but they didn’t bleed. Whatever the rules of this hell were, they didn’t allow blood to flow from a body. I didn’t know what I was going to do, because there was no water to drown myself in and nothing that it seemed like I could drop on myself to crush my head. Eventually I set my eyes on a cliff and started climbing towards it. I was halfway down the hells though, or should have been somewhere close to that, and while it was hot enough that I was dripping with sweat and the rocks were rough enough to scrape skin, I could tell that the regeneration factor had really been ramped up. I wasn’t sure that a fall from a hundred feet up would actually kill me. I set it to myself to try anyway, and began climbing the cliff face. It was hard going with no shoes on, and I scraped myself up on the rocks, but a minor scrape would evaporate away in a minute or so. Getting to the top of the cliff took me twenty minutes, and at the end of it I took a brief look at the view of this wide, windswept, and seemingly empty place, then looked down at the rocks below, trying to figure out the best place to land in order to ensure my death. I steeled myself then ran forward, jumping to get myself as much height and distance as possible, then transitioning into a swan dive with my head pointed straight at the sharpest rocks I’d seen. I didn’t think it was perfect, but the death was almost instant.

In the thirteenth hell I went through, the regeneration factor worked differently, which I learned when I tried to push the spirit blade through my neck. Instead of piercing though, it painfully pushed into the skin, which stretched to accommodate it. A quick test after that showed that I wasn’t able to pierce my skin at all, though it was still plenty painful to try. It was the kind of thing that I’d have seen as a boon, if it weren’t stopping me from completing the mission, and if it weren’t a part of how this particular hell allowed people to be indefinitely tortured. Of course the regeneration and resilience worked differently in each of the hells, but this was an extreme case, and I wished that we’d had time to go through a plan for the different scenarios. Eventually, after a half hour of walking, I found a small town where Valencia had already killed the infernals, and after a brief conversation with a mortal who spoke Anglish for once, I was able to convince her to kill me, which was done via something approximating a blast furnace.

In the seventeenth hell, something must have misfired, because the infernals I almost immediately found myself around didn’t drop dead as soon as I looked at them. Valencia was shepherding the three of us down, assisted by an array of infernoscopes and a team of people, and I waited on them to find me as the hungry infernals turned toward me, feeling my fear and pain. They began trying to grab me and take me, each of them fighting for itself, hoping to get this prize that had fallen directly into their lap. They tore me apart, ripping off my arms, then tearing me apart at my waist, before finally there was only my head left, being carried like a football by a powerful demon. I could still feel every part of me, all of which was still being scrambled over, and I could still see, still think, even torn completely apart. Another demon clashed with the demon carrying me, and my head went tumbling to the ground, where it was crushed and trampled on until even the absurd resilience granted by the hell failed.

I took a break in the eighteenth hell, or at least as much of a break as I could take. I didn’t know how far down I was, but I hoped I was getting close. Valencia could kill the demons and devils, but there were other threats lurking in the hells, things that would make the place still proper hells even if we ever managed to kill all the infernals. I was able to just sit there for a moment, contemplating, trying to get up the will to go on, because if I stopped pushing on, I was never going to escape. I was hoping that Valencia could see me this time, and that she knew I was going to be fine, because I didn’t want someone to get dropped into the hell to help me. Eventually, I got to my feet and walked for a bit, trying to find something that I could use. I was deep enough that I doubted I could properly choke myself to death, and I didn’t want to try using the spirit blade again, not when it had been consistently failing me. I had a walk of at least a mile before I found any kind of settlement, and when I did, all the infernals were dead. It wasn’t too long after that before I rigged up a table to fall and crush my head, which thankfully worked.

At the twenty-second hell I went down into, I was hopeful that I was in the Omega Hell, but I knew enough about the hells to know that I wasn’t quite there. I was hoping, praying that this wasn’t going to be some bullshit like the fire magic trial, but after my conversation with the Dungeon Master, I was more willing to give him the benefit of the doubt. He’d revealed something to me, something about himself, and it had connected with me. While it was possible that he’d bowed out, this all still smelled like his style.

Maybe that’s what the story of Job was about. But Job liked his god, and I didn’t particularly like mine, even if we were kindred spirits.

If you ever get stuck in the hells, The Commoner’s Guide to Being Stuck in the Hells (which bears only a satirical relationship to the series of beginner books) recommends that you do your best to stay where you are, get captured by an infernal, and be a ‘kept’ mortal. What you didn’t want was to be a single mortal held by multiple infernals who would trade you around, milking you for every last ounce of suffering that you were worth. The best place to become a kept mortal is the Omega Hell, because it’s the only place in the hells where there’s a large supply of souls, and infernals powerful enough to keep them. ‘Kept’ mortals were ones that lived relatively decent lives and were allowed to slowly build up hope and lose their calluses, which made the torture all the sweeter. Therefore, in the dark humor that served as the whole point of The Commoner’s Guide to Being Stuck in the Hells, it was suggested that your best bet was to kill yourself, over and over, until you landed in the Omega Hell, were picked up by an infernal there, and then only subject to torture when you weren’t being pampered in preparation for torture. Or maybe you would end up as one of the famed nerve mats, stretched out so that every inch of your nervous system could be individually tortured.

They offered some advice, as well, in their style of dry humor, which was mostly their chance to give a long list of all the horrible ways there were to die in the hells. Still, I thought that I could probably write a serious version, one for someone in a position like my own, not that there were many. Finding civilization was a good start, as was staying as whole and intact as possible until you found a method of execution. Of course, the whole finding civilization thing probably wouldn’t have worked for anyone else, given that Valencia was eliminating infernals left and right, but for me it was handy, because the infernals had all kinds of things on hand artfully to bring a person just to the brink of death. It took some time, but eventually I escaped using one of those implements, stripping out my entire nervous system until my brain itself was being pulled apart.

And then, for what had seemed like a fairly long journey of killing myself twenty-one times in a row, it was suddenly over, and the Doom Sun of the Omega Hell was above me, instantly starting to flay my skin from my body. I ran as soon as I hit the ground until I found a scrap of shade behind a tree, which gave me a brief reprieve. My body didn’t handle the flaying well, as bodies don’t, and given extended time in the Doom Sun, I’d have been ripped to shreds, muscle torn off millimeter by millimeter, then bone, until finally my brain was gone. And then, because it was the Omega Hell, I wouldn’t even die, I would reform somewhere else a moment later. It was said some people spent their time dying over and over, unable to get to shelter with their reformed body.

The damage I’d taken was uneven, and I took a moment to assess myself with shaky hands. I was missing skin mostly on my front, with my back intact, and the skin was regenerating as I watched it. I took in a few deep breaths. As it turned out, I wasn’t a fan of dying.

There were bodies of infernals around me. They weren’t subject to the Doom Sun, nor was any of the flora, fauna, or land, but Valencia had gotten to them, apparently in advance of my arrival. Two of them were large, and would have been twenty feet tall if standing, but the third was smaller, probably a devil, and not more than eight feet tall.

I hadn’t known much about the Omega Hell, except for its famed Doom Sun, and the wealth of mortals there. Hellology, which was definitely a real word and not something that I just made up, had never been a particular passion of mine, not when Aerb had so much fun and interesting stuff that wasn’t going to leave me depressed for the remainder of the day. Given the swollen red Doom Sun, I had expected it to be warmer, but no, it was nearly freezing, meaning that even if I could stay in the shade, there was a good chance my body would slow down and die. There were a fair number of trees scattered on the plain though, with green leaves, even, not looking terribly threatening, though of course I knew better than to think that meant anything. It was one of those trees that I’d taken shelter under, though its trunk was only barely wide enough to give me protection.

In the distance was a castle, built tall, but I had no illusions that this was the place we were meant to be going, not given the facts at hand. Each of the hells was roughly as large as Aerb itself, which was ten times the surface area of Earth. Given that the geographies roughly mapped to each other, and would hold unless you were doing something weird, we were ‘below’ Fel Seed’s domain, and there was no particular reason to think that the door, portal, or whatever it was would be anywhere near there. I’d tried my best not to stray too far when I’d been repeatedly killing myself, because I wanted to be able to meet back up with the others once they finished their descent, but we were looking at a grim trip of possibly thousands of miles.

I waited. My skin healed. I wished that I knew what horrible secrets the Omega Hell held for me. I watched the shadows closely, trying to see which direction the Doom Sun was moving, and hoping that I wouldn’t have to experience high noon, when the trees would do nothing for me. Of course, once nightfall came, I would get to experience the Chaos Moon, which was arguably worse: it was like a microwave, and would cook you from the inside out if you stood in its light.

It had been about twenty minutes when a woman came falling down from the sky. I sat where I was, waiting, but she was slow to get up, and far away from a tree, so I ran out, braving the Doom Sun, and picked her up. From the red hair, I’d assumed, or maybe hoped, that it was Amaryllis, but as I picked her up and ran with her to the relative safety of the shadow, I realized that I was wrong, and it was someone else. It wasn’t until I set her down, fully in the shade, that it occurred to me who it might be.

“Lisi?” I asked.

She gave me a weak nod, then sat up. “We need to go,” she said, groaning.

“Why you?” I asked.

“Volunteered,” she said. “Prior relationship with you.” She looked at the damage she’d taken, the places where flesh had been removed. “How fucking long is it going to take for my skin to grow back?”

“Ten minutes,” I said. “I’d have thought you were watching from above.” She was naked, and I was studiously avoiding that fact, because even though we were in the hells, some part of my brain still felt the need to be embarrassed about it.

“We were,” she replied. “It was rhetorical. Once we have our skin back, we need to grab a corpse and make coverings for ourselves.”

I looked at the corpses, which were still sitting there in the sun. The little one, who wasn’t even that little, would be the only one that we had a hope of moving. “Fuck,” I said. “How are we going to do that? With what tools? And where are we going?”

“A thousand miles due east-north-east,” said Lisi, twisting her fingers but not bothering to point in the actual direction. “Don’t worry, there’s transport to steal. About making the shields, I’ve no idea, rip off their claws I guess.”

“Good to see you again,” I said. “I guess you … graduated?”

She looked at me. “Are you trying to make small talk?”

“I’m just wondering what happened while I was gone,” I said. “I was trying to be polite. To take our minds off things.”

“I got fast-tracked,” said Lisi, watching her skin slowly grow back. “A lot of people died in Li’o. It’s been three years, I’m middling at best.” She looked at me. “Do you actually enjoy this?”

“Being in the hells?” I asked. “No. Learning what happened to you … I guess? Amaryllis didn’t feel like she had the time to give me the details.”

“She didn’t,” said Lisi. “The infernals have planned for this moment. They have counterattacks prepared. Things aren’t going great on Aerb either. If we have downtime, I’ll fill you in, but right now we need to get protection, get transport, then meet up with the others.”

“They’re through?” I asked.

“Fenn is, Amaryllis is still falling, she’s had bad rolls and it looks like she’ll be off course,” said Lisi. “It’s very important that no one dies, because grabbing them from somewhere else in the Omega Hell is going to cost us time we probably don’t have.” She looked at the infernal corpse, then down at her hand, where the skin was still growing back. “What do these trees do?” she asked.

“I don’t know,” I replied. “They might just be trees. I don’t actually believe that, but it’s possible.” I paused. “Shouldn’t you have done recon of the Omega Hell before all this?”

“This was the third contingency,” said Lisi. “The other two plans should have worked, but didn’t. We got an exclusion.”

“Which?” I asked, frowning.

“Rune magic,” said Lisi.

“Fuuuuck,” I said.

“Yup,” replied Lisi. “No rune magic, no soul spikes, no way to prevent people from going to the hells, not unless they have a hundred thousand obols and a week to prepare … there are reasons time is of the essence, and that’s one of them.”

“How is me getting out of the hells supposed to help?” I asked.

“Amaryllis is going for a second attempt at Fel Seed,” said Lisi.

“Fuck,” I said. “And I’d guess I’m a key part in that.” I moved slightly, to keep myself in the shade of the tree. I was starting to feel nauseous, and my teeth were aching for some reason. I hoped that the tree wasn’t slowly killing me, or draining me, or some other horrible but mostly invisible thing. I was hoping that the Omega Hell, absent the infernals, wasn’t going to be that bad, that it would be more about the tools that the infernals had than the ambient dangers themselves.

“It would be better for you to get the corpse,” said Lisi. “You’ve got more skin to spare.”

“Okay,” I said, getting to my feet. My skin was almost entirely back, but I was understandably worried, because if the Doom Sun started eating away at my muscles, I wouldn’t be able to move. I braced myself though, and raced out toward the smallest of the infernals, gripping him by his legs and dragging him over while I screamed in pain. He was fucking heavy, and unfortunately for us, not wearing anything. I collapsed into the shade of the tree, next to Lisi, and panted hard as I endured the pain of cold air on my missing flesh. It wasn’t numbing, as cold sometimes was, it was just cold, like icicles being driven into me.

Lisi started work, using her whole body weight to get the corpse in closer. I summoned my spirit blade, but even with a heavy swing, it couldn’t even break skin. Lisi did her best to get one of the claws off, first by trying to twist or use leverage, then by using her teeth, neither of which worked. Finally, she turned the claw in and tried using it to cut the demon’s skin, but that was slow going, since apparently the demon’s defenses were better than its offenses. There was no guarantee that it would skin easily, and it was rough work. I also wasn’t looking forward to walking around under whatever skin we could get from it.

“If this doesn’t work, our other option is waiting for twilight,” said Lisi. “At this time of year, there’s maybe twenty minutes when the Doom Sun is down and the Chaos Moon has yet to rise.” She paused. “Are you feeling nauseous?”

“Yeah,” I said.

“You look it,” she replied. “Green in the gills.”

“Might be the tree,” I said, looking up at it. “Might just be this place. Might be something in the air, or … anything, really.”

“I’m feeling it too,” Lisi nodded, then went back to her work. Once she’d made the initial cut, it was easier, because the skin of the demon pulled back, separating from the under layer fairly easily. It would be big, but I didn’t think it would be big enough to cover her, let alone me. There would also be the issue of getting it to cover us completely, because if our destination was the nearby castle, we were going to have to go for quite a ways under the glare of the Doom Sun.

“Try biting the intestines,” said Lisi. “Or use a claw to cut them. We can use them as gloves to keep our hands safe.”

“How is Fenn doing?” I asked as I tried to get to the demon’s guts. It was horrible, frankly, and I was skeptical that any of it would work. While I was trying to use a claw to cut the guts open, my elbow went out of the shade and I pulled it back immediately, cursing.

“Fenn is fine,” said Lisi. “She rolled well, got to Omega quickly, and found shelter right away. Grakhuil is with her, and they’re making their way to the meeting point.”

“Grak came down too?” I asked. “Fuck.”

“We’re putting all our eggs in one basket,” said Lisi. “I agree with it, or I wouldn’t be here, but if this all falls through, we, and Aerb, are completely fucked.”

“Who else is on the team?” I asked.

“Everyone,” she replied. She seemed content to talk so long as we were both working. She was still going on the skin, and I was trying to figure out how the fuck to make gloves and boots out of demon intestines without any tools. “Beth, Val, Pallida, Figaro, and Doris are staying up top, all for obvious reasons. A few of the tuung loyalists volunteered for descent, if it was needed, and the infernoscopes are being monitored. Amaryllis has chosen to go alone once she arrives in Omega, with Raven as her backup in case things go wrong.”

She finished getting the skin off, and I vomited off the side, dry heaving, because I was pretty sure that this body had never eaten anything, and was ‘new’ in the sense that it had been created not long ago.

“I think it’s the tree,” I said. “Usually my stomach is a little better about gross stuff.” I had been on Aerb, anyway, if not necessarily on Earth. Having a strong constitution was tied to Endurance, and it really did seem like though the game layer was gone, I’d still kept all the other enhancements that had come with leveling up.

“The nausea has hit me too,” said Lisi. “We’re going to need to get moving. I don’t think we can wait until twilight to make a run.” She finished a crude cut and pulled the skin around her. “How does it look?” she asked.

“A bold fashion choice,” I said, smiling weakly. I felt like throwing up again, and I was getting more and more convinced that the tree was doing something to my intestines.

“Do I look protected?” she asked, glaring at me.

“Yeah,” I said, looking her over. “Covers more than I thought it would. I’m not even sure you’ll need the gloves.”

“I will,” she replied, looking at my work with a frown. “Do you think if I make the run, you’ll be able to survive here alone? The tree might be making you sick, or harvesting us in some way, but it’s unlikely to kill you. You just need to stay well enough to move with the Doom Sun.”

“Right,” I said, then threw up again. “And you’re getting what, a car?”

“Something like that,” she said. “Here, give me those.”

I handed over what I had ‘made’, the intestine that had been cut with the demon’s own claws. Without hesitation, she slipped the pieces over her feet and hands. It was slippery, but she was still able to hold onto the skin around her.

“If I don’t make it,” she said. “You’re fucked. But if you die, or I die, they’ll send someone for us, probably tuung, but possibly someone else, depending on circumstances. We have the respawn pattern mapped. You’re going to the Fortress of the Gilded Behir. Conveyance is on the roof of that castle,” she said, gesturing at her destination.

I nodded, and desperately hoped that I didn’t have to go it alone. Lisi had never really been much of a friend, but I’d killed myself twenty-one times going down through the hells, and aside from meeting some lost souls, I’d been alone for it.

I watched her go, occasionally stopping to vomit. I wondered what the point of these trees was, whether they got something from the vomit. They had leaves, did they have something like chlorophyll which fed on sickness instead of light? Aside from the three dead infernals, and the castle in the distance, there wasn’t much around, just the trees, without anything obvious to sustain them aside from the Doom Sun and the Chaos Moon. It was entirely possible that they were nocturnal, and once night came, they would turn into something more horrible. I was praying that I didn’t get a chance to figure out what.

Lisi trudged on, moving low and slow, with her devil skin wrapped around her, protecting her from the Doom Sun. The castle wasn’t even that far away, almost close enough that I thought I could make the run while under the effects of the Doom Sun as it stripped my skin and later flesh and bone, but with how sick and cold I was feeling, I was probably overestimating myself. I shivered somewhat, then threw up again, losing my balance for a moment and momentarily slipping a hand out of the shade. I yanked it back with just the top few layers of skin removed.

Lisi got to the castle and with some effort, opened the large front door, slipping inside and out of view. The road, if you could call it that, was crude, but the castle itself was well-made, with large bricks of regular size that bespoke a developed civilization. From what I knew of the Omega Hell, it was the place where the richest and most powerful of the infernals were, and they had been adopting human inventions and advancements in the wake of Uther’s technological crusades on Aerb. Lisi had said that they had conveyance, and I was wondering what the horrible twist was, because there had to be a horrible twist.

An hour passed, and then a second. Lisi and I hadn’t discussed how long I should wait before assuming that she wouldn’t return, but I was throwing up every five minutes or so like clockwork, and the cold was really starting to get to me. By my best guess, it would be twilight in another half hour, but with where the Doom Sun was positioned, it would be behind the castle, affording me extra time where I could walk and still be in shade. I was feeling quite ill, but the illness, like the cold, seemed to have peaked at a certain level of horribleness that still allowed me to move and have the occasional scattered thought.

As soon as the Doom Sun was behind the castle, I set off, crawling at first, then staggering to my feet and stumbling forward. The sickness started to fade as soon as I was beyond the trees, but the last little bit of it stayed with me. With the Doom Sun down, the cold was getting worse, and I was still completely naked. I also hadn’t eaten at all, nor drank anything, not that there were things to eat or drink. I was feeling weak and helpless, and it did occur to me that if Lisi had run into trouble, I was probably going to run into the same trouble. The infernals would all be dead, Valencia would have seen to that, but there were plenty of other things that could be in a compound like this. There were things you’d put in a compound like this, if you wanted to defend it against people who could kill you from a distance, either out of deterrence or spite.

I was feeling less sick once I made it into the compound, but then I had no idea where I was going. The infernals in this hell were taller, some of them twice as tall as a person, or more, and the hallways and rooms were built to accommodate. There didn’t seem to be anyone there, or at least, there were no sounds. I was moving slowly, and feeling … not better, actually, but less bad. I continued to pad my way down the large corridors, trying to find some sign of Lisi. When I saw the trail of blood, my heart dropped, and I started running, knowing that whatever had happened, it had likely happened hours ago.

I found her in a compound, torn apart into several pieces, with no sign of what had done it. She’d been completely decapitated, and some kind of creature had mauled her head, gouging out her eyes and tearing the flesh from her face until only a nose hole and bright white teeth remained. Her body was elsewhere, spread out in a pool of her blood, with her limbs separated. One of them looked like it had been thrown against a wall hard enough to shatter the brick there. I was on my guard, trying to listen as best I could with my stupid non-enhanced senses, so I just about shit myself when I heard a wet smacking sound.

It was Lisi. Her mouth was moving, not capable of making sounds.

It took me a bit to realize that she was still alive. Once I did, and having no better options, I gathered up the pieces of her and placed them back together in approximately the right spots. I had been decapitated in one of the hells, and lived through it for at least a little bit, but with so much damage — I’d known the Omega Hell was bad, and that you could survive an incredible amount of punishment, all of which you’d feel at full force. When I’d looked at what had happened to her, it hadn’t immediately occurred to me that she could still be living.

It was slow going, watching her regenerate. I moved her, partway through, into what was probably a small closet, then I closed up the door and pushed whatever I could in front of it. I was worried that it wouldn’t work, but the various bits of her began to reconnect, with veins and tendons wriggling out of her and flopping back and forth like a worm coming out of the ground after a big rain.

It was twenty minutes before she could speak again, though she had some false starts of wet gurgling before that.

“They evacuated, or tried to,” she said. “Probably got killed. Left behind that thing. It played with me, then left, flew up and away.” She coughed up a gob of clotted blood and wiped her mouth with the back of her hand. “Fuck.”

“We should go then,” I said. “If the ride is still here.”

Lisi nodded and ran her fingers through what was left of her hair. She was shaking, badly. “Fuck. Give me a minute.”

“Take your time,” I said.

“No,” she replied. “We don’t want to be the holdup.” She held her hand out in front of her, willing it to stop, but it kept shaking, and she clenched her hand into a fist. “I,” she said. “I’ve been watching the hells. Looking at them, learning about them. Preparing. We didn’t think that we’d have to go with the Omega plan, but here we are. I knew it would be brutal.” She held out her hand again, and it was still shaking, and this time she glared at it, like it was a traitor. Most of her nose had grown back. “It’s hard to die in this hell, but it’s easy to stop moving. I was out of the fight right away. I wasn’t doing much thinking, just a blinding wall of pain. On Aerb, you’d pass out, or go insane, but here, you get kept intact enough that they can go on almost indefinitely. Maybe there was a moment when I hoped I’d be thrown into the glare of the Doom Sun, so that I could die.”

“Yeah,” I said, frowning.

“There are people who live here, Juniper,” said Lisi. “Even before the rune magic exclusion, which is now — I don’t know, two days old? But now that it’s happened, now that we made it happen by trying some things that weren’t meant to be tried, there are three people dying every second, and they’re coming here, or places that aren’t all that much better."

“Yeah,” I said, letting out a soft sigh.

“I don’t want to sit around because my stupid fucking hands won’t stop shaking,” she said. She held her hand out again, and this time, by sheer force of will, she was able to keep it steady. “Come on. Let’s go. Let’s figure out a way to save this miserable world.”

I helped her to her feet, and followed her as she made her way through the castle. She seemed to know where she was going, and I had to wonder how long she had been in here, looking around, before that thing had struck. I was hoping that it was gone, and I asked questions, which she answered in clipped tones. It had been as large as a horse, with huge claws and long, leathery wings, blisteringly fast except when it took off into the sky. I might have scared it, she thought, or maybe it had just decided that it’d had its fill. It was something of a pet to the infernals, or a guard dog, but not one that was willing to stick around if they might come back.

“Here,” said Lisi, pushing open one of the large doors after we’d gone up two flights of stairs.

Sitting on a large landing was a sophisticated contraption with clean lines and four blades on top.

It was a motherfucking helicopter.

Heck if I Know

“Make the pun,” said Lisi.

“The what?” I asked.

“The pun,” said Lisi, looking at me with distaste.

“Oh,” I said. “It’s a hell-a-copter.”

It was only kind of a helicopter, but the basics of its flight were more or less right. The helicopter my dad had used to teach me the basics had been an R22, and it would suffice to say that the hellacopter had somewhat different controls, with everything written in a language I didn’t read. The seat was too large for me, but it was adjustable, because infernals came in all shapes and sizes. When I looked closely at the parts, including the helicopter blades, I could see that they were nothing at all like Earth (or Aerb, for that matter), sometimes including bits and pieces that looked organic. The function seemed right though, and as I tested various aspects of it, sticking my head out and talking to Lisi, I identified which flaps were moving, marking each of the levers. Eventually, our time for experimentation was up, and we had to get moving, because the Chaos Moon was rising.

“You’re sure this glass is safe?” I asked, briefly touching the glass of the cockpit. “The moonlight won’t get through?”

“I’m sure,” replied Lisi. “They use this for transporting people.” She gestured to the open area in the back. “It would be useless for that if their precious mortals cooked from the inside out.”

“Okay,” I said.

“We should get going,” she said. “We have a mission.”

“I know,” I said. I turned the power on and heard an engine behind me roar to life. I wondered how much of the similarities were convergence and how many were the machinations of the Dungeon Master, but it didn’t really bear thinking about.

With a lever pressed down, the engine engaged the rotor, and I slowly pushed the throttle up until the blades above us were spinning. Once they were going fast enough, the helicopter began to lift off the ground, and I held the control stick in a death grip, trying my best not to fuck things up. I still almost crashed it before we got anywhere at all, but after landing back down and testing a few things, I figured out the problem, which was that the collective pitch control wasn’t linked to the throttle. It was annoying, and made flying way more of a pain in the ass than it needed to be, but I got it under control, got us back in the air, fumbled a bit with the anti-torque, and finally had us flying straight. Lisi knew the lay of the land from infernoscopes and looking at maps, and directed me.

Once we were flying in a straight line and constant altitude toward our destination, there was finally some time to marginally relax.

“What’s everyone else doing?” I asked.

“Same thing,” Lisi replied.

“Flying helicopters?” I asked.

“Yes,” she replied.

“I guess everyone took lessons then?” I asked.

“They did,” she answered. “You need to go faster.”

I increased the pitch while increasing the throttle, though it seemed to me that we were already going plenty fast. The ground was whipping by below us, and —

“I’m worried we’re going to hit bad weather,” I said. “I think I can keep us going the right direction, but fuck if I know where the fuel gauge even is, let alone how to refuel this thing.”

“It doesn’t take fuel,” said Lisi. “It’s powered by human suffering. There are four mortals trapped within the engine, and their nerve endings are stimulated to alter the amount of suffering generated, which is what you’re doing when you control the throttle.”

My hand instinctively went to the throttle, but I kept myself from throttling down and crashing us.

“It’s horrible,” said Lisi. “But it’s how things work in the Omega Hell. The Doom Sun and Chaos Moon kill, but they’re practically the only things. There’s a surplus of souls, which is what allows something like this to be built. Oh, and contrary to what you were saying before, there’s no weather, no clouds, just clear skies, which makes it ideal for this form of transportation.”

“Okay,” I said. I swallowed and looked at the throttle. I was going to have to touch it at some point, but knowing that it was literally hurting people to get me where I needed to go …

“Amaryllis still believes in you,” said Lisi. “She still thinks you’re the Chosen One.”

“And you don’t?” I asked.

“She claims you’ve had divine revelations,” said Lisi. “She talks about a prophecy that only you were privy to. The evidence is thin.”

“You came down here on thin evidence?” I asked.

“I did,” Lisi nodded. “The rewards are too great if she’s right. Besides, this mission should still work even if you’re just a normal man. I’ll return, and we’ll still get you back. Maybe that will be enough.”

“Sure,” I said. I tried to focus on the flight. It was bright beneath the Chaos Moon, almost bright enough that I could have been fooled into thinking that it was a second sun. There were no stars though, despite the clarity of the sky, which gave an eerie effect, like there was an eyeball looking down on us. It was made worse by knowing that if I were out in direct moonlight, I would end up burning from the inside.

“You haven’t asked about Reimer,” said Lisi.

“Reimer?” I asked. “Are you two still … together?”

“We are,” she nodded.

“And?” I asked. “How is he?”

“Good,” said Lisi. “Worried. Angry with me for doing this. The original plan didn’t require it, but this contingency did. We had a fight about it.”

“Sorry,” I said. “It … seems like a lot to go through for me.”

“It is,” nodded Lisi. “The world is dying.”

“Still slowly?” I asked. “Death of a thousand cuts?”

“Faster, these past three years,” said Lisi. She was looking out onto the moonlit hell, which was surprisingly normal, at least from high up. “The Void Beast can’t be stopped.”

“We’ll find a way,” I said, though I wasn’t sure if I believed it.

“The elemental plane of gold is gone,” said Lisi.

“That … is way ahead of schedule,” I said. “We shouldn’t have been at that point for decades, maybe more. The DFEZ was brought under control, wasn’t it?”

“They’re major allies,” said Lisi. “And yes, by some estimates they accounted for more than twenty percent of the void use on Aerb. They stopped virtually overnight. There was a major explosion at a processing plant for void crystals, a place that was subject to sane regulations due to their continued industrial use. It’s hard to tell how much damage that did, but we’re guessing a lot, given what we can tell of the Void Beast’s trajectory. There are stricter imperial bans now, but it’s too little, too late.”

“This mission is one of desperation,” I said. “A last chance to stop a world that’s winding down.”

“Infernal unification is a given,” said Lisi. “And they’re going to know who we are. Everyone at all connected with the mission will be under extraordinary danger. It’s another thing I fought with Reimer about. He was a part of it too though.”

“Our weapon’s not strong enough to kill them all?” I asked.

“No,” replied Lisi. “It’s close though. It might be able to kill their leaders fast enough that they can’t organize, but the infernals have known about it, at least in the abstract, and they’ve been planning for it.”

I nodded. She was painting a particularly grim picture, and I couldn’t help but notice that a lot of this was because of me. The rune magic exclusion seemed to have happened because of a risk they’d taken, and everything that the hells were going to throw at us was because Valencia needed to cut loose in order to make the mission work.

We flew in silence. I almost felt like Lisi wanted me to ask her more about Reimer, or their fight, or other personal things, but I didn’t know Lisi all that well, especially not after three years or so had passed. The Lisi I knew would have been direct with me, but maybe Reimer had slightly softened her edges, if they were still together after all this time.

The flight took ten hours, and by the end of it I was feeling incredibly claustrophobic, thirsty, hungry, and dirty.

By the time we got to the Fortress of the Gilded Behir, the Chaos Moon was setting and the Doom Sun was rising once more. Landing was an ordeal, and a part of me wanted to just jump out and smash into the ground, where I would naturally regenerate, but I did my best to land the helicopter, which was done with a lot of damage to the skids and a cracking sound that made me think it was probably not a great idea for us to take off again.

We covered ourselves as completely as we could, then got out and went through a rooftop door.

Fenn and Grak were waiting for us inside.

“Fenn,” I said. “You made it.” They were dressed in the same kinds of cloaks we were, shapeless things that hung loosely on the body and offered only basic protection. Grak’s was tied up so that it didn’t drag on the ground.

She nodded, then looked at Lisi. “Discount Amaryllis?” she asked.

“She’s dating Reimer,” I said.

“Wait, Reimer is on Aerb?” asked Fenn.

“Oh,” I said. “Yeah, forgot to mention that. There are expys of everyone.”

“Tiff?” asked Fenn, raising an eyebrow.

“I’m married to Reimer, actually,” said Lisi. “All that can wait. We need to make plans. Have you located the artifact?”

“We just arrived,” said Grak. “We saw your helicopter coming in and came to meet you.”

“How are you doing?” I asked him, using Groglir. I wanted — hoped — that would encourage him to be more forthcoming.

“Fine,” he replied, also in Groglir.

“I’m sorry for the trouble,” I said. “I know that dying is probably complicated for you.”

“Is there a reason that I’m not supposed to hear this?” asked Fenn. I held up a hand and hoped that she would understand that it was a polite request.

He watched me for a moment. “I did not enjoy watching you kill yourself,” he finally said. “It brought up uncomfortable feelings.”

“I know,” I said. “For me too. It wasn’t the same intended outcome, but it was attached to the same feelings.”

He nodded.

“Sorry I was gone,” I said. “Sorry that it didn’t work out. That I couldn’t be there for you.”

“We need to get moving,” said Lisi, apparently losing her patience for this. “Find the artifact, prepare for the arrival of Amaryllis, then get it done. You can talk when we’re back and dilated.”

“She’s right,” said Grak. “Follow me. We have already done the scouting.” He set off down the hallways of this huge place, moving swiftly. “We’re not that far away. Everyone here should be dead, and we have inside information.” He gave me a look. “So far as we’ve been able to determine, before today, all they knew is that someone was killing them at random intervals and in random locations. That’s changed. They were alerted by what happened in locations that correspond to Fel Seed’s zone.”

“My arrival?” I asked.

“The arrival of many,” said Grak. He glanced at Lisi, then turned back to focus on where he was walking. “When you were lost in Fel Seed’s domain, we searched the hells for you but could not find you. Eventually, we determined that it was probable that you were either alive or bottled. The bomb took care of both possibilities.”

“How big a bomb?” I asked.

“There’s a smoking crater where the City of a Thousand Brides used to be,” said Lisi.

“So we sent thousands of people to the hells?” I asked. “More?”

“Well, we didn’t do that, because you’ve been gone for three years,” said Lisi. “But yes. It made it hard to find you. By the time we did, information was already flowing and nearly impossible to stop. Allowing the interrogation was a calculated risk so that we could find out how much they knew.”

“Antimatter rune bomb?” I asked.

“Yes,” said Lisi.

“And you weren’t worried about the door?” I asked. “That you would permanently sever the connection to the Long Stairs?”

“We tried to get through that door,” said Grak. “I was not worried about its integrity.”

“We were more worried about exclusion,” said Lisi. “Which is what happened.”

“Rune magic is fucked?” asked Fenn. “Isn’t that kind of bad?”

“It’s a disaster,” said Grak. “The connection to the Long Stairs still exists. Doris could still get a faint trace of Uther.” He came to a stop. “We’re here.”

We’d reached a large metal door, one with heavy locks and obvious magic on it, the kind I generally hated, with purple runes all over the place and lines hovering away from the surface.

“Can you break through this?” I asked.

“I know the password,” said Grak. “Ning ye mupshung ndi nde shnaw fe fukseng.” He said the lines carefully and deliberately, and I wondered how long he’d practiced them.

“These bastards don’t use two factor, huh?” I asked, as the lines retracted and the runes spun around.

“Information security in the hells is lacking,” said Grak.

“What the fuck,” said Fenn as the doors opened up, and I was a little puzzled by that, because really, who would be surprised by seeing a hundred foot tall portal made out of thousands of bodies wired together?

“Let me guess,” I said. “It runs on human suffering?”

“No,” said Lisi. “From what we know, it runs on cognition. They could have used infernals, but humans were easier, and more pleasurable to work with. The origins of it are complicated though.” She stepped into the large room and moved over to a console, which had a number of dials and levers on it. To get to the actual portal required ascending a full flight of stairs, one which had been built in the oversized way that the rest of the place had.

“Please tell me we don’t need someone to stay down here and control this thing,” I said.

“It has two ends,” said Lisi. “If it’s working on this end, then it should fire when the other end connects.”

“And we control the other end, I hope?” I asked. “There’s not some ongoing operation there that I should be aware of?”

“No,” said Lisi. “It’s in the DFEZ.”

“And we control some part of the DFEZ?” asked Fenn.

“The whole thing,” said Grak. “There are no holdouts.”

“Blood God Doris?” I asked. “It’s … not a shitshow?”

“Utopia would be overstating it,” said Grak. “But it is pleasant and clean.”

“Huh,” I said.

“Who or what is Blood God Doris?” asked Fenn. “She sounds like either someone I really want to meet, or really never want to meet.”

“Long story,” I said. “And I apparently don’t know the ending to it.”

“Good to go,” said Lisi, who had been doing something with the controls. “Someone go stand in the center of the ring and we can test it. They should be monitoring us.” She gave a brief wave to an imagined person above us.

“I suppose you made some advancement in infernoscopes while I was gone?” I asked.

“No,” said Lisi. “You just didn’t know everything.”

“Star magic augmentation,” said Grak. “It was classified.”

I looked over to Fenn, wondering how she was handling this, and saw that she’d already taken off toward the stairs. “Fenn?” I asked.

“Getting the fuck out of here while I can,” she said. “See you on the other side, I’ve got shit to catch up on.”

“Better to have someone to test this before us,” Lisi said under her breath, quiet enough that Fenn didn’t hear. She looked over at me. “Ten minutes between resets.”

“I don’t understand why they did this,” I said, looking at the portal. “I don’t understand how, but I accept it, but the why … does it work on infernals?”

“No,” replied Grak. “It fails. Only mortals.”

“But in theory, now that we’re here, we can resurrect more people,” I said. “I mean, we can inject people to the Omega Hell, to this specific room, probably, and then shuttle them through? Anyone we have the soul of, that is.”

Grak shifted uncomfortably.

“What?” I asked. “There’s something that you haven’t told me.”

“Two things. First, the other end is simple,” said Grak. “It could be constructed anywhere. The problem is that it requires deaths.”

“Deaths?” I asked. “You fuel it through … killing people? People are going to have to die to bring us back?”

“Yes,” said Grak.

“Dorises,” said Lisi. “Fetuses as well, meaning that newborn souls are being sent to the hells, but only ten of them.”

“Ten?” I asked. “Sending us up condemns ten people to hell?”

“Ideally they’d have been spiked,” said Lisi. “The rune magic exclusion is unfortunate.” She was watching Fenn climb the stairs.

“Fuck,” I said. I looked at Grak. “I don’t —”

“We went through with this because we thought that it was in the balance of good,” said Grak. He had a grim look on his face. “It is not just for you, but for the future of Aerb.”

“How?” I asked. “Because we’re going after Fel Seed again, in the hope of getting Uther from the Long Stairs, and … what, the promised godhood? Grak, I was killed, Fel Seed cheated, and I don’t think that there was anything I could have done about it.”

“Amaryllis agrees,” Grak replied. “She thinks that the second time will work.”

“On what basis?” I asked.

“On the basis that if you had been given a second chance, you would have let the players win,” said Grak.

“And you believe that?” I asked.

“Options are thin,” said Grak. “Our choice is between laying down to accept our fate and giving it everything we have.”

I stopped myself from saying more and thought about that for a moment. I hadn’t expected to die, and hadn’t expected a timeskip either. I’d thought that if there were some kind of rescue, it would happen after months in the hells. I tried to think back on what the Dungeon Master said to me, and whether or not there was a chance that was right. He’d said that he hated me. He’d said that Fel Seed’s weakness was that there was an entity above him.

“We have to do the thirty-two miles again,” I said, groaning.

“No,” said Grak. “It’s part of our worldlines. We can teleport there. I can bypass my own strongest wards with wardproof. The definitions are permissive enough. If Fel Seed can do better, it is a sign we should not go.”

I let out a sigh. I was going to ask about downtime, but with rune magic excluded and mortals freely falling into the hells with no real way to stop it, the situation was dire. Infernal unification was a given, after this focused attack against the hells, and while we could fight back, it wasn’t clear to me that it was something we’d want to invest in for the long term.

“What was the second thing?” I asked. “About the portal?”

“It’s schloss,” said Grak, giving a glance at Lisi, who seemed not to hear him. “Amaryllis went to the Outer Reaches.”

“Shit,” I said. “And she … came up with this?”

“Apparently,” replied Grak.

“I need to talk to her,” I said. “All this, it’s something, but going after Fel Seed —”

“You won’t convince her,” said Grak. “You should try though.”

“She’s gone,” said Lisi, not really paying attention to us. “Juniper should be next.” She was looking at the center of the portal, and she was right, Fenn was gone. I’d thought there would be something interesting, or at least a flash of light or a whirring noise, but it was silent.

“How do we know it worked?” I asked.

“If it didn’t, they’ll send someone to tell us by the time you get up there,” said Lisi.

“I’m waiting for Amaryllis,” I said.

“She wanted you to go without her,” said Lisi. “She got unlucky falling through the hells, it’s going to take her some time to catch up, and there’s a chance that she dies to the Doom Sun, like we almost did. Go, now.”

“No,” I replied. “I won’t abandon her. I’m making sure she gets through safely. Besides, we’re not going against Fel Seed without her.”

Lisi rolled her eyes and turned to Grak. “Can you talk sense into this idiot?” she asked.

“No,” said Grak. He started off toward the stairs, then looked at Lisi. “Leave him to it.”

Lisi glared at me. “We risked our lives to bring you out of the hells,” she said. “Don’t fuck this up, don’t touch any of the controls.” She stalked off after Grak, and I watched them, then turned toward the door, waiting.

Lisi was right, in a way. It was useless to wait for Amaryllis. She would be making the same kind of journey I had made, flying a helicopter for a long, long time, hoping that she didn’t run into trouble, that there wasn’t a mechanical issue, and that the site would be secured and the artifact still functional. The only way I would even know she was in trouble was if she had a problem right in the last mile, and the only way I’d be able to do anything about it would be to run out there. I didn’t have any magic at my disposal, no weapons, no tools, no armor, no entads, so there were only very specific circumstances that I could provide aid.

Still, I waited. I didn’t know how long it would take her to reach the Omega Hell, nor how long it would take for her to get to where we were, but I waited all the same. The thought of going back up and leaving her to fend for herself down here, or learning that she’d died in a way I could potentially have prevented … after Arthur had died, I’d thought a lot about everything I could have done differently to have prevented it, even though I hadn’t known that it had happened. It had been worse when Fenn died, because there had been a lot of ways it could have gone differently, a lot of ways I could have had different priorities or reactions or just planned things out better, or listened to the voice I’d dismissed as paranoia. Maybe it was the wrong lesson to take from those experiences, but I wasn’t going to feel those same regrets.

It was about three hours later when I heard the distant rumbling of an explosion outside.

I ran, full-tilt, through the maze of corridors, doing my best to update my mental map of the place. The sound had echoed through the compound, and it was hard to tell where it had come from, but I pulled the hood of my cloak up and stepped out onto the first balcony I saw, looking for a plume of smoke, or some sign of trouble. I saw it, then ducked back inside, running along the corridors, hoping that I could get there in time. If she died … well, she would come back to life somewhere else in the Omega Hell, and be left to her own devices on her way back, but there was a chance she’d end up like Lisi had, torn apart and left that way, more food for other creatures or plants.

I kept running, and passed an infernal corpse as I ran and picked up a spear that was laying next to its body, went out onto another of the balconies, trying to see smoke and debris. This time I saw a plume of it, when I continued running, I changed my path, trying to go through the corridors and cut through rooms to get to where she was. Eventually, I reached one of the outer walls and looked out another window, careful to avoid the light of the Doom Sun.

I saw a crashed helicopter outside the walls, and flopped out of the shattered cockpit, a woman’s body. There was a screech, then a fluttering of leathery wings, and the wyvern, or whatever it was, dove down towards her, the claws of six limbs pointed forward and wings swept back. I lifted up the spear, thinking that I might be able to throw it far enough, but realized how absurd I was being before I actually tried to huck it through the window. I was up on the third floor, raced down a set of stairs I had passed earlier, taking them three at a time.

When I got to the ground floor, the windows were smaller, too small for me to fit through, if I’d been willing to brave the Doom Sun. I ran through more rooms, looking for the door that I’d seen when we were flying in, and hoping that I wasn’t too late. If it was the same thing that had gotten Lisi, and I had no idea whether it was, then it was going to rip her apart and spread her out, and it was going to do that in the Doom Sun, which would kill her after not all that long. Based on how tough to get through the infernal had been, I had no idea whether the spear I was carrying, and the strength with which I could throw it, would be enough to drive it away.

I kicked open the door, careful to stay out of the Doom Sun, lined up my shot at the flying creature, then hucked the spear as hard as I could. It went high, over both the creature and the helicopter, but to my surprise, it returned to my hand, glowing faintly green. I threw it again, adjusting my aim, and it sailed through the air, striking the creature right through the torso. It let out a loud shriek from a mouth with too many parts, violently shook its claws, spreading Amaryllis all over the place, then launched itself into the air with the spear still stuck in it.

I don’t know what it had planned to do next, but the spear inside it glowed a bright green, then the whole thing, spear and creature, exploded in a rain of gore across the surroundings. A second later, the spear re-appeared in my hand.

“Fuck,” I said, glad that it didn’t seem like we were fighting any actual infernals. (Or rather, we were fighting them, but fucking them so completely that none would ever know what had happened or get within visual range of us.) I tossed the spear to the side.

I ran out, even as the blood and gore were still raining down, and grabbed the various pieces of Amaryllis, or at least the ones I could see. The cloak I was wearing didn’t cover me enough, not when I was moving at speed, and I felt the sting of it eating away at my hands and feet. I ran regardless, depositing what I had, arms and legs, then went back, searching frantically for the torso and head. I finally found them, unscathed in the shadow of the helicopter, and grabbed them, sprinting as fast as I could. The Doom Sun was getting my feet too much, making each step slippery with my blood, and I cradled Amaryllis close to me, hoping that she wasn’t too far gone, that she wouldn’t die on me.

Once I was inside, I put Amaryllis back together. I was missing a leg, but I couldn’t see it out there, and it was taking some time for my skin to regenerate back to what it had been. The regeneration itself was painful, and I took in a sharp breath as I felt it knitting my fingers back together.

When Amaryllis was together enough that she could be carried in one piece, I lifted her up and started carrying her to the portal.

“Thank you,” she croaked, once her vocal cords were intact.

“Come on,” I said. “Let’s get the hell out of here.”

I sent Amaryllis first, though she tried to fight me about it. They must have been primed for it, because as soon as she stepped into the opening, she vanished, again with hardly any of the special effects I’d hoped for. I had some time to look at the portal, and all the bodies that were arranged to make it up. There were all kinds of species, connected by wires in their brains, and at the center of it, hidden from the base but very visible once I’d gone up the stairs, was a gilded staff decked out in gems. They didn’t have entads in the hells, or at least weren’t supposed to. I wondered about its provenance, and how it had been schlossed in.

I didn’t have too much time to wonder though, because the machine activated for me, and I was back on Aerb.

Long Shot

Moving through the rooms was easier, now that we had the crystals in our heads. Using them, we could confirm that it was Earth, or at least a version of it, since one side benefit of the crystals was that they were capable of telling you whether or not someone existed. We all picked different targets on Earth, but they seemed to point in the same direction, which was a good sign. Amaryllis and I were the only ones that they seemed to fuck up for.

“There’s more than one time effect,” I said. “And the time effects serve different functions. But it’s not timey-wimey stuff, it’s just … a bunch of rules stacked on top of each other. The first and biggest effect is that time passes faster in the Long Stairs, relative to Earth, but apparently not relative to Aerb. There wasn’t really a design consideration for that, it was only to make the Long Stairs a bit more valuable, to make sure that teams were chewed through faster, and so that there was some fig leaf for why everything was infinite and unchanging.”

“Not much of a fig leaf,” snorted Fenn.

“No, it is,” I said. “I mean, let’s say that the army went through to the first Landing, and after a few times, they realize that Landings don’t change as much as the other stuff, it’s kind of a constant, a place where reality is marginally more stable than elsewhere. Well, the army sees that and says, ‘hey, okay, we’re going to colonize’. But because of the time effects, that doesn’t work, does it? If literal decades are passing whenever you turn your back for five seconds, you can’t take over the Landing, or even a part of it. At best, you can try to set things up for the relative future, or maybe try to plant someone in the Landing who’s doomed to live there for those decades, but obviously that doesn’t work because the Landings, by their nature, are incredibly resistant to change of any kind, and worse, if you do manage to change them, you’re basically just generating novel threats for yourself, because no one is going to stay sane.”

Fenn gave me a punch. “You’re such a dork.”

“And the second effect of unsteadily flowing time is this,” said Uther, gesturing at the bodies in front of us. “The dead are captured in their moment of death, for those who come after to find.”

“Right,” I said. “Partly to be creepy as heck, but also because it gives a kind of timelessness to the place. Also, mechanically, it gives a chance of offering some loot. I didn’t really do that much in the second go-around though.”

“Not much loot,” said Fenn, looking over the bodies. There were three of them, all slumped against the wall, and she was right, there was nothing to take off their bodies but their rifles, which didn’t have any obvious magical modifications or enchantments on them.

“I had a timeline for the Long Stairs,” I said. “It took some time for them — the War Department — to figure things out, and a lot of the deaths happened early on, when they just had no fucking clue about the Long Stairs. Early teams didn’t know much and were poorly armed, or at least, poorly armed compared to the ones who had magical enchantments and entads and stuff. Because they’re disproportionately represented in the deaths, you tend to see a lot of them.”

“How many people are meant to have died in this place?” asked Amaryllis.

“Look, if you’re thinking about how they hide the death tolls, just don’t,” I said. “There were like four thousand deaths or so between the Iraq and Afghanistan Wars, and there’d be no way to hide as many deaths as are implied to have happened to American forces in the Long Stairs. We never really went into the alt-history stuff, and only spent a few fractions of a session anywhere that wasn’t the Long Stairs themselves, even though there were a few opportunities that we might have followed up on. I think I had the idea of the Long Stairs deaths being hidden by the government as suicides, but that’s pretty gross, for obvious reasons.”

“Their families would think they died a dishonorable death?” asked Raven.

“Ah, no,” I said. “I meant gross from our perspective, as people playing the game. It’s saying that mental health stuff isn’t ‘real’, which, uh, is the gross part.” I also didn’t like the framing of suicide as dishonorable, but that was a personal pet peeve.

“You never talked much about the whys and wherefores of your decisions,” said Uther. He was searching the bodies, though no one was hoping for much. We had seen more than a few dead soldiers, some of them stripped of anything valuable, presumably by members of their team, and others who had probably been wounded and then limped their way to another room where they expired.

“It ruins the mystery if you explain it,” I said. “Besides, if I’d talked about it, it would have meant that there was less room for you to have your own interpretations. And god forbid you explain a joke, people hate that.”

“I suppose ‘living in your own little world’ would be both trite and insulting,” said Uther with a sigh. “But it does seem true, to me. You were always doodling in class, or writing entries for some world bible that no one else would ever see, and always keeping parts of them from us, even when we were playing.”

I frowned. “No,” I said. “I mean, there was definitely stuff that I didn’t share, that I couldn’t share without ruining a surprise. But I wasn’t like … I don’t know. I wasn’t keeping stuff from you.”

“You never talked about what was going on with your parents,” said Uther. “You gave hints and left us to guess.”

“That’s a totally different subject,” I said, frowning.

He stood up from the bodies and looked at me. “Is it?”

“I can see where you’d draw the line between the two,” I said. “But it is different. I’ve got an inner life, yes, but … I don’t know, I’ve been working on sharing it, expressing it to other people. I was working on it, even on Earth, before you died, and after.”

“And who did you share it with?” he asked. “Tiff,” he answered for himself as he watched me.

“Yeah,” I said.

“You got close, after my death,” he said. “Nine months, was it? Enough time for you to find solace in each other.”

“No,” I said. “It was before you died. We were dating, in secret.”

“Ah,” he replied. A mix of emotions flickered on his face, too confused for me to track.

“Sorry,” I said. How long had I been carrying around that guilt for? Saying it to him felt like a knot unwinding itself. “At first it was just — it seemed complicated, and then later, it seemed like it was really complicated.”

“Huh,” he said. He was still looking at me. “I was married, for a good many years, and have had hundreds of lovers, but still, somehow, that stings.”

“Maybe because you’re a creep?” asked Fenn.

“Fenn,” said Amaryllis.

Uther looked at Fenn, his eyes moving down her body. “You have a personal dislike of me. Is there something in our history I’m unaware of?”

“Nah,” said Fenn. “You know, with your whole thing about how we’re the perfect group to bring you in, you had nothing for me. Seems like it kind of puts a hole in that theory.”

“You’re the comic relief, obviously,” said Uther, looking her over. “You joked about being a love interest, but there’s nothing special to recommend you in that regard.”

“Don’t be a dick,” I said, scowling at Uther.

“Classic Juniper,” said Uther, smiling at me.

“What, trying to get you to not be a dick?” I asked.

He nodded.

“Okay, if you’re going to twist my arm about why I think you’re shit,” said Fenn, shifting her weight. “Juniper put you on a pedestal after you died, and maybe even before. I think that’s pretty clear to everyone. I’m the kind of person who likes you less because you’re a royal and a colonizer and whatever else, so there’s a bit of that, but it’s mostly the way you’re continuing on without giving us the basic courtesy of explaining a few hundred things to us. And yeah, you’re being a dick, not just to Juniper, who’s been mourning you and trying to get to you for the entire time I’ve known him, but also to Raven, who I don’t particularly know or care about, but who probably deserves better. She was a librarian or something.”

Uther regarded Fenn. I thought he was going to continue on his way, drawing us in his wake, leading the adventure against our wishes. It was what he’d done in the past.

“Colonizer?” he asked.

“You know,” said Fenn, waving a hand. “Setting up colonies, and … stuff.” She looked to me for support.

“The history of colonization is different on Aerb,” I said. “She was calling you a colonizer because she’s read a lot of Earth stuff, and I guess she thought that it would hit hard for you, because it seems like the kind of thing you thought about and tried to avoid. But that said, you did your best to obliterate cultures, and some of what’s downstream from what you did and what you preached turned out kind of ugly, in ways that I think would probably be familiar to you. Second Empire stuff, which you’d need a history lesson to understand.”

“Ah,” he said, looking at Fenn. “It’s a difficult thing, when one is taking the world through several different revolutions and getting everyone on the same page. I made mistakes with the orcs, because at the time I thought what I was doing was necessary, but I never engaged in genocide or anything like it.”

“And the fact that nearly everyone on Aerb speaks Anglish is, what, a crazy random happenstance?” asked Fenn.

“No, it was deliberate,” said Uther. “But also inevitable, in the scheme of things, unless enormous amounts of care and effort were taken. The memes fight each other for dominance, whether the cultures themselves wish for it or not. The endgame of a connected world is a single language. Anglecynn was a somewhat large and quite important power, and I did what I could to ensure that Anglish would be the standard, rather than some pidgin, but you could hardly call it colonialism, not as the term was understood in America, at least the last time I was there. There’s a reason that ‘colonizer’ isn’t a dirty word in Anglish. The colonies that I established were in places where no one had yet set foot.”

“Which was, you have to admit, convenient for you,” I said.

“Certainly,” he replied. “All part of the falseness of Aerb. And all the more reason to get going.”

It was more than I’d thought he would admit. Knowing Arthur as he’d been, I’d expect a hot take like ‘actually, some cultures are bad and should be squished’, and knowing Uther, I’d expected him to have a well-crafted argument to back it up. I didn’t know whether he was letting his guard down, or whether this was an area where he had some actual regret.

“Are their books less rotten than our own?” asked Amaryllis, whose eyes were on the bodies. “They should be, if these bodies can be dated to the last time a person was down here.”

“The bodies are old,” said Fenn, who had leaned down to touch a few drops of blood. “Either one of them took quite a while to die, or after they died, some separate team came in here.”

“Either way, their books are terrible,” said Uther. He opened one of them up to show Amaryllis. “Every other word is ‘Walter’.”

“Keep it away from the other books,” I said immediately. “Also, avoid saying or thinking the word.”

“Why?” asked Uther, raising an eyebrow in my direction. “We never came across that one.”

“It’s from the second iteration of the campaign,” I said. “It’s benign to the mind, but it will eat through books in a hurry, helped along by people talking or thinking about it.” I turned to Amaryllis. “Sorry, I forgot about that one. It’s not dangerous, just annoying.” I looked at the dead people. “It might have killed them, but only by screwing with their map.” Left unspoken was the fact that the meme might have made its way to our own books and be worming its way through them as we spoke. There wasn’t much to be done about it though, and I was hoping that being stored in Raven’s entad, Sable, or other extradimensional places might help.

“Either way, this room was a waste,” said Uther with a sigh.

I wasn’t so sure he was right. He was talking to us more with every room we passed through, and taking the opportunity to ask questions and reminisce. When he’d first come out of the time bubble, he’d been expecting to be ambushed by someone trying to bring him back, and he’d been resisting his natural impulse to stop and ask questions, but that was a stance he could maintain for only so long. We didn’t need to stop for so long to examine three dead bodies, but we’d done it anyway, because his defenses were weakening.

We went through another six rooms before Fenn and Uther got into an argument again.

“All I'm saying is, I could hit you,” said Fenn. “I’m the best archer in the whole damned world, you’ve never faced my like, and I could at least hit you with an arrow. Now maybe your armor would stop it, maybe it wouldn’t, but however good you are with a sword, you’re not fast enough to stop the kind of barrage I can put out.”

“Has Raven never told you stories of the kinds of opponents I’ve stopped dead in their tracks?” he asked.

“You don’t have still magic anymore,” Fenn replied. “I’m talking about your skill as a blade-bound against my skill as an archer, so long as we’re not standing right next to each other, but maybe even then. My arrows are considerably faster than bullets. I’ve got the fire rate of an AK-47.”

“I’ve fended off entire platoons of archers,” replied Uther, giving her a skeptical look. “And these were skilled archers, not an army of fresh recruits.”

“Yeah, and they’re like children with pea shooters compared to me,” said Fenn. There was a hunger in her eyes when she looked at Uther, a challenge and an anger. I wondered why, exactly she was trying to goad him on. I was even more surprised when he went for it.

“Alright,” replied Uther. “I’ll give you ten tries, in the next room that’s more than a hundred paces long.”

“We don’t have bone magic,” said Amaryllis. “That means primary healing is down to fairies.”

To be honest, I’d completely forgotten about the marzipan fairies, but apparently Amaryllis hadn’t.

“I don’t think that a dungeon full of things that are increasingly likely to kill us is a good place to spar,” said Raven.

“Perhaps not,” replied Uther. “But I’ve never been one to back down from a challenge or a boast. What kind of man would I be if I did? If the elf believes that she can hit me with an arrow, let her try.”

“Half-elf,” I said. “You can tell by the teeth.”

“But she’s well-versed in Earth culture, thanks to the gift you were given that allowed access to Earth,” said Uther.

“I am,” replied Fenn. “You know, there really wasn’t enough anime in your oeuvre. I’d for sure thought that you would have adapted something like, I don’t know, the Ghibli stuff, or Death Note, or other normie anime.”

Uther gave her a look. “I had more of an interest in the Western classics,” he replied.

“Who are you calling a weeb?” she asked, frowning at him. For a moment he was silent, but then he laughed.

It didn’t take long to find a suitable room, and to my surprise, Uther took off his armor, a magical process that caused all of the small black beads that made it up to fall to the floor at once, leaving him in nothing but briefs. The beads gathered up in a pile, ordering themselves into a hexagonal pillar, and while they did that, he took off his rings and crown as well.

“I’ll give you the best chance,” he said to Fenn. “Feel free to aim to kill, if it helps you.”

“I’ll be going for center mass,” she replied, nocking an arrow. “Ten shots, was it?”

“Ten shots at a hundred paces,” he replied.

“And what do I get if I hit you?” she asked him as he walked away, sword in hand. Fenn was very clearly staring at his butt.

“The satisfaction of having bested me?” he asked, looking back over his shoulder.

“Worthless,” she replied. “Besides, the world is ending, and if you’re right, your story is too. Think big.”

“A proper sit-down conversation,” he said. “Of your choice.”

“One for each hit,” said Fenn.

“Certainly,” he replied. He was a hundred paces away, pretty far, if perhaps not by archery standards. “And if you fail to land a hit, then you’ll leave us, back to the previous Landing. You should have little trouble getting there on your own.”

“Agreed,” replied Fenn.

“Not sure I like those stakes,” I said. I’d thought that this was just going to be a sparring match, a good sign, because it meant that Uther was slowing down in spite of himself, but nothing serious.

“Yeah,” said Fenn. “If I accidentally kill him, he’s going to have a hard time having a conversation with us.” She pulled her bow back to full draw and aimed it squarely at Uther, who had his sword casually held at his side. The bow looked like it was just about ready to snap from the tension, which was far in excess of what Fenn’s slender body should have been able to produce. “Are you ready?” she called to him.

“As ever,” he replied, not looking terribly worried.

Fenn stayed like that for what felt like a long time, especially given she was at full draw, putting her arm under strain.

“Any time,” muttered Amaryllis.

“Just enjoying the view,” Fenn replied. She looked over at me and winked.

When Fenn loosed her arrow, it whipped through the air faster than I could even see it move, with a booming sound like a gunshot from both the arrow and the bowstring. For all that, Fenn stayed perfectly still, undisturbed by the release of an immense amount of energy. A hundred paces away, Uther was still standing with his sword by his side, and an arrow lay on the ground in two pieces next to him.

“You’re better than I expected,” he called to her. “But clearly not good enough. Nine chances left.”

“Alright,” muttered Fenn. “Time to make a pin cushion.”

She drew again, let out a breath, then released, and this time, the magic of her bow multiplied the arrows as they went along, until they were a cloud of arrows by the time they reached Uther. From my perspective, it was happening pretty much all at once, and I only saw the end of Uther’s sword stroke, which had caused a burst of wind which knocked the arrows aside. He was still unscathed, but he was regarding Fenn more carefully now.

“By your reckoning, that was one shot?” he asked her.

“If you wanted a rule against it, you should have said so,” she replied back. “Your fault for not asking what the bow did.”

“It’s unsporting,” he replied, smiling at her. “But I suppose it makes things interesting. How many more times can you do that?”

“Enough!” she called back, but I knew Fenn well enough to see that she was doubting herself.

I could kind of understand why Uther was doing this. He had given up on Aerb, but not on the power of narrative. If someone challenged him, he wasn’t going to back down from it, that wasn’t something that protagonists did. I wasn’t sure what he thought would happen if he didn’t accept Fenn’s challenge, but perhaps he thought he’d need to prove it one way or another.

I had more trouble understanding Fenn, but that wasn’t much of a surprise. Maybe she wanted to see whether we could take him or not and make violence an option. Maybe she just really wanted to tag him with an arrow.

She watched Uther carefully, planning her next shot. I wondered whether this was going to be another volley shot, or something else. I was on her side, obviously, but I didn’t know if she could actually best him. Even if she was the best archer in the world, I didn’t know whether that meant she could beat the best swordsman. Parrying was fundamental to the blade-bound, one of the very first things that they learned, and I didn’t know whether various trump cards at the upper levels would allow Fenn to land a single hit. Given that he’d stripped down, I was worried that Uther would get an arrow through the heart, and given the healing we had available, it seemed reckless, but it was the kind of recklessness that you always heard about in stories about Uther, and Raven was doing nothing to stop him. This was pretty normal, I figured.

Fenn drew three arrows from her quiver and held two of them between her fingers as she nocked one. I had some sense of what she was trying to do, but didn’t see how it would be much better than the volley shot. She fired in quick succession, moving so quickly that I began to wonder what her punches must be like, if she was capable of using her muscles like that. Uther parried still, but not with a single big swipe. Instead, he just moved the blade very quickly, parrying one, then the other, and dodging the last with a motion that he’d started in the middle of the first parry.

“Fuck,” said Fenn.

“Five left,” called Uther.

“Did you think that would work?” asked Amaryllis, frowning at Uther but speaking to Fenn. Like me, she was probably having trouble fully tracking the movements.

“Volley shot lost me a lot of velocity,” said Fenn. “I was hoping that doing them like that they’d be fast enough that he’d miss one. The first arrow was slow but the others were faster, so they should have gotten to him at the same time. His big swing of the sword was slow too, so he couldn’t use it, and no matter how fast he can parry, he shouldn’t be able to use his sword to block all the arrows if it’s physically impossible for the blade to get in the way of all of them.”

“I see,” said Amaryllis, in a way that made me think she was only following in a very technical sense. A lot of what Fenn was doing should have been impossible.

“I am the best archer in the world,” said Fenn, drawing more arrows. “You could give me a little credit.” She got her arrows ready and let out a breath. “Five more, time to make them count.”

Whatever she was doing, what I saw was rapid shooting, two volley shots speeding at Uther and three arrows, one between the volley shots, and the other two after.

Uther swept his sword through the oncoming arrows, against both volleys, and I could immediately see what Fenn had been trying. If the duplication slowed her arrows down, she was hoping to hide a fast arrow among the slow ones, camouflaging it. It was the kind of thing that made me think maybe she was the best archer in the world, if that’s what she was capable of.

It also seemed like some anime bullshit.

And still, Uther was standing there, surrounded by duplicated arrows, most of them cut in half, without a scratch on him.

“Turn around, so they can see,” Fenn called to him.

Uther frowned, but did as he was told. I was shocked to see an arrow sticking in his left calf, especially because it must have entered from exactly the opposite direction from where she’d been shooting.

“How’d you do it?” he asked as he limped over. “I haven’t been hit by an arrow in a decade.”

“I bounced it off the back wall,” said Fenn.

“Good work,” he said, but I could tell it was making him some effort to be gracious. “Raven, could you remove this arrow? And Amaryllis, the fairy?”

“It was a dumb thing to do,” said Raven, but she helped him all the same, extracting the arrow. She looked up at Fenn. “There wasn’t a need to use real arrows, they could have just as easily been blunted.”

“Fucks with the flight,” said Fenn as she watched the arrow being taken out. “To be honest, I didn’t think I’d be able to hit him.”

“It was clever, using a ricochet off the back wall,” said Uther. “I’ve never seen that done.”

“Still,” said Fenn. “Armor would have stopped the arrow dead. It was moving slowly. A real target would have been on me like white on rice. If we’d actually been fighting, I’d have been shredded.”

“You’ve won your conversation,” said Uther with a sigh, as though he’d known it would be inevitable. “It’s yours to spend how you wish.”

“To be honest,” said Fenn. “I’m probably out at the next Landing anyway. It’s the maze one, right?”

“Labyrinth,” I said automatically. “But yes, you’d be safe there. Safeish.”

“Tell us about Vervain,” said Amaryllis. “His role in things, how you figured him out, what he said to you.”

“It’s my conversation to spend,” said Fenn, looking Uther over as he examined the healing that the two fairies he’d eaten had given him. He was still without his armor, and her eyes were wandering. “And Vervain is boring.”

“He was a mystery,” said Uther as he put his armor back on. The black beads swarmed around him, coating his skin once more. I knew the armor from our games. Each bead was its own extradimensional space, some of them probably filled with ultradense materials to stop hits, others as basic storage, and a few empty to absorb arrows or other projectiles. “The more I knew about him, the less I seemed to have a firm footing on his origins and motives. He was never involved in the plots, except as a mentor, or, when Raven wasn’t available, as a conduit for exposition.” I looked at Raven, who had a frown etched on her face. “Sometimes he gave quests.” He looked at Fenn. “Do you want to know more?”

Fenn looked at Amaryllis, then back at Uther. “Sure, I guess. If it were up to me, I’d make you tell us about Earth, or share some embarrassing Juniper stories, but I guess we can do the Vervain stuff.”

Uther nodded. “When I first came to Aerb, I was in the woods, wearing clothes I’d never known on Earth, well-made but too rough on my skin. I went down the path I was on, and found myself looking at a farmhouse. Everyone inside was dead, and I vomited, then fled. I didn’t know what was happening or why. Eventually, I stumbled into a theater troupe, and joined them, for a time. I learned about Anglecynn, and the wider world, or at least what was known of it to these common people. Orcs, elves, dwarves, mages, the fantasy kitchen sink … I was overwhelmed by it, at first, but I adjusted. The troupe took me in, fearful that I would be killed or enslaved if I were found wandering alone, and I made friends with them, using what skills I had on Earth. I discovered the Knack, my ability to become better at things in a hurry. I went from practicing sword fighting for a play to being able to best a trained duelist in the space of a week. And then the Dark King came and burned it all down, and I was on my own again, running through the woods, fleeing for my life. That was when I met Vervain.”

I was watching Uther closely, and listening to how he framed things. He’d said nothing about how long he’d been with the Erstwhile Players, but from the way he’d framed it, you might have been forgiven for thinking that it was a few weeks rather than three years.

“He was a wise old wizard,” Uther continued. “He was Gandalf, he was Dumbledore, he was Merlin, mysterious to his core, with inscrutable plans, wise, but also pretending to be wise, answering with vagaries that I could weave my own thoughts into. He asked for my name, and I told him that it was Arthur, but he didn’t seem to find that satisfactory, because he cast a spell to see what was written on my soul. He broke the news to me that I was heir to the throne.” Uther sighed. “In my history with Vervain, I pulled back his mask a dozen times, and always, until that last time, I found another mask beneath the one I’d removed. It was gaslighting, plain and simple, even at the start. That a powerful wizard should find the last living heir to the throne not long after a horrible tragedy was, to put it mildly, suspect.” He looked at me. “If you read that in a book, you’d think that the wizard had something to do with the attack, wouldn’t you?”

“Well,” I said. “It would be one hell of a coincidence, but implicating the wizard doesn’t seem right. Maybe he was like Old Ben Kenobi, waiting around for a long time in the background, revealing himself only when the time was right. Or maybe there was some other way that one could cause the other. He was following the group that went after your troupe, for example. That would still be a little fishy, because you’re the chosen one, but less fishy than him being in the woods on other business.”

“His story developed over time,” said Uther. “Just as you say. At first, it was a chance encounter, one I felt only relief at, but as I picked at his backstory, he had revelations to give. He’d been one of the court magicians for the Penndraigs, and told me he’d learned of the existence of a wayward son, who he’d long been seeking out, only to run into me by chance. Later, the story changed, and he had been doing the same thing the Dark King was doing, seeking out those who might be exceptional in some way, those who had signs of kingly breeding and might be able to pull the sword from the stone. And finally, of course, he told me that it was all lies made up after the fact to hide the truth, which was that he was a man who hadn’t existed until moments before I bumped into him.”

“There’s something I don’t understand about you confronting him. He can freely rearrange history and reality,” I said. “Why would it ever be possible to catch him out?”

“He stopped short at changing my memories,” said Uther. “That was by his own admission. He said that it put constraints on him. Personally, I think he was just lazy, in whatever way it’s possible for an all-powerful god to be lazy. Vervain was an addition to the story which would have fundamentally changed the fabric of everything else he had planned. He was a character who it would have taken too much effort to properly schloss in. There was a certain sloppiness to it all, which was the surest sign that Vervain was what he was.”

“We knew Vervain,” said Raven. “There was never anything suspect about him.” She sounded unsteady, wavering as though it took great effort for her to contradict him.

“He was secretive,” said Uther. “He would disappear at inconvenient times and appear with plot hooks whenever it seemed like the narrative was flagging. He always knew more than he let on, and that wasn’t just a matter of him taking credit for revelations other people had, which he definitely also did.”

“Your conversation with him, the one where he admitted everything,” said Amaryllis. “How did it go?”

“It was after we’d been to the Outer Reaches,” said Uther. “The schlossvolk were an answer to questions I’d had about the setting. They were entities who could, under the right conditions, insert entirely new things into reality as though they’d been there all along.” He watched us, perhaps wanting to see whether this would slip off any of our minds. “There were enemies I’d faced and phenomena I’d discovered which seemed out of place, as though they couldn’t possibly have been hiding in the background the entire time. The schlossvolk were a Watsonian answer to the question, but it didn’t escape my notice that I’d seen neither hide nor hair of Doyle, and whatever Vervain was, he wasn’t a creature created by the schlossvolk. Knowing how many of my adventures had been directly caused by the schlossvolk, and how they fit in with the narrative, I took a closer look at Vervain, doing my best to work behind his back. I hadn’t known the enormity of his powers, naturally, but I did my best to be secretive about it and continue the narrative as normal, with all that entailed. My pursuit of him was only when he was safely away.”

“But what could you possibly find?” asked Amaryllis. “He would only have left tracks if he’d wanted you to find them.”

“I found no tracks,” said Uther. “I searched the past with postcognition, and the future with a return trip to the Library, and I found nothing but boring answers. He thought that would satisfy me, but he didn’t fully grasp the lessons he’d been teaching me over the course of my time on Aerb. I had been pulling threads and finding quests at the other end of them for a very long time. Every time, every time, there was something on the other end of my hunches and inquiries. The lack of dead ends or plans that fizzled out was suspicious. For there to be, in the course of decades, exactly one instance of a lead which didn’t pan out, and for that to be Vervain, was like a lighthouse in the dark, a signal of deafening volume.”

“Sensible,” said Amaryllis. “So you confronted him.”

“I did,” replied Uther. “I didn’t know exactly what he was, but he accepted the label of DMPC readily enough. I had the sense that he was bored with me, and the game he’d been playing with my life, though he never said it outright. He answered many of my questions, but there was no moment, no real reckoning between us, no catharsis, no punchline to the whole affair. I had been living within the narrative, steeped in it, and it was one of only two or three times that the narrative felt like it had been completely dropped. In any proper story he would have been the villain, and there are all sorts of ways for a villain to reveal their plans, or at least display their true threat level. Instead, he quietly revealed himself as the avatar of a god so far above the others as to not even be the same class of being. I got nothing from him but a kind of sadness.”

“That wasn’t my experience with him,” I said.

“Fine,” said Uther. “Go on, explain him to me.” He hadn’t asked about my meetings with the Dungeon Master, when I mentioned them before, and I could imagine why. To Uther, those conversations couldn’t be trusted to reveal anything. They might have all been planted there with the specific intent of enticing him to come back to a life of adventure on Aerb.

“My read on him was that he was something like an addict,” I said. “He wasn’t getting much from it anymore, but letting it all end, giving you a happy ending, wasn’t something he was prepared to do, I think. At a guess, anyway, based on what he said to me.” Kindred spirits. I kept coming back to that phrase. I imagined myself sitting on the computer, going back to our dead wiki, or through old notes, reliving memories with Arthur, and sometimes imagining what he would say or how he would respond. It was a way of refusing to let go, refusing to accept the reality of his death. Maybe, for a healthier person, it might have been a part of the grieving process.

“I killed him because he said that he couldn’t stop,” said Uther. “I knew that it was a meaningless gesture. He held all the cards, he was the one who’d picked out the rules of the game we were playing. After Vervain’s death, things lightened considerably, like an apology expressed without words, but it didn’t stop. The adventures continued, as he said they would. It wasn’t that he couldn’t end them, it was that he knew he wouldn’t. There was only so much solace I could take in the conquests, the powers, the proficiency, the women, the riches — everything that I could ever have asked for, save for an end to the narrative. I thought long and hard on how I could avoid being the subject of stories, where I might redirect my imprisoner’s attention, and at times, it seemed to work, and I could rest until being called on once more to adventure.”

“There was more the Dungeon Master told me,” I said. “There’s more that I think you should know.”

Uther eyed me warily. “Go on then.”

“He told me that it was real,” I said. “That he nudged things here and there, but that it was all real.”

Uther laughed. “Oh?”

“He said that it was within my power to become god,” I said. “He said that he wouldn’t stop me, that when it was all over, he would fuck off forever and give me his powers, let me make everything into a heaven for everyone. He told me … that I’d deviated from his plans. Then he made it so a giant deer locus spit out a magical backpack that could pull things from Earth.”

Uther was watching me. I could tell what he was thinking, that my conversation with the Dungeon Master was all for this moment, all too perfectly calibrated to reassure Uther and Uther alone, to get him to play along for just a little bit more.

“The second time he showed up was when skin magic got excluded,” I said. “We’d been pushing the limits of several different magics, so he just … appeared in the room with us, stopping time so that it was just me and him talking. He had a book with him, purportedly written by me, though I’m not sure about what the point of that was.”

“It’s obvious,” said Uther. “He was pointing out the narrative to you. He wanted you to see it, to know it, to accept it.”

“He told me that he was excluding skin magic,” I said. “He said that he’d never intended it to get out of control. And then he said,” I considered whether to say it. “He said that he wasn’t my adversary.”

“I wrote about exclusions in Degenerate Cycles, if you read it,” said Uther. “One of the primary narrative functions they serve is a return to normalcy. I saw many of them, in my time. They allow magics to be present for an arc or two until they’ve been wrung of narrative weight and possibility. And the last time?”

“I died,” I said. “And I went to the hells. He met me there.”

“And?” asked Uther, when I paused for a bit too long. His gaze was piercing and his voice commanded respect. I wished I knew how he did that.

“A lot of it was about you,” I said. “He … he talked about how he’d been Vervain. He said that he’d made some mistakes with you, things that he wished he’d done differently. He talked about your early years on Aerb, before Vervain, and how he created Vervain to get you back on track. He talked about how you were happy for most of it, which … you said was true, didn’t you?”

Uther slowly nodded. “Juniper, can’t you see how much all of that was meant for my ears? You were smart, on Earth, surely you’re smarter here — is there a single word the Dungeon Master said that wasn’t intended for me? Do you really believe that?”

“I do,” I said.

“Then I don’t think there’s anything to discuss,” said Uther. He turned toward the next door. “I’m going to Earth.”

“You think that this is a way out,” said Raven, stepping forward.

“It plays within the rules of the game,” said Uther. “I couldn’t be allowed to simply leave, it needed to be a matter of narrative, a story of loss and hardship before I could finally win my prize and be free. But it also works outside the narrative, a break from the false reality of Aerb and a rebellion against my captor.”

“You left your wife to die,” said Raven. “You left your sons to nearly break the kingdom with their squabbles.”

Uther cast her a piercing glare, and she shrank back from it. “Zona was the love of my life,” he said. “I told her everything, years before I even considered leaving. I went with her enthusiastic blessing. As for my sons, I set my affairs in order well enough. It was their own weakness that they couldn’t find a workable solution between the two of them and had to come running down the Long Stairs in order to beg for my intervention, and failing that, counsel.”

“Sorry,” said Raven.

“You’ve spent five hundred years having your own ideas about who I am and what I did,” said Uther. “You have an idea of Uther which doesn’t match who I am as a person. I imagine it’s a shock, but it’s the kind of shock you’ll need to deal with quickly.”

He turned toward the door, then glanced at Fenn. “I trust you consider me to have upheld my end of the bargain?”

“Sure dude,” said Fenn. “Honestly, I checked out a bit, but the others seem happy.”

Between me, Amaryllis, and Raven, there wasn’t a hint of a smile to be found.

It All Depends On What You Mean By Home

Darili Irid was the same as it had always been. Every time Grak went back, he found that strange. He could understand, in the abstract, that some people wanted things to be how they’d always been, and those sorts of people made up the bulk of those who populated the lower heavens, but the people of Darili Irid had been resurrected, returned to life by the Authority. Grak would have thought, naively, that this would cause them to have some kind of revelation about how terrible the old world had been, and given them some leeway to make changes. Instead, it was the same, a mausoleum where the dead walked around, doing what they’d always done.

“I thought about leaving,” said Naridalogor when he picked up Grak in the communal truck. It was all exactly as it had been when Grak had returned home from the athenaeum. “Everyone does.”

“But you didn’t,” said Grak as they made the drive.

“No,” said Nari. “It’s where my family and friends are.”

“You’re all stuck together,” said Grak.

“Yes,” replied Nari. “If we don’t like it we can leave. If we leave we only see our friends and family to visit.”

“So leave together,” said Grak.

“It isn’t bad,” said Nari. “Lower heavens are still heaven.”

“Mrm,” Grak murmured.

“Some have left,” said Nari. “Mostly the younger ones.”

“Some have come to see me,” said Grak. “I have helped them, where I could.”

“Which ones?” asked Nari.

“I would not betray their confidence,” said Grak.

“Malik?” asked Nari.

Grak stayed silent. It was this kind of nosiness that had once been a larger part of his own problems in life, not just in terms of gossip, but thinking about others, and what they were thinking, and worrying about how he was seen. It wasn’t entirely behind him, but he could see, in retrospect, that much of his misery had been because of the same rumination that Juniper was often prone to, only more centered around other people.

“People leave because of scandals,” said Nari. “It’s made the clan’s power weak.”

“The higher heavens must stay on the mind,” said Grak.

“Speak to your father,” said Nari with a shrug as he focused on the road. “He worries that the town will collapse.” The Groglir word was gali, a word of utter destruction, beyond salvaging.

“He still doesn’t want ‘spians,” said Grak.

“No,” nodded Nari. “No one does.”

Grak sighed, but said nothing. He had done his own experimentation with ‘spians in various ways, especially early on, taking them as friends and lovers of different varieties. It had taken him a week to shake the falseness of it, and a few months to shake the feeling that he didn’t deserve to be treated so well. Everyone was treated as well as they allowed themselves to be. He didn’t keep any ‘spians now, but that was because he lived in a large apartment building with communal spaces, one constructed by a matchmaker, and there were more than enough real people around.

There was still the same main lift to take them down, still the same fifteen minutes of waiting while the chains rumbled. It was his third time visiting Darili Irid since the resurrection of everyone who’d died there, but his mind still went back to when he’d visited before, when the halls had been lined with the dead and the air had been toxic to breathe. It was, in a way, a continual surprise to see it restored, the result of some miracle that would never be explained. Logically, Grak knew that the explanation was simple: he had petitioned the Authority, and after only a momentary pause, the Authority had granted the request.

There was no one waiting for them, not like there had been the first time. It was understood that this was not a homecoming, but rather, a visit, nothing more. Grak had no friends in Darili Irid, only people who had once been friends and were now so far removed from him and his experiences that there was no possible way to connect.

Nari went off his own way, and Grak followed the familiar path to his father’s home.

“You’re back,” Grak’s father said, by way of greeting. It was like looking in a mirror that led into the future, but Grak never planned on aging, and in fact had taken a few years off, up in the middle heavens. “Come on in.”

“I’ve been trying to make the visits regular,” said Grak.

“Once every half a year or so,” said his father, nodding. “It would be better if you came during the high holidays.”

Grak shrugged, then took a seat at the table. His father doddered over to the cabinet and pulled down two ceramic mugs, then picked up an urn beside the chiller and poured each of them a glass of nego, whose name translated into Anglish as simply ‘the ferment’ or ‘the drink’. It was made from fermented kear.

“How have you been?” his father asked. It was a bland, inoffensive question, which was better than Grak had gotten in the past.

“I am well,” said Grak. “My days are long. My life is rich and vibrant.” In ways you would not appreciate.

“It’s good that you come back,” said his father. “It’s good that you don the proper clothes for it.”

Grak looked down at what he was wearing. “I want you to know that I am well. I feel like the person I was always supposed to be.”

“I am happy for you,” said Grak’s father. He sighed. “I wish that people could be happy in the life that was planned for them. Not all can be.”

Grak’s lip trembled. This was the closest that his father had ever come to an apology, or to an understanding of why Grak had found life within the dwarfhold of Darili Irid so intolerable.

“Eighteen lost since your last visit,” said Grak’s father. He took a drink of his nego, heaving a sigh as he swallowed it down. “We cannot go on like this.”

Seven of those eighteen had come to speak with Grak in one capacity or another. Sometimes it was for a brief conversation, and other times it was on a more permanent basis. One of them, Orkalon, had stayed with Grak for nearly two months, experimenting with forms and taking tentative steps into the culture of the middle heavens.

There were many more though, from beyond Darili Irid. The full text of Worth the Candle had not been released, and the Authority was mostly quiet about what had happened and why, but word of what had happened had spread, somehow. How could it not? They had all been known quantities on Aerb, Amaryllis and Juniper especially, but to a lesser extent, everyone else as well. Grak had a modest level of fame, which he found he somewhat enjoyed the perks of. The downside of that fame, if you wanted to call it a downside, was that people looked up to him in various ways. To the extent that Juniper was the Chosen One, and to the extent that Grak was a Knight, the dwarven communities that dotted the lower heavens and kept in touch with him had made him into something of a folk hero.

There had been a newspaper article written about him in one of the large dwarven presses, which he’d learned about through his assistant, one which painted him as a traditionalist dwarf soldiering on through thick and thin, head down, nose to the grindstone. When he heard about that, and a few others like it, he accepted an interview, which had gotten him some level of notoriety, particularly because of the kralikadon cast to his answers. Someone had gotten in touch with him and asked him to come to the High Heavens to write a book, which he agreed to, and which was completed in the blink of an eye. Then, somehow, that book had made its way down to the lower heavens, quietly infiltrating through layers of protection against that kind of thing, in a way that the Authority only rarely allowed. Many found it emotionally affecting, a story of loss, rejection, grief, and finally, picking yourself back up from the ashes of your old life.

Dwarves, most of them young but a few of them old, would have turned up on his doorstep by the thousands if he’d let them. Not able to bear turning them away, he had consented to have the ‘spian play him and give over a blunted version of the memories when the visit was finished. Dwarves had the second-highest population on Aerb, and the book (tentatively, Grak’s book) had been a hit, especially among the disaffected, and especially in these times, when the only thing holding people back from living exactly how they wanted to live was their ties to families and friends. He was happy that he was able to be a part of people like himself figuring out who they were, but there was something slightly bittersweet about it, because it meant that the dwarven communities of the lower heavens were shrinking.

“I agree,” said Grak softly. “You cannot go on like this.”

Grak’s father shook his head. “All we wanted was to persist. There has always been assault from the outside.”

“You use electricity,” said Grak, gesturing to the lights. “Your clothes are imperial.”

“Perhaps we shouldn’t have allowed even that,” said Grak’s father said with a sigh.

“People do not see doing things the way they’ve always been done as good,” said Grak. “You still use something meant to mimic bulk teleportation.”

“Change,” said Grak’s father, not answering that point. He clucked his tongue. He looked up from his nego and looked at Grak. “How do I keep them from leaving?”

Grak thought about it, and the other question that seemed to be implied, ‘how could I have stopped you from leaving?’.

“There are things that I liked about Darili Irid,” said Grak. “I have fond memories of childhood. I enjoyed adding spices to the kear from the pouch we got by bulk.” This had been done only rarely, as a treat. “I liked testing myself against others my age in a game of Ranks and reading through the books.” He was being careful not to say that his fondest memories were of the outside world and the promise that it held. “The most difficult part of leaving to Barriers was losing the rhythm of the day. The most difficult part of leaving the second time, to go on my own,” Grak swallowed. “The most difficult part of leaving was knowing that I would be cut off from the familiar.”

Grak’s father nodded. “You think that we should save what is good and leave behind whatever you think is bad. This cannot be done. They are linked as one way of life.”

“The losses will get worse,” said Grak. “The young are leaving. If you do not accept change it will be forced on you.”

Grak’s father was silent, in a particular dwarven way that involved drinking more nego and looking in the distance while measuring words. “This is a battle to save the soul of Darili Irid. You are the enemy.”

Grak felt a pain in his chest at that. They had never had a strong relationship, not since Grak had gone to Barriers, and when Grak had fled, leaving the dwarfhold without a warder, he had simply assumed that it was irreparably damaged. Yet he still loved his father, in a way, and it was clear that his father still loved him back.

“I don’t want to be the enemy,” said Grak.

“That’s what makes you an effective enemy,” sighed Grak’s father. “Not an enemy to me, but to Darili Irid. We can see your kindness. We can see that you think there’s a soul of something worth saving. You have no thesis though.”

Grak nodded. “This is true. I could not articulate the changes I would make. I could not say what Darili Irid would be if it allowed more aspects of the higher heavens. I can only say that it would make people stay. I’ve been keeping my thumb on the pulse of the dwarfholds. There are different solutions people have tried.”

“I have been doing the same,” said Grak’s father. “Allowing them out, but welcoming them in. Neo-traditionalism. Reinvention. Revival. Thespians. Clones.” He shook his head. “All are destruction in their own way.” There was something ironic in Grak’s father telling Grak that clones were a step too far, given that they were genetically identical, but Grak let it pass.

“As is the unchanging place you have now,” said Grak. “They are allowed to leave. They will leave. The more that leave, the more will follow. You will be forced into a choice at some point. Better to choose now than when half the dwarves are gone.”

Speaking persuasively had never been Grak’s forte, and in the middle heavens, he would have used augmentation for that, at least up to baseline. Being here though, in the lower heavens, meant that you came as you were, translated into some older form.

“Did you come here for this?” asked Grak’s father. “To tell me that we are doomed?”

“No,” said Grak. “I came because you are my father.”

His father made a happy grumble at that.

Their conversation quickly moved on to other things, at first the gossip around Darili Irid, then some of the small, minor concessions to heaven that they’d made, like allowing some level of regeneration and rejuvenation. Grak’s father was trying to find some way to keep the deathwatchs going, though no one was dying anymore, and there were no hells. They spoke for a bit about the spirit of the thing, and what that might mean, why something like the deathwatch was a valued tradition, and how you might have that tradition still, even if the thing underpinning it was completely gone.

Grak spent some time going around Darili Irid, checking in on the elders and assuring them that he hadn’t been eaten by demons, or whatever else they thought might have happened to him up there. He endured more gossip about people he only had a mild connection to anymore. He accepted praise for his part in saving the world, ate kear, drank nego, and where possible, when it didn’t feel like overstepping, spoke about his life in the middle heavens. He could see hunger, sometimes, in the eyes of the people he spoke to, envy over his place and his position. They could have it too, if only they allowed themselves to and turned their backs on their home like he had. Except, of course, that he was there, in among them, proving that it was possible to return.

Grak spent the night, the same as he had the two times before, in a small house that wasn’t being used by anyone else. He stared up at the ceiling and listened to the relative paucity of sounds that you got in a place like Darili Irid, nearly a mile underground, where everyone was meant to sleep at the same time. It was nothing like his home in the middle heavens, where there was always noise of one kind or the other. You could turn it off, of course, but Grak kept it on. He found something comforting in it.

Late at night, after the city’s lights were turned down low, there was a knock on Grak’s door.

He rose from his bed to go open it, and saw another dwarf standing there, looking unsure. It took a moment to place the face: it was Kradohogon Kadok, the dwarf that Grak’s father had arranged for him to childbond with.

“Grak,” he nodded.

“Kradoh,” said Grak. “If my father sent you, —”

“He did not,” replied Kradoh, somewhat stiffly. “Do you have time to talk?”

“I do,” replied Grak. His heart was already beating faster, given the strangeness of the visit. He led Kradoh in, and gave them more light. The place was small, even by dwarven standards, but Grak would be leaving in the morning. He sat on the bed, and Kradoh took the single chair.

“Do you think about our childbond?” asked Kradoh.

“Rarely,” replied Grak. And when he did think about it, it was with a fair amount of distaste.

“I read your book,” said Kradoh.

“Ah,” said Grak. He had read his own book, naturally, and was asked about it with some frequency in the middle heavens. In truth, the book had gotten bigger than he had even thought that it would be.

“I am sorry for the pain I caused you,” said Kradoh. “I am sorry that I made you feel out of step with this place.”

“You were playing your part,” said Grak. “I do not condemn my father for wanting Darili Irid to continue. I do not condemn you for attempting to tie me here.”

“I think of you often,” said Kradoh.

Grak nodded. He had nothing to say in response. Kradoh rarely crossed his mind. Aside from these visits, which Grak had committed himself to do twice a year, he thought relatively little of Darili Irid, except when people brought up the book, or another person came to him, looking for advice or solace. The previous two times Grak had visited, Kradoh had been absent, but not conspicuously so.

“I’m leaving Darili Irid,” said Kradoh.

“You are?” asked Grak. The question of ‘why’ had so many answers that it was hard for Grak to see what could be gained from asking it. “When?”

“Soon,” said Kradoh. “I was waiting.”

“Waiting for what?” asked Grak.

“I don’t know,” said Kradoh. “I kept finding reasons to put it off. This time, I was waiting for you.”

“I can have a ‘spian of myself speak with you in the middle heavens,” said Grak.

Kradoh nodded. “Thank you,” he said. “How long — how long did it hurt?”

“The leaving?” asked Grak. Kradoh nodded. “It still hurts, in its own way. There is a part of me that longs for this place and the feeling of being here. It took many years for it to be as small a part as it is now.”

“But you can cut the feeling out, in the higher heavens,” said Kradoh.

“You can,” replied Grak. “Some prefer to dull it.”

“Then why do you keep it?” asked Kradoh. There was something pleading in his eyes, as though he somehow thought that Grak had the answers.

“I value the connection, even if it is a small source of pain,” Grak said.

Kradoh looked down at his hands, which were gripping his knees. He nodded slightly, not seeming to have liked that answer. “Thank you,” he said, standing. “You had no obligation to hear me out.”

“I did,” said Grak. “Because I thought that it might help you.”

Kradoh nodded and then left, seeming somewhat defeated, the light of decision he’d had when he’d knocked on the door now faded. It went that way with the dwarfholds sometimes. People would decide to leave, then decide to stay, making a decision and then backing out of it at the last moment. It had been like that for Grak, in more ways than one, though the circumstances had been so much different.

Grak stared at the ceiling in the dark, turning these thoughts over in his head and trying to remember how to sleep, until eventually it came to him.

He left early in the morning, as he often did, wanting to relieve the itch to be back home as quickly as possible. There was a long ride up the main shaft, then a drive by truck, which was again done by Nari, and then, finally, Grak was free from the limits of the lower heaven. If it had been truly intolerable, he was entirely capable of directly leaving, but it would cause ill will from his father, and perhaps others within the clan. He liked being able to come back, especially if he could make his arguments, and he wasn’t in his apartment for more than five minutes before he was making distant, far-off plans to go back.

‘Apartment’ was, perhaps, understating it, but it was a ‘building’ which he lived in with other people. When Juniper had talked about the kind of heaven he would build for Grak, he had talked about a communal place, and this was more or less what Grak had ended up in, one with perhaps a thousand people all told. There were enough that you didn’t know everyone, but not so much that you couldn’t link yourself to anyone else through friends of friends. There were fewer dwarves than Juniper had guessed Grak would prefer, though that might have been because Grak had a surplus of dwarven visitors from outside.

“Schedule,” said Grak to the air as the assistant stripped off his clothes and reverted his body to how it had been. There were many things that Grak had gotten rid of, but transitions were not one of them, and he rarely skipped them, except when he was in a hurry. He had tried having his clothes teleported off or his body instantly changed, but there was something he didn’t like about it, even with the smoothing and mediation that the assistants applied.

“There is a Ranks competition you might be interested in,” said his assistant. “That’s in an hour. There’s a restaurant that just started visiting the colony that I think you might enjoy, and I have a list of dinner dates for you, either individually or in groups. There are six letters that you’ve previously expressed interest in answering yourself, none personal. You currently have twelve books on your reading list, eight short-dives, two movies, and several articles, if none of that interests you.”

Grak thought about that. “Answer the letters as me,” he said. “One time only, integrate the process.” Almost at once, the memories of having written six letters was inserted into his head, and with some effort, he could recall the exact wording he’d used and why. He didn’t make the effort. This wasn’t the first time he’d done something like this ‘one time only’, and it was becoming a pattern. “Nothing pressing on the schedule?”

“No,” replied the assistant. “Would you like me to find you a date?”

“Something fast and tactile,” said Grak. “You can look into my mind, one time only. Find someone suitable.” It wasn’t normally what Grak liked to do, but he was feeling anxious and helpless, albeit at a low level. It was clear that things in Darili Irid could not stay as they were, and there was nowhere to go but up.

“I’ve found a match,” said the assistant. “They’re available now. Will you accept?”

“Will they take me as I am?” asked Grak, looking down at his dwarven body. He had put on some muscle, and lost a bit of fat, had straightened his teeth and given his eyes a bit of depth of color, fixed a few irregularities and enhanced the ones that gave him character — but he was still mostly Grak, most of the time.

“They will,” said the assistant.

“Then I accept,” said Grak.

The man that greeted Grak at the door ten seconds later was wearing a draconic body, big and bulky, muscular and smooth on his front, but bumpy with protrusions on his back. He was nude and already half-erect, with the kind of bespoke phallus that was currently in vogue.

It was, as he’d asked the assistant to provide, fast and tactile.

Afterward, they both laid on Grak’s bed, staring at the ceiling and enjoying the afterglow.

“Do you mind if I change?” asked the man.

“Not at all,” replied Grak. These were the first words they’d exchanged.

The transition was fairly slow, and Grak idly watched as the man went from draconic monster to something softer and more human. Once it was complete, Grak found himself next to a thickly built woman, Broshe by the look of her, though with ambiguous enough gender markers that it was possible that she was a gender blend, neither male nor female. Grak had been among the humans for so long that the bimodal genders had become his usual way of thinking. A quick mental ping of his assistant supplied a name, Lanik.

“I prefer male when I’m in the mood, and female right after,” Lanik said, by way of explanation. “Though I’ve never been too hung up on it.”

“What were you, originally?” asked Grak.

“Well that’s a very personal question,” Lanik said. “I’ll answer if you go first.”

“This is what I was,” said Grak. “Just a dwarf.”

“I imagined,” Lanik replied, running fingers through their hair. “There aren’t many who adopt a dwarven form. You’re quite fetching though.”

“That may be the orgasm talking,” said Grak. It wasn’t all that common that he spoke to his partners afterward. “If you don’t want to talk about your past life, I don’t mind.”

“I was a very rare quarto,” Lanik replied. “One fourth Broshe, one fourth Mezin, one fourth human, and one fourth vitric. Female, though I prefer male most of the time now.”

“How many were there like that, in all of Aerb?” asked Grak.

“Three,” Lanik replied. “My brother and sister were the other two. I checked with the assistants. Thankfully now it doesn’t matter.”

“It might matter to some,” said Grak.

“Fuck ‘em,” Lanik replied. They turned to look over at him. The masculine aspects of the gender blend had, with time, begun to heighten. “From the room, which I assume is yours, you agree? Fuck ‘em if they have a problem with who you choose to be?”

“Mmm,” said Grak. He lifted Lanik’s hand to his mouth and kissed it. “Fuck them. I wish them the best.”

“What did you ask for, that brought us together?” asked Lanik, who was now fully a man of some variety, though with no trace of draconic features.

“I let the assistant see what I needed,” said Grak. “I requested something fast and tactile. I didn’t think I would get someone interested in talking.”

“And the talking is going alright?” Lanik asked. He leaned forward and kissed Grak’s chest.

“It is,” replied Grak. “What did you ask for?”

“The same thing I always ask for,” the man replied. He moved himself to be over Grak, not quite straddling him. More of the draconic features had surfaced around the face, and the bumps and protrusions that Grak had seen before were surfacing. “I asked for someone whose life I could make better with a particular part of my anatomy.” He was breathing a bit harder, and kissed Grak again. The two of them were still naked, and draconic eyes roamed Grak’s body. “Are you one of those people who thinks that having sex all day is just wireheading with extra steps?”

“I limit myself,” said Grak. “No more than six hours a day.” He paused. “I could make an exception today though.”

After, Lanik transformed back into a womanly form, and curled up next to Grak.

“We have another five hours left,” said Lanik.

“Mmm,” said Grak. “When the five hours are up, we’ll have to focus more on talking.”

“I worry you’ll find me boring,” said Lanik.

“You’re a rare quatro,” said Grak. He thought for a moment. “I imagine that’s a lot to live up to.”

“It is,” nodded Lanik, their forehead against the side of Grak’s head. “I got so little of each species, each culture. A few months ago I went through some microdives to get insight into each of them, the ancestral processes. I felt like …I don’t know.”

“A tourist,” said Grak.

“Yes,” said Lanik. “Exactly.” They sat up slightly, looking into Grak’s eyes. “Do you think the assistants set us up? Like this was meant to be more?”

“I don’t know about that,” said Grak. “Whatever the assistants intended, we’re free to make our own path.”

The Narrator, the Angel, and the Devil

The Angel and the Devil had dressed up to play cheerleader to their Juniper, the Narrator.

The Angel was Fenn, of course, the one who had died to poison and then gone to heaven, where she’d spent approximately three years with the Narrator, lounging about and getting a taste of the heaven that everyone else now enjoyed, though with perhaps less than her fair share of the modifications. She had hobnobbed with the Pantheon, and occasionally spoke with the Dungeon Master, though despite the fact that he’d put her in heaven, he seemed somewhat disinterested in her. Most of her time was spent watching television, chiefly anime, which could be had at incredibly high resolution compared to VHS copies pulled from the backpack to play on Mary’s homemade television.

The Devil was Fenn, the other one, who had died of poison and then woken up in the hells, going on to follow Uther Penndraig down the Long Stairs. She had put an arrow in him, as she would tell anyone who listened. She still had that arrow, which was kept on display in a glass case.

They were more alike than they were different, and they went through phases where they did more or less to differentiate themselves. Sometimes they would make themselves exactly identical, down to their makeup and how their hair fell, and other times they would wear different bodies entirely. They also merged specific memories with some regularity, usually when one of them had something they didn’t want the other to miss out on, which made them even more identical than they otherwise might have been. Still, they had started with a rather large divergence, and it had grown somewhat with time.

The house the three of them shared was a sleekly alien thing, constructed of curves and sharp edges, then decorated with all kinds of plants and comfy, furry bits, and occasional pieces of wood. It was expertly designed, just the right juxtaposition that made it clear that anything was possible. There was no kitchen, since none of them had any interest in cooking, and their bathroom had a large bathtub but no toilet. Beyond the boundaries of the house were clouds, and getting to the rest of the property involved dropping down from the sky and gliding, which took half a minute, if you didn’t elect to just teleport. There was a large beach beside an ocean with a coral reef, and a little villa that they used when they wanted a more rustic experience. The villa came with thick, muscular, well-oiled men whose hands were perfectly suited to giving massages. They ‘unfortunately’ took liberties with the Fenns sometimes, those wicked men.

The two Fenns stood on either side of the Narrator, watching the game he was playing. The Devil was dressed up like one of her namesakes, though an Earth interpretation, with a slender tail, horns growing from her forehead, and a pitchfork that she kept using to poke at things. The Angel had a softly glowing halo that floated above her head, and a pair of small white wings that grew from her back. They’d been having great fun with the whole concept, which the Narrator suspected would last for another few days, and then be resurrected periodically as a callback.

“How are you so bad at this?” asked the Devil, peering down over the Narrator’s shoulder. The game was played mentally, but with voice channels layered on top of it so there could be some ‘normal’ communication. The game board appeared fifteen feet across in their hyper-modern living room, having required a bit of an expansion to accommodate it. Within the hexagonal board, there were mountains and grasslands, seas and trees, a whole world rendered in unbelievable detail, and you could only get a sense of what was actually going on by wildly enhancing your senses or getting a direct feed into your brain.

There were tiny cities down there, with tiny people living in them, all played by the ‘spian. Their lives, such as they were, were influenced but not decided by the three gods above them. The Narrator was one such god.

“I’m not bad at this,” the Narrator grumbled. “They’re both better than me. There’s a distinction.”

His opponents were Juniper and Juniper. One of them was the Juniper of Legend, the dream skewered boy from Earth, while the other was the Other Juniper, who had defeated the Union Empire of the Other Side with his harem.

“Doing this three-way is hard,” said the Narrator. “There’s too much potential for ganging up, and with the cognitive limits it’s a strain to figure out what themes you’re working against.”

“Boon,” that was B-side Juniper, “has crisis, books, and puzzles,” said the Angel. “I will bet thirty million dollars on it.”

“You’re not allowed to help,” said the Narrator. “Though I was able to hear that, so I suppose it must not have been that helpful.”

“Color commentary is allowed,” said the Devil. “It’s in the rules, we added that clause.”

“Hey, shouldn’t you be good at three-ways?” asked the Angel.

The Narrator turned to her, though almost all of his attention and sensorium were on the game. “Why would — oh,” he turned back, having seen Fenn’s grin.

The Narrator’s primary theme was Ruin, his secondary theme was Hope, and his tertiary theme was Harmonic. He was attempting to use his limited power to make a world that was maximally conducive to those themes, as measured by the collection of the best stories that took place within the world, though it was sufficient for them to have happened, even if they weren’t recorded. The most expensive (but also most impactful) method was through injecting a magic system, which everyone had already done, but another magic system, especially so late, would have driven any of them to bankruptcy, and would mean that they were virtually locked out of the rest of the game, which usually lasted five thousand years (some of which was sped through by mutual agreement).

The Narrator was, at that moment, attempting to make a religion, which was rather difficult, given that he didn’t want to spend too much of his godly power on it. This was made doubly difficult because his primary, Ruin, wasn’t terribly conducive to it, though he had gotten lucky with having Ruin and Hope together, since they could play off each other. The real trick with playing this variety of Godsgame was that you didn’t know the themes of the other players, which were guaranteed to be unique from each other but not necessarily in conflict. There was a hidden roles aspect that the Junipers found themselves quite liking, because it meant that you were not only creating, but attempting to read meaning into the world.

The Junipers had invented this game, with the rules and mediation largely through assistants. They loved it with a passion, and loved it even more when playing against other Junipers. Sometimes the Narrator played mirror matches against a temp clone of himself, but often it was with the original Juniper. The Narrator lost more than he won, especially in three-way games like this, enough that he’d been offered a handicap of some sort. It was an offer he’d rejected because he didn’t lose that much, and the fun was mostly in the playing, at least for him. He’d given some thought as to why he was worse than the other Junipers, and he thought that perhaps it was his tendency toward a certain kind of thematic pareidolia. At the end of the game, he would sometimes find that he’d been reading the themes almost entirely wrong, picking up on things that hadn’t been there.

“We should do sexy Godsgame sometimes,” said the Angel. “How have we been in heaven this long and never thought to do it?”

“Not even sure how that would work,” said the Devil. “We’d get themes, but they’d be sexy themes?”

“Fetishes,” said the Angel. “We’d each get three fetishes, and at the end of five thousand years, we’d get scored on the best sex scenes to come out of it.”

“I think you’d run into some problems,” said the Narrator. He was looking down into the game world, which was momentarily paused, trying to hastily construct a Divine Revelation for someone in what was presumably an opponent’s religious order (though it was often hard to tell).

“We’d just have assistants take care of the nitty-gritty,” said the Angel. She looked over at the Devil. “We could do that now, if you’d like?”

“I want to spectate,” said the Narrator. “Can it wait until after this game?”

“Temp clone?” asked the Angel, seeming quite hopeful. The Narrator only rarely went for it though. He liked linear chronology too much.

“Request for a visit,” chimed the assistant. She spoke as a disembodied voice, one modeled off GLaDOS, at the Narrator’s insistence. The Fenns might have preferred something different, and could have changed their perception of it to something else, but part of living with someone else was sharing experiences. They had played Portal, the two Fenns working together, and not really gotten all that much from it.

“For whom?” asked the Devil. She put extra emphasis on the ‘whom’.

“Fenns,” replied the assistant. “The visitor has identified himself as Nellan.”

“Alright,” said the Angel. “One of us needs to not panic, not it.”

The Devil rolled her eyes. “It’s fine, we need to treat this like it’s normal. Be normal!”

“Do you need me?” asked the Narrator, looking away from his game for a moment, his attention fully on them.

“No,” said the Angel. “I think we’re getting better at this whole estranged mother thing.”

“We’ll give you the full debrief when it’s over,” said the Devil. “Now, what to wear?”

“Just have the assistant pick something,” said the Angel.

Because the assistant was linked into their minds, the thought went through in an instant, and a mannequin Fenn stood in front of them, wearing a somewhat conservative cream-colored dress that had a few layers to it. Certain aspects of the body (which was part of the outfit, in this day and age) had been changed, de-emphasizing the breasts, cutting even more of the muscle, and shortening her slightly. It was an attempt to project ‘motherly’, and perhaps a bit too obvious as that, but part of the complex signaling of clothing was sometimes over- signaling so you could really drive the point home.

“Good,” said the Angel. “Let’s make like The Fast and the Furious 3 and drift.”

Being two people was, sometimes, complicated. Clones were much more common now than in the beginning of heaven, but having two clones that lived together and shared memories so much wasn’t how most people went about it. In Fenn’s case, the clones were also more divergent than most people got, by virtue of their unique circumstances.

When it came to what to do about this, there were several different options. Sometimes both Fenns were present, but some people felt that was a little much, either because of being outnumbered, or because they bounced off each other, and it just changed the dynamic of interaction too much. Sometimes they engaged in memory sharing, but that wasn’t perfect either, because they were divergent, and if it was important to both of them, they sometimes had different takes on what to do and who to be. There was little more annoying than sending your clone to a social function and then getting a chunk of their memories only to see that they had done things in a very different way than you would have liked. The final class of options was a temporary merger of one kind or another.

There were two basic schools of thought. The first was that the merger should be like Dragonball Z or Steven Universe, creating a composite of the two halves. There were a number of benefits to this, like it being easy, but it had drawbacks, like sometimes saying things that weren’t what either half would have chosen to say. A composite was a third person, in a way. The second school of thought was that it should be more like two people in one body, agreeing or disagreeing on various courses of action, or, sometimes, with control switching seamlessly from one to the other, driver and passenger.

There was also a hybrid model. This was the Pacific Rim school of thought, and the Fenns had seen it with the Narrator on movie night shortly before they’d decided they needed a better merging solution. As it turned out, they were drift compatible (“What a shocking stroke of good luck!”). They could work as one, with some minor overlap of their minds mediated by the Authority. In some ways, it was the best of both worlds.

“Okay,” said the Angel as she strapped in. Their cockpit was modeled after the movie, with little suits and helmets and things, though for the most part their ‘attention’ was on the outside body they were sharing, with the internal part only there for a shared fiction of convenience. “Good to go?”

“Good to go,” said the Devil.

They walked to the door in their approximately motherly body, and opened it wide to see Nellan coming up the path, part of the garden area which was attached to the house. The timing was perfect for him to arrive just as the door opened, because this was heaven, and if you allowed it to, heaven could have impeccable timing like that.

“Hi Fenn,” said Nellan. He was a lanky boy, though not even really that much of a boy anymore, well on his way into adulthood. He could pass for human, though he was tall and had a skinny muscularity that you didn’t often see people go for by choice. In the middle to high heavens, bodies were a matter of convenience and aesthetic preference, but Nellan was comfortable in his own body, and had kept himself mostly as he was, though it was possible that he only did that for these visits.

“Hello Nellan,” said Fenn as he walked up. “What brings you by?”

“I just wanted to talk,” said Nellan, shrugging. “Are you free?”

There was a bit of awkwardness between the two of them. The relationship was too new. The Angel had written him a letter, which the Devil had revised, in part because the Narrator had thought that it would be good for them. They had fired the letter off, pressing a symbolic red button together, and then waited, not knowing whether it would be delivered, or whether he would read it, or whether he would have a good reaction. One of the frustrating things about heaven, which the Fenns had talked to the Narrator about quite a bit, was that people could just opt out of talking to you, or have preferences that meant you were basically a ghost to them. Worse, other people could set it up so that it was difficult to check whether they could see you or not. The Narrator (who hadn’t actually been the one to set up the heavens, not really) had argued that other people fundamentally had no right to each other, not even a single bit back, the 0 or 1 of read or unread.

Almost no one actually did that though, and Nellan had gotten a response back to the Fenns later that same day. From that point on, their contact had been in bits and pieces, with a few meetings and the occasional dinner, and they would sometimes bump into each other while out doing other things, in the way that the heavens sometimes arranged, if you were into it.

Still, there was some awkwardness. There were times when the Fenns wanted to propose retroactively adding in memories for the three of them, of a happy life in some alternate timeline that hadn’t actually happened.

“I got into the program,” said Nellan. “I’m going to be a runner on the barrisball team.”

“Oh!” said Fenn. “Well, congratulations, I know that you were waiting on tenterhooks for that. But that means you’ll be gone for a few months?”

“Six months,” he said. “I could run a clone on the outside, but part of what I enjoyed about the proposal was the sequester, so … that’s part of why I’m here.”

“To say goodbye?” asked Fenn.

“Well,” he said. “Not for good, obviously, but six months can be a long time.”

“And you think you’ll do well?” asked Fenn.

“It’s not really about doing well,” said Nellan. “It’s more about … being a part of a team, being a part of the experience. They managed to attract a lot of players for it, and they think the audience is going to be even bigger. The team I’m on won’t necessarily do that well, but so long as we don’t end up in the bottom tier, I think I’ll be good with it.”

“Could that happen?” asked Fenn. “Ending up in the bottom tier?”

“Sure,” he said. “There was a proposal to include some ‘spian teams, or players, or something like that, so you could always be better than someone, but they decided against it.”

“Ah,” said Fenn. “Well, then, I hope you do well.”

(“More supportive,” said Devil Fenn.

“Yeah yeah,” replied Angel Fenn.

“Fucking frightening to have a risk of failure like that,” said Devil Fenn.

“That’s why it’s better not to try,” replied Angel Fenn.

“Important life lesson, that,” said Devil Fenn.)

“I’ll be fine,” said Nellan, giving her an embarrassed smile. “You’re worried about me.”

“Competition isn’t how I like to spend my time,” said Fenn. “It gives me nerves, unless I go in knowing that I’m better than everyone, or I don’t care about the outcome.”

“Don’t you, the two of you, compete?” asked Nellan. “Archery competitions and things like that?”

“We do,” said Fenn. “It’s different though, especially because she’s me. I never have to feel inadequate if she wins.”

“I’m not worried about feeling inadequate,” said Nellan. “There was a screening, they rejected people they thought would have a bad time.” He was watching her. “I’ll be fine. I’m glad you care.”

“Of course I care,” said Fenn. “And you should know that I’ll be watching you the whole time.” She glanced at the house. “Are you staying for a bit, or leaving?”

“Leaving,” he said. “Just a quick visit, to let you know I wouldn’t be around for a bit. I’ve got other people to see and talk to, stuff to prepare.”

“Well, I appreciate it,” said Fenn. She beamed at him. It was hard to think of him as her son, given how much time they’d missed together, but —

“Alright, later mom,” said Nellan. The word seemed to slip out of him, and for a moment he just stood there, awkwardly.

One of the weird things about sharing a body like they did was that some things could cascade onto themselves. Angel Fenn took a faltering step towards him, and Devil Fenn pushed it harder, and then they had reinforced each other’s decision and had moved forward to wrap him in a tight hug. He accepted it, with his strong arms around her, so grown up, nothing like the hugs that he’d given as a child. They stood there for a moment, and Fenn turned away to compose herself.

“It’ll be okay,” said Nellan. “It’s only six months. We’re sequestered, but it’s only one way, so I can give you a shout out every once in a while.”

“Thanks,” said Fenn, beaming at him.

He left back down the path, fading away to smoke almost instantly as he departed to elsewhere. The Narrator was always changing up the special effects used to mask transitions and make things feel more magical.

The Fenns split apart, back into Angel and Devil, though neither of them had the same costuming on.

“He called us mom,” said the Angel.

“Maybe he was just confused,” said the Devil. “I mean, he does have a real mom.”

“We’re his real mom,” said the Angel.

“We’re his bio mom,” said the Devil. “He never had anything bad to say about the people who raised him, except that they were a bit too human for his tastes.”

“Still,” said the Angel. “He did call us mom. And then he gave us a hug.”

“We gave him a hug,” the Devil corrected.

They were both still standing there, looking at where he had been, and the smoke that was languidly rising into the air.

“We’re the best moms in the world,” said the Angel, grinning at the Devil.

“Come on,” said the Devil. “We’re going to have to learn all about barrisball, and also tell Juniper, so he’s not bored out of his mind when we’re competently talking about what’s surely the greatest game in the world.”

“One sec,” said the Angel.

“Yeah?” asked the Devil.

“Have you ever,” she paused. “Thought about having more kids?”

“Meh,” said the Devil. “Thought about? Yes. Seriously entertained the idea? No.” She looked at the Angel. “You know that if you have a kid with him, then we’d basically both be raising her together, right?”

“Her,” smiled the Angel. “And yet you haven’t seriously entertained the idea.”

“Whatever,” sighed the Devil.

“Juniper Prime wanted kids,” said the Angel. “Amaryllis is pregnant again. Just sayin’.”

“Yeah,” said the Devil, crossing her arms. “I hear ya. But, and I know asking this is a bit too on brand for us, what if we fuck it up?”

“It’s simple,” said the Angel. She leaned close and did her best conspiratorial whisper. “We blame Juniper.”

“Fuck we’re brilliant,” grinned the Devil. “He’ll never know what hit him.”

As it turned out, barrisball was fucking complicated and absolutely enormous. The Fenns had a philosophy, which was that you should extract as much fun from something as you could normally, then have assistants or modifications do the rest. For whatever reason, they’d felt that learning barrisball was something that had to be done properly, but the rulebook was thick, and it had lots and lots of tables.

“It’s a middle heavens megasport,” said the Narrator, as though that explained everything. He had lost his Godsgame match, and came to help them. “You’re not meant to sit there and read a rulebook, though it’s designed so you could, you’re meant to either get the whole thing downloaded straight into your head, or you’re supposed to listen or watch with active commentators to help you make sense of what’s happening. If you’d like, I can do the download and then explain to you? I have some contact knowledge of barrisball, since it’s shaping up to be a big thing, but I wasn’t going to go through the rules.”

“Sure,” said the Angel. “We know you love explaining things.”

“Okay,” said the Narrator. “Well, to start with … huh.” He paused, as if trying to make sense of what he was seeing. “It’s pretty clearly of the ‘lots and lots of things’ school of design, more than other megasports. I think the overall aesthetic is that it’s never the same game twice, kind of a … descent into madness type thing? So, there are a hundred teams of a hundred players, divided into squads of ten. Nellan is part of Squad Furlow on Team Echelon, and the team’s unique power is shapeshifting, while the squad’s unique power is a shapeshifting version of rubber band stuff. Each individual team member has their own unique specialty within the squad focus.”

“Is this the most fucking anime thing ever?” asked the Devil. “Everyone, all ten thousand people, they have some unique power, and they’re in matchups together?”

“I mean, I guess,” the Narrator said. “So, the goal of the game always involves a ball, sometimes multiple balls, and sometimes it’s about possession of the ball, sometimes it’s scoring goals, sometimes it’s stealing someone’s ball … there are a lot of variations. Typical match time is about two hours, but there are also some long runners. The matches can be either squad on squad, or team on team, which is less common. There are arenas, lots of them, with —”

“Fucking Christ,” said the Angel. “How long does this go on for?”

“— modifiers that can be purchased with points won, random modifiers, and a bunch of other stuff,” the Narrator finished. “Basically, you can think of it like anime, yeah. Nellan will have a squad, which exists within a larger team, and will face down other squads, which have their own superpowers. So, standard sports anime, I think? Except the ‘cast’ is probably too large for that. The rules and teams get more complex over time, and the special properties of each arena and match mean that everyone is always figuring things out.”

“Well, no way around the download,” said the Angel, sighing.

“Wait,” said the Narrator. “Maybe partial download? Only the stuff you need to know? Rules that get introduced to you as you see them in the game? Because I’m not going to lie, barrisball has an absolute fuckton of rules, and I think if they get introduced slowly, that’s the only way you’re going to have fun with it.” He snapped his fingers. “Hey, if you’d like, we could actually make it into an anime, if you want to watch it that way?”

“Could we do that?” asked the Devil. “Doesn’t that count against creative scarcity?”

“Eh,” said the Narrator. “I would argue to the Authority that it’s a form of format shifting, which is usually allowed. Translating things into different languages or formats … usually you can squeak by with it and not be considered part of the upper middle heavens by the preference clusters. Okay, I just checked, and it would be fine, but the quality is going to be a little bit lower than you’re used to. Or we could consume the media that’s going to come out of this thing, which I imagine there will be a lot of, and all that will probably pre-digest the games into something a bit more palatable. Or we could move to a place without creative scarcity.”

“Would you want to do that?” asked the Angel. “I thought you said you’d feel like there was no point in your hobby if you did that.”

“Eh,” said the Narrator. “I’m coming around to Valencia’s way of thinking, that life is in the living, and you shouldn’t just be doing things because they’re hard. I think I would still enjoy creation if I knew that I could just get an assistant to do the creation for me. I think it would still be worthwhile. And heck, we could just do a split heaven, where you can have all the anime or movies you want, and I could still toil away at my games and novels. Having the assistants mediate with the preference clusters might get annoying, but,” he shrugged. “I kind of feel like it’s been a long time coming.”

“Sweet,” said the Devil. She looked around. “Shit, we’re going to have to get ready to move, huh?” She eyed the couch, as though they would have to lift it. “Wait, what am I thinking? We’ll just hire movers.”

“Yeah, but how are we going to pay for them?” asked the Angel.

“I’ll take a look at the budget,” said the Narrator. “We might have to cut back on those well-oiled men.”

“Never,” said the Devil.

“You’re not getting rid of the well-oiled men, Juniper,” said the Angel.

“But thank you,” said the Devil. “For suggesting a move, I mean.”

“We appreciate it,” said the Angel.

The Narrator snapped his fingers. “And done.”

“Nice place,” said the Angel, looking around at the unchanged house. “Much more spacious than the last one.”

“Luxurious accommodations,” the Devil agreed.

“Good neighborhood, I guess,” said Juniper.

“Nice place to raise a family,” said the Angel.

There was a bit of silence between the three of them, as the two Fenns stared innocently out at the house. Eventually, the Narrator cleared his throat.

“That’s, um,” he said. “Something the two of you agreed on?”

“It’s something we very briefly discussed a few hours ago,” said the Devil, looking at the Angel.

“Some things would have to change, if we had a kid,” said the Narrator. “No walking around half-naked.” He looked down at their outfits. “I guess we could do some perception stuff and present differently to the kid than we do to each other.”

“Kids,” said the Devil. “One for each.”

“Yeah?” asked the Angel.

“It would also mean less time for other stuff,” said Narrator. “Less time for games. I mean, you can have a ‘spian take care of your kids, but if you’re going to do that, why even bother? And there are temp clones too, I guess.”

“Is he saying no?” asked the Angel.

“He’s doing a Juniper,” said the Devil.

“Ah, so he is,” nodded the Angel.

“I’m making sure that we consider it carefully and understand the impact that it would make on our lives,” said the Narrator. “Do I need to engage serious mode with you two?”

“Well we’re not deciding today, duh,” said the Angel, who always disliked serious mode. “We just moved our house.”

“We’ll give you time to think, and us time to think,” said the Devil, “And think about how we’re going to do it, and what it will mean, and we’ll petition the Authority to see whether we’ll even be allowed —”

“Already did that,” said the Narrator. “A hypothetical request was sent and answered, we’re fine to have kids.”

“And when did you do this?” asked the Angel.

“Just after you guys sent a letter off to Nellan,” said the Narrator.

“Well, be that as it may, we’re waiting,” said the Devil. “At least a day.”

“Such restraint,” said the Angel. “Such character growth.”

“He always did like our arcs,” said the Devil.

“Also, we were supposed to play Sexy Godsgame,” said the Angel.

“Yes,” said the Narrator, smiling. “One shitshow at a time.”

Nevermore

Chapter Notes

See the end of the chapter for notes

After ten years of heaven, it felt to Raven like everyone had moved on but her. She kept in touch with the entire party, with the exceptions of Bethel and the locus, occasionally meeting with them for a movie or game night, and sometimes one-on-one for coffee, or dinner, or something like that. They had twice-yearly trips together, though Raven had now missed a few. They rarely talked about Old Aerb, and most of the inside jokes were from the heavens, rather than the time before. There were trials and tribulations in the heavens, almost entirely social in one way or another, and all that was well and good, because the heavens simply didn’t allow for that much in the way of badness.

It felt like everyone had coupled off and had children. Grak had been the last of them, but eventually found a husband five years in, and had seven children, which seemed like a lot, especially in such a short span of time. Raven had briefly worried that it was too many, that they wouldn’t be able to give them attention, but it wasn’t like Grak or his husband had jobs, and the Authority didn’t grant children to people who wouldn’t help give them mostly happy lives. When they had the families together, which happened only rarely, the children outnumbered the adults by a wide margin.

Raven played the role of aunt, which she enjoyed, especially with the children who she could most closely identify with. There was a particular brand of child that dove into books, whether fiction or nonfiction, and Raven, as a former librarian and avid reader, took them under her wing as best she could, sometimes spending a fair chunk of her free time looking for recommendations for them, or at least reading through what they were reading. Some of the books were bespoke, created by the Authority for the precise purpose of pleasing one specific child, and Raven found those particularly interesting to read, since they had some insight into those specific children.

One of the Fenns had dubbed the group ‘Raven’s Readers’, which had, unfortunately, stuck. Raven would sometimes take the group to one of the many libraries around the heavens, and she did babysitting sometimes, which was always a ‘for fun’ type of thing, since the actual work could have easily been done by assistants or temp clones.

Raven spent two years immersed in a simulation, playing the role of a precocious sorceress who had to defeat a wickedly evil witch bent on subjugation of the Dragon Kingdom. She had consented to a memory wipe and memory implant, so that she believed she really was Madeline Melcore, and that it was all real. It was her chance to play at being Uther, or something like him. Surfacing from those adventures and getting her old memories back was incredibly pleasant, like welcoming a part of herself home, and it helped her to put some puzzle pieces into place with regards to her emotions, and also brought some context to her time with Uther.

Still, she spent at least part of her time in the past. She finally finished her book on Uther and his Knights, which had been in progress since she’d lived in Five Spires. She hadn’t expected all that much to come from sending it out, but perhaps because it was quite candid, or perhaps because so much of the information in it had been kept secret by the Authority due to privacy concerns, it was relatively well-read. Even years afterward, positive reception still came trickling in, and if there was any negative reception, her assistant quietly threw it in the metaphorical trash.

The year-long relationship with a false Uther had proven instructive, and the slow goodbye had allowed her to no longer pine for him, though there were occasional flashes of longing from time to time which she didn’t see fit to edit out. Never being completely at peace with a loss seemed, to her, human, and in the heavens, human was what she’d decided to be.

At least some of Raven’s time was spent on resurrections.

The Authority had three general methods of life creation: births, whole creation, and resurrection. In all cases, the Authority moved slowly and with somewhat undue deliberation, most of which (it claimed) was the result of interviews with what it thought would be the affected parties. Even beyond that, the Authority wouldn’t “create life” simply because you wanted it to, or simply because the created life would be happy, it needed something a bit more. Saying simply “I want everyone resurrected who would be happy being resurrected” was not enough.

It was, in Raven’s view, the wrong way to go about things, and one of the only ways that she had a concrete disagreement with Juniper about the shape of the heavens. They’d had the argument in person only once. Juniper had said, ‘But by your logic, the Authority should be instantiating every possible person who has ever or could ever have existed’, and Raven had shouted, ‘Yes, exactly!’, which on reflection she wasn’t entirely sure she believed. There were some people who believed that, and she was friends (or at least acquaintances) with some of them, given that there was coordination and discussion among those who cared about resurrection. Then there were the people Raven could only think of as fanatics, who wanted endless fields of wireheaded brains, though most of them weren’t particularly involved in doing anything about it besides complaining to (or about) the Authority, or arguing in terms of the mathematics of happiness and infinities. Besides, there were mind-meltingly enormous fields of wireheaded brains, ones which had been purpose-built to experience optimal pleasure under different definitions of ‘pleasure’, stripped down so there were no memories, no personality, no identity. Raven had spent an afternoon going to see bits and pieces of them, to get some sense of what people wanted, and hadn’t really seen the attraction, which she thought might have been the point of the Authority showing people those fields. The Authority didn’t seem to particularly favor wireheading, and would argue against it, which Raven appreciated. Raven favored resurrection because it was real and tangible in a way that the other stuff was not.

Resurrection was easy if it was someone close to you, someone you had an attachment to, some love for, or who would measurably improve your life, especially if it seemed like they would have liked to have been resurrected. Unfortunately, part of the Authority’s argument against resurrection was that it had no informed consent to resurrect anyone unless they explicitly said so, only inferred consent, and no informed consent to read their mind to get consent. Again, Raven could understand why Juniper had set things up this way, but didn’t inherently agree with him. Her pleas to the Authority had not been met with the Authority agreeing that it was wrong, so it was a matter of values that they simply did not share.

All the easy resurrections had been done in the first year, if not the first month. People got back friends, family members, and loved ones. The entirety of Uther’s Knights had been resurrected, including Everett, who was de-aged and had taken up painting in the span of four hours. Raven met with them from time to time, and reminisced about the old days, though they were missing their most important member, a man who the Authority would not recreate except in ‘spian form, and then with serious limitations, not taking from his memories. Raven agreed, in this case, that there was nothing like consent, and that consent was important.

The resurrections had chained backwards. Someone would resurrect their parent, who would resurrect their parent, who would resurrect their parent, and it would continue on like that. But these chains left incomplete gaps, either people who no one really wanted resurrected, or whose family line had died out, or who had been clear about preferring to stay dead.

That left the hard resurrections.

“This person has no connection to you,” the Authority would say. “That you would prefer them to be alive instead of dead is not sufficient. They have not consented in any meaningful capacity to a resurrection. There is no way of knowing whether they would meet baseline happiness within the society that we can provide. We are not in the business of creating life on mere whims. We do not believe the dead have a right to life, just as we do not believe those who do not exist have a right to existence.”

The Total Resurrection Working Group had thought up a clever solution to this, which was to make a self-edit such that they truly, desperately wanted the individual resurrected. The Authority had smiled and said ‘nice try’, as it often did when someone found a seeming contradiction in its values or a seemingly clever workaround to its rules. This was particularly the case when someone attempted to become a ‘utility monster’ whose demands could not be ignored. The Authority was good at ignoring that kind of thing, it seemed. Raven imagined that it was a lesson Juniper had learned from tabletop games, but perhaps she was just seeing things.

Instead, resurrection had to be approached the more difficult way, which was to honestly care without motivation about the particular deceased, one at a time. Honestly, it was a solution that shouldn’t have worked, given that it didn’t seem all that much different from just directly editing in the caring, but the Authority, for ineffable reasons, had decided to allow it. Raven had asked Juniper about it, and he had been a bit baffled, but suggested that perhaps it was a form of make-work, or that it was about the energy put into it. The Authority wouldn’t trivially resurrect anyone, in the same way that it wouldn’t trivially create anyone, but if you were willing to put in the time and effort, the Authority would oblige.

Raven’s current target was a boy who had died in his early twenties during the Third Overfell War, approximately twenty thousand years ago. He’d been picked as a target by her assistant, who thought that she would find him easy: the assistants were an enormous help, and the project likely would have been nearly impossible without them. The boy in question was notable among those thousands who had died for having kept a fairly extensive journal, a rarity at the time. The Authority was unwilling to spy on the private lives of people in the long-distant past, and especially unwilling to spy on people on behalf of others, but made exceptions for books or letters, and for journals when there was some presumption that they might have wanted these things read, and sometimes for things which were ‘public’ even if no one had imagined that the ‘public’ in question would include far future researchers.

Thus Raven was allowed to read through a recreated journal penned by Shermarin Cartier. This needed to be done slowly, with deliberation, because the Authority paid attention to ‘cheats’ like immediate reading and integration of a historical text. Raven didn’t mind, and didn’t have all that much interest in ‘Authority games’, as they were called. She liked reading, and the kinds of things the Authority picked out for her were usually fairly compelling. It was that compellingness that allowed the resurrection to take place, reaching back through time and pulling someone into the present at the moment of their death.

“I’d like to resurrect Shermarin Cartier,” Raven said idly once she’d finished another entry, this one concerning some personal drama with the other soldiers over something improper they’d said. Shermarin had explicitly refused to repeat the improper phrase, but it had concerned a medic, whose honor he felt it necessary to defend. There was something chivalrous about him, Raven had decided. It was important to see the good in people.

“The request is denied,” said her assistant, who had picked the name Lil.

Aside from the reproduction of the journal, Raven had a number of other things from the era, and she had transported herself to a facsimile of the area where Shermarin had been camped. As she flipped a page, the scene changed, and she found herself in a familiar house, one which Shermarin had written about before. It was, so far as she could tell, some kind of plantation at a crucially important position with regards to the war which had been commandeered early on.

She read on, giving the words her full focus, trying to put herself in Shermarin’s shoes. Early on in this endeavor, she had tried altering her body so that she might better get a feel for who the person was, but it was more of a distraction than anything. Instead, she put herself into period-appropriate clothing. The entry from the house was fairly brief, largely just reporting on the mundanities of the life of an officer, but Shermarin wrote with an attention to detail that Raven found laudable. He had wanted to have a record of his time, something that could be kept for later, and during that era, notebooks had been fairly expensive.

“I’d like to resurrect Shermarin Cartier,” said Raven, once she was finished with the entry. It wasn’t necessary to ask every time, you could simply put in a standing request, but Raven liked to ask every now and then, because it helped her keep focus on why she was doing this.

“The request is accepted,” said Lil.

“Really?” asked Raven, closing the journal. “Good.”

They were whisked to the resurrection chamber, a specific room of Raven’s house. Lil had already changed it to be the kind of place that Shermarin would be most comfortable with, done in approximately the correct style. The resurrection was different for everyone, and depended on what would work best for them. Raven was allowed to watch, in part because this resurrection was ‘for’ her, but she typically kept her involvement minimal.

The body formed in an instant, and a moment later, Shermarin woke up. He was dressed in period-appropriate clothing, a styled cloak that covered most of him, and layers beneath that. He sat up and looked around.

Lil had changed, putting herself into period clothing as well, but beyond that, she’d grown a bit taller, more busty, and with features that mimicked what Raven knew to be true of the era and region that Shermarin was from.

“Shermarin Cartier,” said Lil, in Vorslock, the language of Shermarin’s time and place. “You died on the battlefield in the course of the Third Overfell War. A very long time has passed since then, and you have been resurrected. Do you consent to this?”

This wasn’t merely a formality. From time to time, someone would say that they did not, and the Authority would inquire further. The Authority did not unmake lightly, and would try other solutions or explanations first, but some people simply did not want to live in the world they found themselves waking up in. Raven didn’t think that would be true of Shermarin, but it was hard to tell from just someone’s writing.

“I do,” said Shermarin. “You … brought me back?”

“Yes,” nodded Lil. “The world has changed since your time. There is no longer any scarcity. People are free to remake their reality as they wish. We anticipate that you might wish to resurrect a number of people from your time who also died. It would be better for us to get started on that now, if you would like.”

“I’ve seen enough of this,” said Raven. Her speech had not been audible to Shermarin.

Instantly, she was whisked away to a different part of the house, and from experience, Shermarin had been split off into his own reality. He would likely allow Lil consent to read his mind, and more resurrections would chain off of his. Raven had helped to cause the resurrection of hundreds, perhaps thousands.

And still, there would always be more.

“This endeavor has stopped making you feel good,” said Lil. She leaned against a counter. She’d gotten more personality as the time went on, and a kind of endearing laziness. They were in the study, which had an enormous library opening up above it, an inverted cone of books so large there were birds flying around in clouds. It gave the whole thing a flair she really liked. The birds had little cubbies, so they wouldn’t affect the books, and they were trained to poop in places that Lil would clean out.

“I could give the old hedonic treadmill a kick,” sighed Raven. “I’m surprised I was able to care enough to pass the imaginary threshold for a resurrection.”

“Mmm,” said Lil. “I’m not sure you’ll be able to do it again, and you know I hate to see people grinding away at something just because they think they should.”

“So resurrect everyone,” said Raven. “No, you know what, I don’t want to have that conversation again.”

“Neither do I,” said Lil. “You know, the TRWG isn’t going to miss you if you take a break.”

“I know,” said Raven. “It’s always been your opinion that I’m doing this because I can’t resurrect Uther. I’m starting to think you might be right.”

“Of course I’m right,” said Lil. “But Uther isn’t even dead, he’s just off beyond the reach of the Authority.”

Raven sighed again and looked up at the cone of books. It was pretty, but a bit pointless. She was going to have to replace it with something else at some point, perhaps something that didn’t remind her so much of the Infinite Library.

“When’s my next meeting?” asked Raven.

“Are we including the TRWG?” asked Lil. “Because I can have a regretful notice sent to them right now.”

“Fine,” said Raven. “A break of, let’s say, a month.”

“Then your next scheduled meeting is with Amaryllis and Juniper in six hours. You were invited to dinner and I accepted on your behalf.” Lil smiled. She had partial access to Raven’s mind, and authority to accept or reject a whole host of things on Raven’s behalf. It was very helpful given the moderate level of fame that Raven had, and the way that social obligations seemed to multiply if left unchecked.

“See if Arthur is available,” said Raven.

“He’s still on extended leave,” replied Lil.

Raven tapped her foot. “Fine, tell me how to best fill the time, temporary full mind access, five minute interval.” She was stingy with her mind, in a way that was common among people who had lived through the Second Empire. She couldn’t say that it was a better way to live, but she hadn’t worked up the courage to make a modification so that she wouldn’t care. Eventually, she might do that. There was a trend throughout the heavens toward giving more permissions and rising to higher levels, and Raven didn’t think that she would buck that trend for long.

“I think it’s high time you accepted matchmaking,” said Lil.

Raven sighed. “And I suppose you’re telling me that because you know that this time I’m inclined to finally give in?”

“Of course,” nodded Lil. “The best candidate is available now, and would be ready for a date in ten minutes, duration of, say, an hour unless things go horribly or very well.”

“But you know in advance,” said Raven.

“We can guess,” replied Lil. “We don’t have permanent full mind access on either of you, and both of you have explicitly barred advanced prognostics. Obviously if we expected it to go poorly, we wouldn’t set it up, but with the information we have, —”

“Fine,” said Raven. “Get me something to wear, make sure I’m clean, pick the venue.”

“Would you rather I pick something he would like, or something that best represents you?” asked Lil.

“Make me the best version of myself,” said Raven. “Irrespective of what he likes.”

Ten minutes later, Raven was transformed (black dress, earrings, makeup, ample but tasteful cleavage) and sitting on a patio that jutted out over a lake that was filled with lily pads and glowing flowers. It was around dusk, and there were lights up on poles to give soft illumination, along with a pair of candles in the center of the table. There were other couples with their own tables, talking in murmured conversations. There was no telling whether they were ‘spians or not, aside from asking, which Raven wasn’t inclined to do. She didn’t normally eat, but a waiter stopped by with a menu and filled her glass with a dark red wine, so Raven had decided to get in the swing of things and get a bit tipsy. She hadn’t accepted matchmaking before, and the kinds of things that people said about it — well, there were trillions of people in the heavens, and the Authority might have limited itself for the sake of privacy, but with the kinds of consent people had given it, it could pick out dozens of people who might almost instantly become the love of your life.

She first saw him as a waiter led him to their table. It wasn’t love at first sight. He didn’t have the muscular build that Raven normally went for, nor the same commanding presence. He was tall and lanky, and showed a deference to the waiter that she found a bit surprising. He wore glasses, certainly an affectation, and had an aloof smile as he sat down.

“Hello,” he said as he sat down. “I suppose this is a date.”

“I suppose so,” said Raven, raising an eyebrow. So far, she had no idea why the Authority had picked him. “Sorry, I didn’t request a dossier on you.”

“Oh, I didn’t ask for one of you either,” he said. “Better to get to know each other in the flesh, so to speak.” He reached his hand across the table, avoiding the candles. “Clarke Rinsome.”

“Raven Masters,” Raven replied as she shook his hand. He had a strong, firm grip, and that was the first moment she felt anything like attraction.

He faltered. “Oh,” he said. “I … I was going to say that I’m a big fan, but actually I’ve only read your book about Uther and his Knights. I’m sure there are people who are big fans, the kinds of people who devote a lot of time and attention to you, specifically. There’s probably a fan club somewhere, I would reckon, or people who go to visit places you mentioned, or, ah. Well, you know what I’m saying, surely. I’m not a big fan, but I read your book, and looked to see if you had written another. That’s the level of fan I am.”

“Then I suppose you have me at a disadvantage,” said Raven. There was something that she liked about his rambling. Too many people had sanded themselves down or rounded out their sharp corners. That he was capable of an awkward monologue like that spoke to a deep conviction in the integrity of the self. There was something bold about that. The more she thought about it, the more charmed she found herself being.

“Well,” said Clarke. “I suppose the short version of my entire life,” he paused, looking up for a moment. “Prior to the end of the world, I was an architect. Outside of that, I was, well … I made little scenes. There’s a particular tradition among the Akishi, pendai, where you have a small plot of soil in a tray perhaps a foot or two across, and fill it with mosses, grasses, small plants, things like that all made to look like life but reduced in size, sometimes with a miniature sculpted tree or two. Then there’s usually a single human element. Most people did little figures walking down a path, that was traditional, but I added tiny architecturally correct houses, which I had learned to make for my job, and left the people implied.”

“Oh,” said Raven. Her heart had started to beat a bit faster as she realized what he was talking about. “I do that too. Or, something similar. Mine is called bonsai, it’s mostly about the small trees. Or, entirely, I suppose, in the traditional form.”

There was some joy in discovering this area of commonality together, and they spoke about their respective hobbies for quite some time, both the areas of overlap and the substantial differences, where they could find them. In bonsai there was typically one preferred angle to view a tree from, and the same was true in pendai, a special spot from which the view was ‘best’. Yet there was also a way in which the aesthetics diverged: bonsai was largely refined and stylized, while pendai was rustic and wild, a cultivated sense of the overgrown and untamed.

“But you said you put buildings in,” said Raven.

“Oh, that’s the um, well, the tension that I like,” he replied. He took a sip of his wine. “When I had one properly set up, I would get this frisson from looking at it. And because they were, after all, living things that needed to be tended to, it wasn’t simply a matter of a scene that I was looking at, like a painting. I knew that the feeling of a building on the verge of being overgrown was, in some sense, real.”

“But the way you speak of it, you don’t do that anymore?” asked Raven.

“Heaven is where hobbies go to die,” Clarke replied with a sheepish smile. “I suppose at this point I have to confess that I’ve spent quite a bit of my time in deep dives, with a shallow clone to answer obligations. There’s a part of me that feels a bit guilty about that.” There was, again, that feeling of being with someone who was confident enough in himself to allow that guilt to remain a part of him. Raven liked it.

“I was in two years,” said Raven, momentarily placing a hand on her chest. She’d drained a glass of wine already, and it was doing its work. “What did you go for?” Once the question was out, she realized that she was going to have to answer in return.

“I’ve been in three so far,” he replied. He was measuring his words, just a bit. “In the first — it’s hard to describe without going into detail, but there were nested worlds, not quite infinitely many of them, but it was about gods, I suppose, or gods in relation to each other. I have to think that the pendai were an inspiration. I lived in a picturesque little house with woodlands around me, and a small garden to feed myself with. It was a plot of land owned by a man for whom I was a plaything, one of several he owned. But I, too, had several plots of land with their own people living on them.”

“How long were you there for?” asked Raven.

“Oh, a year, maybe a bit more,” replied Clarke with a sigh. “I had a magical gift to shrink and to grow, which allowed me to explore up and down the layers. There was always someone higher, and always someone lower, and the higher levels caused a terror in me, because a hundred levels up the relative size would be … well, immense, capable of instantly crushing all smaller worlds.” He paused. “I think that the point of it was for me to become at peace with the idea of god.”

“And did that work?” asked Raven.

“It’s hard to say,” replied Clarke. “I think that my emotions have stilled, but my thoughts are still complicated.”

“And the second?” asked Raven.

“Oh, that one was easier,” he replied. “It was a simple little life, one of exploration, trekking into uncharted lands, meeting new people, avoiding bad fates. If I had to take a lesson from it, I think that it would be that there’s always something new to explore, always some new experience. That one was three years, all told, all of them packed with new sights and sounds.”

“Do you always have them give lessons?” asked Raven.

“Oh, never,” said Clarke. “No, each time, I’ve asked for something that I would like. If the Authority thinks that involves lessons, who am I to argue? And I can sense that you’ll ask about the third, but I don’t want to talk about myself at length, so you’ll have to tell me about yours first.”

“Ah,” said Raven. “It was nothing special. I mean, it was … well, two years, shallow clone to take requests and a deep clone for important things. The dive was about being a hero, fighting against — if you read the book, then I suppose this will make sense — the Dark King, or close enough that I don’t think there’s all that meaningful of a difference. She was a witch, and I was the plucky young hero with outrageously powerful magical abilities.” She shrugged. “It feels embarrassing. Juvenile.”

Clarke chuckled. “Not at all. I think we all seek something like that, a fantasy of being the best, being a hero.”

“Have you heard of the Total Resurrection Working Group?” asked Raven. Clarke shook his head no. “They’re this group that wants to bring every single person who has ever died back to life. I worked with them for quite a while, trying to petition the Authority in order to get people back. I guess when I think about it, I’ve already made the decision to stop doing that. The project is enormous, and the further we get into it, the more questionable it gets. There are people who literally no one wants alive, and the group is committed to getting them resurrections as a matter of dogma.” She shook her head. “I think I was doing it because … well, because I wanted to be a hero. I wanted to do good.”

“And did you?” asked Clarke. “You managed to bring people back who otherwise wouldn’t have had a chance?”

“I did,” said Raven. “One every two or three days for seven years or so, taking many breaks, of course. I brought back just a little more than a thousand, I think, though I never tracked metrics that much. I enjoyed it, especially as a student of history. But … I don’t know.” She shook her head. “I think perhaps I need another run at a deep dive, one that’s meant to teach me something. It’s a more palatable form of therapy, maybe, than just having an edit done.”

“Oh,” said Clarke. “Then you would be gone for quite some time.”

“I would,” said Raven, suddenly aware of herself again. The makeup and the dress felt like a promise that she wasn’t going to keep. “Sorry.”

Clarke gave her a wan smile. “Well, not a mark of a good date if partway through, your date makes the decision to leave for a few years.”

“It’s not meant as a mark against you,” said Raven. “I’m just … in a transition, I think. It’s the reason that I agreed to this date in the first place.”

“Ah, well,” said Clarke. “Not meant to be then, I suppose.” He still smiled. “Are you really decided then? Just like that?”

“I don’t know,” said Raven. “I’ll think about it, make some arrangements, and set my affairs in order.” She hesitated. “Sorry.” She hesitated again. “You know, it’s probably too forward of me, but … if you wanted to, we could take the dive together.”

A smile spread across Clarke’s face. “But I suppose we would have to negotiate?”

“What’s there to negotiate?” asked Raven. “We could just have the Authority handle it. I’m fine with prognostics if I’m not burdened with the knowledge ahead of time.”

“I suppose I am too,” said Clarke. “You know, it is the mark of a good date if partway through, your date suggests that perhaps you spend a few years together.” He was beaming at her, happy but also amused. Raven found that enthusiasm charming as well. “But as for negotiation … well, what relation would we be to each other, in this dive?”

Raven shrugged. “I suppose I would allow the Authority to handle that, if you would be fine with it.” She blushed.

Clarke slowly nodded. Perhaps he was thinking what she was thinking, which was that the Authority had set them up on a date, putting them together from trillions of possible matches. In a deep dive together, it was almost certain that the scenario would have at least some element of romance, especially given that it was something Raven could feel a keen longing for.

“Perhaps we should stop here then,” he said. “Not that I didn't have a nice time, but … well, the next time we meet, when our real selves meet, we’ll have a lot to talk about, and we’ll understand each other better.”

“I think I’d like that,” said Raven. “I’m comfortable enough to take the dive.”

“Then I’ll see you in … what, two years?” he asked. “If that’s not too hopeful?”

“Two or three,” Raven shrugged.

There was, again, a warm smile on his face. He extended his glass to her for an impromptu toast. “To new worlds.”

“And to new adventures within them,” she agreed.

Chapter End Notes

This is the the end of Worth the Candle, and now we bid these characters a happy rest of their lives.

If you'd like to read/follow my next work, This Used to be About Dungeons, a fluffy slice-of-life palate cleanser, that can be found over on RoyalRoad.

All your other usual links follow:

Discuss on reddit r/rational
Join my subreddit
Chat on my Discord
Visit my website